<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The plaine mans pilgrimage. Or iovrney tovvards heaven Wherein if hee walke carefully he may attaine to euerlasting life. By W.W.</title>
            <author>Webster, William, treatise writer.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 233 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101835</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837638</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837638</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1015:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The plaine mans pilgrimage. Or iovrney tovvards heaven Wherein if hee walke carefully he may attaine to euerlasting life. By W.W.</title>
                  <author>Webster, William, treatise writer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 172 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by G. Eld, and are to be sould at his house in Fleet-lane at the signe of the Printers Presse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.W. = William Webster.</note>
                  <note>Title within decorative border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1975:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1975:1"/>
            <p>THE PLAINE MANS PIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRIMAGE. <hi>OR</hi> IOVRNEY TO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARDS HEAVEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein if hee walke</hi> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he may attaine to <hi>euerlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. Imprinted by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> and are to be ſould at his houſe in Fleet-lane at the ſigne of the Printers Preſſe. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1975:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1975:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Contents of this</hi> Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chapter</hi> 1. FIrſt to ſerue <hi>God</hi> with true <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Three ſpeciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents to be followed.</item>
               <item>Firſt, A ſpeedy going forward in Chriſtian Religion.</item>
               <item>Secondly, out of Prouerbs 23.26. <hi>My Sonne giue me thy heart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>Moſes</hi> praier. Pſal. 19.12. <hi>Teach vs O Lord to number our daies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. The benefit of the renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man.</item>
               <item>Secondly, The nouriſhment of
<pb facs="tcp:1975:3"/>the renued Man.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, Out of the 14. of <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ver. 6. <hi>I am the way, the Truth and the Life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap 4. <hi>The path for a Chriſtian to walke in.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. Three Chriſtian duties to be obſerued.</item>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>Reioyce euermore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>Pray continually.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, <hi>In al things giue thanks.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Laſtly</hi> 4. Admonitions.</item>
               <item>1. <hi>Quench not the Spirit.</hi> 2. <hi>Deſpiſe not propheſying.</hi> 3. <hi>Try all things.</hi> 4. <hi>Abſtaine from all appearance of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1975:3"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, I haue not compiled this worke for the delight of thy worldly mind, but for a preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thy Pilgrimage toward Heauen, that is, to walke with God as Enoch did: For whoſoeuer entreth into conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with himſelfe of his humane nature, ſhall eaſily perceiue that it is addicted to imitation. And though indeed wee ſhould liue by <hi>lawes,</hi> and not <hi>examples,</hi> yet by common experience we find, that <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1975:4"/>mooue more then <hi>lawes:</hi> Therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> what ſoeuer thou art (high or low) iudge charitably of this my worke. Thus wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee (good reader) not only to look on the title, but reade it to the end, and I doubt not but thou ſhalt be preſerued from prophaneneſse Idolatry, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VVILLIAM</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1975:4"/>
            <head>The Pilgrims iourney to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heauen.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S GOD hath created all things for his owne ſake, and man beeing head of all, is made Lord and Ruler of them, and ſo conſequently they to ſerue him, hee (I ſay) is to conſider and to counſell with God and his owne conſcience, why and wherefore, and to what end he was created, and ſent hither into his world, what to doe, and wherein to beſtow his dayes, &amp;c then ſhall hee finde, that for no other cauſe, matter or end, but onely to ſerue God with true faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this life, and by that ſeruice to enioy heauen, and euerlaſting ſaluation in the life to come, this was the conſideration of our redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, fore told by <hi>Zacharie,</hi> before we were redeemed, that beeing deliuered from the hands of our enemies, ſhould ſerue God in holyneſſe and righteouſneſſe, all the dayes of our liues. Of this conſideration, do enſue two conſequents to be obſerued, whereof the firſt is, that ſeeing our end and finall cauſe of beeing in this world, is to ſerue God, and ſo to worke our ſaluation with feare and trembling, and whatſoeuer thing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1975:5"/>wee doe, or beſtow our time in, which either is contrary, or not profitable to this, that is, to ſerue God, it is vanity and loſt labour, and will turne vs in time to griefe and repentance, for that is not the matter for which wee came into the world, nor whereof wee ſhall be demanded any accompt of. Secondly, ſeeing that our buſineſſe and affaires in this world, is to ſerue our maker with true faith and repentance, and ſo to ſaue our owne ſoules, and that all other earthly creatures are but here to ſerue our vſes, and to that end onely are they ſent of God: We ſhould therefore bee indifferent to all theſe creatures, as to riches or pouerty, to health or ſickneſſe, to honour or contempt, &amp;c. And wee ſhould defire but ſo much or little of them as were beſt for vs toward the attainment of our ſaid end and but pretended: for whoſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth, ſeeketh, or vſeth theſe creatures more then for this, runneth from the end for which he came hither.</p>
               <p>And for that the moſt part of all that are in this world, not onely Infidels, but alſo Chriſtians doe runne amiſſe in this point, and doe not take care of that affaire and buſineſſe for which alone they were created, and placed here in this world. Hence it is that Chriſt and his holy Saints, both before the appearing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1975:5"/>in the fleſh, and after, haue ſpoken ſo hardly and ſeuerely of the very ſmall number that ſhall bee ſaued, euen among Chriſtians, and haue vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered certaine ſpeeches which ſeeme very ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous to fleſh and bloud, and to ſuch as are moſt touched therein, as among other things, that a greedy louer of this world cannot bee ſaued. 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 29. <hi>verſe.</hi> and thoſe that greedily deſire to bee rich, fall into many temptations, and noyſome luſts, which draw them into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and perdition, and that ſuch rich men doe enter as hardly into heauen, as a Cammell through a Needles eye, and the reaſon of which manner of ſpeach doth ſtand in this, that a rich worldling, attending with his induſtry and care to heape vp riches, (as the faſhion is) cannot attend to that for which hee came into this world, and ſo conſequently can neuer attaine heauen, except God worke a myracle, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by cauſe him to ſpend out his riches to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his ſoule, and by grace to call him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Goſpell (as often hee doth) and ſo doe make leſſe the Cammell in ſuch ſort as hee may paſſe the Needles eye, whereof wee haue an example in the Goſpell by <hi>Zacheus,</hi> who beeing a very rich man, and a great ſinner, preſently vppon the calling of Chriſt, hee beeing in a Figge Tree, and ſo entring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1975:6"/>into his houſe, but much more as appeareth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his heart, whereby hee receiued faith, and vpon the ſame did reſolue himſelfe to change his former life, touching riches, and at one blow to begin withall, gaue away halfe of his goods vnto the poore, and for the reſt, made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, that whoſoeuer had any wrong at his hands, hee ſhould come and receiue foure times recompence for it, and ſo by this conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hee was made fitte to enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, for thoſe things which are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to men, are poſſible with God.</p>
               <p>Further, let vs conſider and behold the great multitude of all ſorts of people vpon earth, and ſee what their traffique and conuerſations are, and whether they ſeeke after thoſe things, for the which they came into this world, for few of them that ſeeke, you ſhall finde thouſands, who ſpend their time in ſeeking after vanities, as worldly honour, glory, riches, and all fleſhly and carnall comforts, and contentments, which are nothing but vanities, and the capitall eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>O yee ſonnes of men, ſaith <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 4. Why loue yee vanity, and ſeeke after lyes. Alſo will you haue the lamentation of ſuch vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate men as thus vainely and fooliſhly haue ſpent their golden dayes. Theſe are their owne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1975:6"/>words recorded by Scripture. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5.7. in the end of their liues ſaying, <hi>Wee haue wearied our ſelues in the way of wickedneſſe, and diſtruction, yea wee haue gone through tedious deſerts, but as for the way of the Lord, wee haue not regarded it: what good hath pride brought vs, or what profit hath the pompe of riches brought vs. All theſe are paſſed away like a ſhadow, and as a Poſt that paſſeth by, and wee are conſumed in our owne iniquities:</hi> This is the lamentable complaint of ſuch men as runne amiſſe, and followed a wrong courſe in their actions of this life, theſe are they which purſued riches, honour, pompe, and ſuch like va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and forgat that great and weighty buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for which they were ſent, theſe are they who were eſteemed happy men in this world, and thought to run to a moſt fortunate courſe, in that they heaped vp much riches together, and aduanced themſelues, and their poſterity, and families, to great dignities, and ſo become gorgious, glorious, and dreadfull to others, and finally obteined whatſoeuer their luſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence deſired, this made them ſeeme bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the worldly thoughts, and the way they ranne to be moſt proſperous and happy, but the Scriptures of God are wholy and manifeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch, and thundreth many woes and curſes againſt them, for why hath God giuen
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1975:7"/>reaſon and vnderſtanding vnto men, but to ſerue him, and praiſe him vpon earth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo ſoone as wee come to yeares of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and begin to vnderſtand, wee ſhould then begin a new life, and ſerue him, whom all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe ſerue with vs, or elſe our vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is vaine.</p>
               <p>Now therefore becauſe the militant Church here vpon earth are but Pilgrims and ſtrangers, not hauing here in this worldly wilderneſſe, any certaine place of abode, but trauaileth for one eternall in heauen, and hauing dayly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enemies to encounter withall, therefore it ſtandeth euery child of God vpon, and thoſe that loue their owne ſaluation, to haue a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, and a true examination of their liues and conuerſations, leaſt they bee drawne away from their true ſeruice and obedience which they owe vnto their God and Creator, and ſo follow the intiſements of their enemies, to bee drawne away from God.</p>
               <p>Now that wee may the better voyde the danger of our enemies, wee are to diſtinguiſh truly betweene ſpirituall carefulneſſe, and worldly carefulneſſe, and how can wee haue a truer Iudge for the triall thereof, then our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt himſelfe, who hath deciphred it in the ſtory of <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1975:7"/>
               <p>For when our Sauiour Chriſt entered into the Village where <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> dwelt, and ſo into the houſe, then they ſhewing their thankfull mindes to Chriſt againe, the one by receiuing him into her houſe, and the other by enterteining him into her heart, as he was God hee was receiued of <hi>Mary,</hi> and as hee was man, hee was receiued of <hi>Martha,</hi> but <hi>Mary</hi> made choiſe of the better part, and was preferred before her ſiſter, and although the care of <hi>Martha</hi> in entertaining of Chriſt is not to bee miſliked: yet <hi>Maryes</hi> diligence in hearing his doctrine, is of purpoſe preferred, to teach vs, that it is much better with <hi>Mary</hi> to ſtudy in the word, and ſo firſt to ſeeke the kingdome of God, then with <hi>Martha</hi> to labour in the world, and ſo to neglect that heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and yet notwithſtanding ſuch is the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of this ruſty age, that our greateſt care is to prouide for this preſent life, as the riche man in <hi>Luke</hi> the twelfth, inlarged his Barnes wherein to put his ſtore for many yeares, but wee neuer, or very late, remember to prouide for the life to come, like that other rich man in <hi>Luke</hi> 16. that neuer thought of heauen till hee was tormented in hell.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1975:8"/>
               <p>Theſe ſiſters were godly women, and both earneſt fauourers of Ieſus Chriſt, and yet in the manner of their deuotion, there is ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that the wordly affection of the one, may in ſome ſort be miſliked in reſpect of the godly exerciſe and practiſe of the other. <hi>Martha</hi> is fore incombered with much ſeruing, but <hi>Mary</hi> is at tentiue to heare the word of God: for if it be a matter of coſt or trouble, if they cannot heare the word preached without ſome hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to their worldly buſineſſe, and ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary charge to their purſſe, then like the Gadarinites they are content to take their leaue of Chriſt and his word, and had rather looſe that heauenly pearle, then they would part from their worldly pelfe, but let Chriſtians learne firſt to ſeeke the kingdome of God, and his righteouſneſſe, and then to prouide for the things of this life.</p>
               <p>Now while <hi>Mary</hi> was carefull for the food of the ſoule, <hi>Martha</hi> was curious to prouide food for the body, her greateſt care was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine Chriſt, and to make him good cheere, to teſtiſie her thankfull minde vnto him, that had raiſed her brother <hi>Lazarus</hi> from death to life, therefore hee was worthy to bee well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained.</p>
               <p>It was well done therefore of <hi>Martha,</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1975:8"/>ſhew her thankfull minde vnto Chriſt, but it was not well done at that time, to ſhew her ſelfe thankfull in that manner, for ſhee was to heare the word, for at that time Chriſt preached the word, it was then no time for her to ſpend in other affaires, and to neglect the greateſt affaire, which is the meanes of our ſaluation, there is a time wherein wee ought to labour in our vocation, and a time wherein wee ought to heare the word. And as wee may not vtterly neglect our lawfull callings to follow Sermons, ſo muſt wee not beſtow the Sabaoth which is conſecrated to the ſeruice of God, in following the workes of our vocation. All things haue their appointed time (ſaith the VViſe man) <hi>Eccle.</hi> 3. and euery thing is ſeemely in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient ſeaſon, but when things are done pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterouſly, and out of order there followeth confuſion.</p>
               <p>Although <hi>Martha</hi> did not heare Chriſt, yet ſhee did labour for Chriſt: many in theſe dayes will neither labour for Chriſt, nor heare Chriſt, but as the Iſraelites were weary of their iorney in the wilderneſſe, and loathed that heauenly Manna, ſo theſe men are weary of euery godly exerciſe, and are cloyed with the word of God.</p>
               <p>Yet behold how our Sauiour Chriſt reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>Martha,</hi> and excuſeth <hi>Mary,</hi> for when
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1975:9"/>
                  <hi>Martha</hi> complained of her ſiſter to Chriſt, that ſhee would not helpe her, and ſeeming after a ſort to blame our Sauiour for winking at it, requiring him to ſee the matter amended, but Chriſt reprooueth <hi>Marthas</hi> curioſitie, and then excuſeth, yea commendeth <hi>Maryes</hi> care, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto her, <hi>Martha, Martha,</hi> thou careſt and art troubled about many things, but one thing is needfull. <hi>Mary</hi> hath choſen the better part, which ſhall not bee taken from her, one thing is neceſſary ſaith Chriſt, and what is that one thing, euen to heare the word of God prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, which is the power of God to ſaluation to euery one that beleeueth.</p>
               <p>A man may better want all things, then that one needfull thing, and yet wee deſire all other things, and neglect that one thing which is ſo needfull: this one thing hath <hi>Mary</hi> choſen, and therefore hath choſen the better part. <hi>Marthas</hi> part is good, becauſe it prouideth for this life, but <hi>Maries</hi> part is better, becauſe it leadeth to eternall life, it is good to bee occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied about our calling to get our liuing, but it is better to bee occupied in hearing the word, which is able to ſaue our ſoules: As the head and the foote are both needfull in the body, ſo <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Martha</hi> are both needfull in a common-wealth, therefore God hath giuen
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1975:9"/>two vocations vnto man, the one earthly, by his labour, as hee ſayd vnto <hi>Adam, Thou ſhalt eate thy bread with ſweat of thy browes:</hi> the other is heauenly, as is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſerue the Lord thy God in holyneſſe and righteouſneſſe, all the dayes of thy life,</hi> ſo there is an actiue life which conſiſteth in the practiſing of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this life, wherein man ſheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee like himſelfe: and there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue life which conſiſteth in the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diuine and heauenly things, wherein man ſheweth himſelfe to bee like the Angells: for they which labour in their temporall voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doe liue like men, but they which labour in ſpirituall matters, liue like Angels; when theſe heare the word, then GOD ſpeaketh vnto them, and when they pray, they ſpeake vnto God, ſo that there is a continuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene GOD and them, becauſe they are continually exerciſed in hearing and praying.</p>
               <p>As for all other things, whether they bee honors, promotions, pleaſures, riches, and what not, they ſerue onely for maintenance of this preſent life, which is ſo ſhort, and ſubiect to mutability, but the word of God, is the food of the ſoule, the bread of life, that immortall ſeed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1975:10"/>which bringeth forth vnto eternall life: Let the word of God therefore be precious vnto vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, becauſe it is ſo permanent.</p>
               <p>Againe the ſpirituall minds are heauenly and looke vp, becauſe their minds are aboue, where their treaſure is, but the carnall minds are earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and looke downe like beaſts, becauſe their treaſure i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> below. As the Serpent grouels vpon the earth, ſo doth the Serpents ſeed, and hath not ſo much as the countenance of grace.</p>
               <p>Therefore as God hath giuen theſe vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto euery true Pilgrim, to bee exerciſed therein, during this preſent life, the one for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the other for God; And for that wee may the better, as it were, beare an euen hand in the practiſing and exerciſing of them as God may be pleaſed, and wee comforted: Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take thoſe directions for the ſame, as God hath appointed by his word, otherwiſe wee ſhould not be able to walke aright, but wander cleane out of the right way: For if we doe not aske councell at Gods word, but truſt in fleſh and bloud, wee are ſure to runneawry, for as the difference is betweene the body, and the ſoule, the one mortall, to liue but a ſhort time, the other immortall to liue for euer, euen ſo muſt our exerciſe and reuerent care bee in our ſeruice towards them both.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1975:10"/>
               <p>Now for the bodily eſtate, the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>If wee haue food and raiment, let vs be therewith content.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. and <hi>Salomon</hi> beeing both wiſe and rich, prayed for a competent liuing, ſaying, <hi>Lord giue mee neither pouerty nor riches, onely grant mee a neceſſary liuing, Pro.</hi> 30.8. Againe, the Apoſtle exhorteth vs to haue our conuerſation without couetouſneſſe, beeing content with ſuch things as wee haue, beſides many other like places for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Now the worldly man hath no contentment, but a continuall deſire of worldly riches, which is but a falſe treaſure to truſt vpon, but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth vnto vs a riches which euery true Chriſtian ought to couet and deſire, ſaying, <hi>Godlineſſe is great gaine, if a man be content with that hee hath.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. Out of theſe words iſſue many profitable leſſons and inſtructions for all true Chriſtians to obſerue and follow, for a Chriſtian ſhall finde little ioy in riches but ſhall finde great ioy in the holy Ghoſt, they ſhall finde little peace in the world, but ſhall finde great peace in conſcience.</p>
               <p>Now, when the Apoſtle had found out the diſeaſe of couetouſneſſe, hee like a skilfull Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, goeth about to pick out the greedy worme, which maketh men ſo hungry for wealth, and then ſetteth ſuch a glaſſe before
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1975:11"/>them, which hee calleth contentation, that will make a ſhilling ſeeme as great as a pound, and a cottage ſeeme as faire as a Pallace, &amp;c. that hee which hath but twenty pounds, ſhall be as merry as he which hath an hundred pounds.</p>
               <p>If wee heare and vnderſtand them with the ſame ſpirit that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> writ them, then will they ſo worke vpon our hearts, that euery man ſhall goe away contented with that hee hath, like <hi>Zacheus</hi> which before hee had ſeene Chriſt, knew nothing but to ſcrape, but as ſoone as hee had heard Chriſt, all his minde was ſet vpon giuing. This was the firſt day that <hi>Zache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſeemed rich to himſelfe, when riches ſeemed dung vnto him, and godlineſſe ſeemed riches, for when wee contemne riches, then ſhall wee ſeeme riche, becauſe no man hath enough but hee which is contented, for wee ſhall be coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous vntill wee become religious. Therefore he that will haue contentation, muſt leaue his couetouſneſſe in pawne for it, for what hath brought vſury, and ſimony, and bribery, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, enuie, ſtrife, and deceit into the world, and made euery houſe an Inne, and euery ſhoppe a market of othes and lyes, and fraude, but the ſuperfluous loue of money, and therefore name couetouſneſſe, and thou haſt named then the mother of all theſe miſchiefes.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1975:11"/>
               <p>Of them which ſeeme to bee wiſe, there bee no ſuch fooles in the world, as they which loue money better then themſelues, but this is the iudgement of God, that they which deceiue others, deceiue themſelues, and liue like <hi>Caine</hi> which was a vagabond vpon his owne land, ſo they are beggers in the middeſt of their wealth: for though they haue vnderſtanding to know riches, and a minde to ſeeke them, and wit to finde them, and policie to keepe them, yet they haue a falſe ſight and bleered eye, that when their riches lye before them, they ſeeme poore, and hee which hath ſo much, ſeemeth richer then they.</p>
               <p>It is a wonder to ſee men compaſſing about ſeeking what they may get, ſuch loue is there betweene men and money, that they which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe good will vnto it with their harts, will not take ſo much paines for their life, as they take for gaine, therefore no maruell if they haue no leiſure to ſanctifie themſelues, which haue no leiſure to refreſh themſelues. Our Sauiour Chriſt knew what hee ſpake, when hee ſaid: <hi>No man can ſerue two Maiſters,</hi> meaning God and the world, therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The loue of this world is enmity to God,</hi> ſignifying ſuch emulation is betweene theſe two, that God cannot abide the world ſhould haue a part,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1975:12"/>and the world cannot abide that God ſhould haue a part, therefore the loue of the world muſt needs be emnity to God.</p>
               <p>And ſo no couetous perſon is Gods ſeruant, but his enimy, for this cauſe couetouſneſſe is called Idolatry. Now the Apoſtle to make vs to loue godlineſſe, hee calleth it by the name of great gaine, heare wee may ſee that God doth not command men to bee godly onely, becauſe it maketh for his glory, but becauſe godlineſſe is profitable to vs. Alſo, for godlineſſe is not called gaine in reſpect of God, but in reſpect of vs, it is gaine to vs, but it is duty to him, ſo it is not called a health in reſpect of vs, becauſe it is the health of our ſoules, ſo it is not called a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in reſpect of God, but in reſpect of vs, becauſe wee are intituled to the kingdome, by this difference from the reprobates.</p>
               <p>Now put all the good things in the world together, and the goodneſſe of all is found in godlineſſe, to ſhew that the godly are as well, as merry, as content, with their loue towards God, and Gods loue towards them, as other are with health, and wealth, and pleaſure. Therefore it is ſaid of the godly, <hi>The feare of the Lord is their treaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the riches of the world are called earthly, tranſitory, ſnares, dung, as though they were
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1975:12"/>not worthy to bee counted riches, and therfore to draw the earneſt loue of men from them, the holy Ghoſt brings them in with ſuch names of diſdaine, to diſgrace them with their louers.</p>
               <p>But when hee comes to godlineſſe, which is the riches of the ſoule, then hee calleth it great riches, heauenly riches, vnſearchable riches, euerlaſting riches, with all the names of pleaſure, and all the names of happineſſe.</p>
               <p>The worldly man hath a kinde of peace and ioy, and riches, but it cannot be called great, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue not enough, they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as the godly are, therefore godlineſſe hath his honour, to be called great gaine.</p>
               <p>Riches makes bate, but godlineſſe makes peace, riches breeds couetouſneſſe, but godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe brings contentation, riches makes a man vnwilling to dye, but godlineſſe makes a man ready to die, therefore onely godlineſſe hath this honour to be called great riches, ſuch ioy, ſuch peace is in godlineſſe, and yet no man couets it.</p>
               <p>For this is the quality of vertue, it ſeemeth nothing vnto a man, vntill he haue it, but when hee hath found it, hee will not then looſe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for all the world, becauſe it brings him to be contented with that he hath: Now becauſe contentation is of ſuch a nature, that it can pleaſe it ſelfe with pouerty aſwell as riches, as though
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1975:13"/>it had all which they wanted, and this content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wee owe to godlineſſe becauſe it is not poſſible for a wicked man to bee contented, but the godly man hath found that which all the world doth ſeeke, that is enough.</p>
               <p>It is ſildome ſeene that contentation is found in riches, therefore the Apoſtle teacheth vs, to ſeeke it in godlineſſe, ſaying, <hi>Godlineſſe is great riches,</hi> and this riches the world ſeldome think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of, but when Godlineſſe commeth vnto a man, it ſaith; Peace be in this houſe, peace be in this heart, peace be in this man, and this is the ſigne whether Godlineſſe bee in a man, if hee haue ioy and contentment with that he hath: if he haue much, he can ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, I haue learned to abound,</hi> if he haue little, <hi>I haue l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arned to want,</hi> that is, if we haue much as <hi>Abraham,</hi> as <hi>Lot,</hi> as <hi>Iob,</hi> as <hi>Iacob, &amp;c.</hi> Yet it cannot corrupt his mind, for though the godly man be full of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yet his heart is not rent, his minde is not troubled, his countenance is not changed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he remembreth that theſe things were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him to do good: ſuch a commander is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation, that whereſoeuer ſhee ſetteth foote, an hundreth bleſſings waite vpon her, in euery diſeaſe ſhee is a Phyſitian, in euery ſtrife ſhee is a Lawyer, in euery doubt ſhee is a Preacher, in euery griefe ſhee is a comforter.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:1975:13"/>
               <p>Therefore if wee ſee a man contented with that hee hath, it is a great ſigne godlineſſe is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into him, for the heart of man is made the temple of God, and nothing can fill it but God alone.</p>
               <p>Therefore bleſſed is the man whom godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth make rich ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſorrow of heart with it <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.22. theſe are the riches which at the laſt wee muſt dwell with, when all the reſt which we haue lyed for, and ſworne for, and fretted for, and broken our ſleepe for, and loſt many a Sermon for, will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake vs, like ſeruants which change their Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, then godlineſſe ſhall ſeeme as great gaine vnto vs, as it did to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and hee which loued the world moſt, would giue all that hee hath for a dram of faith, that he might be ſure to goe to heauen when he is dead, though he went towards hell ſo long as he liued.</p>
               <p>Thus wee may ſee the fruites of godlineſſe, and the fruits of couetouſneſſe: for if wee bee couetous, wee ſhall neuer haue enough, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we haue too much, but if we bee godly, wee ſhall haue enough, though wee ſeemed to haue nothing: therefore what counſell is there to be taken herein, but as our Lord Ieſus coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled his Diſciples; Bee not friends to riches,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1975:14"/>but make you friends of riches, and know this that if wee cannot ſay with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in what eſtate ſoeuer we are in, wee haue learned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be content, that is whether we be riche or poore, in health or ſickneſſe, or in any other eſtate whatſoeuer, if contentation be not there, then godlineſſe is not yet come vnto that man, for the companion of godlineſſe is contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which when ſhee commeth will bring vnto vs all good things.</p>
               <p>Thus much for this firſt part, wherein is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the beginning of our Pilgrimage iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, beeing ſtrangers here placed in this world, and withall hauing all other creatures giuen and made in ſubiection for the vſe and ſeruice of man. And ſo conſequently man himſelfe, while he remaineth a Pilgrim to ferue God his Creator, with true faith, obedience, and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life all his dayes, and that all earthly things be made indifferent for the vſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of man, with a breefe note how the moſt part of this world doe runne contrary in this point, and doe not take care of that duty and buſineſſe for which alone they were created and placed here in this world, and is alſo declared what great dangers and deſtructions ſuch run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners away fall into, with an admonition to all true Chriſtians, which are but ſtrangers and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1975:14"/>Pilgrims in this world, and hauing many eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to encounter withall, and for the auoyding the dangers of them, wee ought to bee carefull to diſtinguiſh truly betweene ſpirituall and worldly care, which is recited in the ſtory of <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> by our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe. Alſo that God hath giuen two vocations vnto men, the one heauenly and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall for the ſoule, the other earthly and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall for the body; therefore as God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen theſe vocations to euery Chriſtian to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exerciſed therein, the one for our ſelues, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for God, and that we may the better beare an euen hand in the vſe and practiſing of them, as God may be glorified, and we comforted, we muſt embrace and follow the exhortation of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> where hee ſaith. <hi>That Godlineſſe it great gaine, if a man bee content with that hee hath.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.6. wherein enſueth many profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table leſſons for the better performing of theſe two duties both for Gods glory and our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:1975:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Pilgrims iorney towards Heauen. Part.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this ſecond part is contained a more carefull and ſpeedy going forward, in feeking to come to the knowledgment of the true way, which leadeth euery true Pilgrim to his wiſhed deſire that is, eternall reſt and happineſſe, to raigne with Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and his Church in the kindome of God his Father, for euermore: And in this part is ſet downe three ſpeciall conſequents to bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and followed. The firſt is a ſpeedy begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and going forward in Chriſtian religion, ſet downe by <hi>Salomon</hi> in <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12.2. ſaying, <hi>Remember thy maker in the dayes of thy youth, or euer the dayes of aduerſitie come,</hi> which may bee called the young mans taxe. The ſecond is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſet downe in the <hi>Pro</hi> 23.26. ſaying, <hi>My ſonne giue mee thy heart, and let thy eyes haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in my wayes:</hi> which may be called the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian mans ſacrifice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The third is the prayer of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.12. ſaying; <hi>Teach vs O Lord to number our dayes, that we apply our hearts vnto wiſdome:</hi> and may fitly be called the godly mans requeſt.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1975:15"/>
               <p>In theſe three notes or parts, are ſet downe many godly and profitable leſſons and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to bee followed of euery true Chriſtian, which is carefull of his owne ſaluation and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for the kingdome of God, and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe thereof, with ſuch obedience of life and conuerſation, as may be agreeable vnto the holy word of our God. And for that God would not haue vs to looſe our labour, but he would haue vs ſeeke and find, to aske and receaue, to runne and obtaine: therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>So run as you may obtaine.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. As there is a heauen, ſo there is a way to heauen; one way <hi>Adam</hi> came from Paradice, and by a nother way hee muſt returne to Paradice, the paſſage is not ſo ſtopt, but there is a way, though a ſtraight way, and therefore few doe finde it, but onely thoſe which are like <hi>Iacob,</hi> that dreamed and ſaw a Ladder which reached from earth to heauen, and the Angels diſcended, and aſcended by it, to ſhew that no man aſcended to heauen, but by that Ladder: This Ladder is Chriſt, which ſaith, <hi>I am the way,</hi> in <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14. there hee bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to follow him: If wee muſt follow Chriſt, let vs ſee how hee went to heauen, hee began betime, for at Twelue yeares of age hee ſayd, <hi>I must goe about my fathers buſineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:1975:16"/>
               <p>Hee made ſpeed, for <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith 21.25. that hee ſpake and did more good things in three and thirty yeares then could be written. <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſheweth when it beſt time to ſow the ſeed of vertue, that it may bring forth the fruite of life, and make a man alway ready to dye. Let him remember his Creator in the dayes of his youth, and ſo all his life ſhall runne, the middle like the beginning, and the end like the middle: for if the minde be planted in ſinne, in the time of youth, ſildome any goodneſſe buddeth out of that ſtock, for vertue muſt haue a time to grow, the ſeed is ſowne in youth, which commeth vp in age. As the Arrow is directed at the firſt, ſo it flieth all the way, ouer or vnder; but it neuer findeth the marke, vnleſſe it be leuelled right in the hand. So they which make an euill begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, forſpeake themſelues at the firſt, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out all their race, becauſe, when they ſhould haue directed their life aright, they wandred cleane contrary way.</p>
               <p>Therefore God requiring the firſt borne for his offring, &amp; the firſt fruits of his ſeruice, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the firſt labours of his ſeruants, becauſe the beſt ſeaſon to ſeeke God in, is to ſeek him early.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Wiſdome</hi> ſaith, <hi>they which ſeeke mee early ſhall finde,</hi> but to them which deferre, ſhee ſaith: <hi>yee ſhall ſeeke mee, but yee ſhall not find me:</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:1975:16"/>therefore the holy Ghoſt cryeth ſo often. <hi>This is the acceptable time, this is the day of ſaluation, to day heare his voyce, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So hee which taketh time is ſure, but hee which looſeth time oftener faileth then ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: for when golden oportunity is paſt, no time will fit for it: therefore linger not with <hi>Lot,</hi> for if the Angell had not ſnatched him away, he had periſhed with Sodom for his delay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Samuell</hi> began to ſerue God in his minority, and was made a Prophet, <hi>Timothie</hi> began to read the Scriptures in his child-hood, and was an Euangeliſt, <hi>Daniell</hi> beeing in captiuity in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, and a yong man, would not bee changed from the ſeruice of his Lord God, but prayed dayly vnto him, yea though hee were therefore put into the Lions Den, yet the Lord deliuered him from the Lions, and brought him in great eſtimation with the King, and alſo a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. <hi>Dauid</hi> beeing the yongeſt of his brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, could not abide to heare <hi>Goliah</hi> to raile of his God, tooke in hand to fight with him, and ſlew him, when none of the hoaſt durſt. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> beeing the yongeſt of his bretheren, but <hi>Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> being ſold by his bretheren into Egipt, and there becauſe he would not defile the law of his God, by committing fornication with his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, was wrongfully throwne into priſon, yet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1975:17"/>the Lord his God deliuered him forth, and brought him in great fauour with King <hi>Pharao,</hi> and was made ruler ouer all his kingdome.</p>
               <p>Therefore this doth teach vs, how God doth loue and regard timely beginners in religion, &amp; ſo to ſerue him accordingly, ſo that they which are yong, need not to trye the ſnares and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world, or the iſſues and effects of ſinne, which old men haue laid before them, but go a merrier way to obtaine their wiſhed deſire, that is this, ſaith <hi>Salomon, Thou muſt remember thy Creator which did make thee, which hath elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee, which hath redeemed thee, which dayly preſerueth thee, which will for euer glorifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee.</hi> And as the kinde remembrance of a friend doth recreate the minde, ſo to thinke and meditate vpon God, will ſupply thy thoughts, diſpell thy griefe, and make thee cheerfull.</p>
               <p>Now if thou wouldeſt haue this ioy, comfort, and pleaſure to belong vnto thee, and wouldeſt eſcape thoſe thouſand miſeries, vexations and vanities which <hi>Salomon</hi> by many weary and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious toiles ſought to make naked before thee, and yet held all but vanity, when hee had found the right way, <hi>Thou muſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>remember thy maker in the dayes of thy youth, and then thy hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe shall bee as long as thy life, and all thy thoughts whileſt thou remaineſt on earth, a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1975:17"/>of the glory of heauen:</hi> this is the ſumme of <hi>Salomons</hi> counſell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> findeth man ſeeking happineſſe out of the way, he pittieth to ſee him ſeeke, and not find, to run, and not to obtaine, therefore he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him in the way like a guide ſent from God, which often hath ſtraied himſelfe before, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now recouered to the right way againe, ſtandeth like a Marke of knowledge in the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings that lead vnto blind by-wayes, to direct all thoſe that ſeek for comfort, that they may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ready path that leadeth to eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: Therefore from the firſt ſetting forth, euen from the time of youth, when man begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his pilgrimage courſe, <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth how he ſhall therein prepare himſelfe to walke, and ſetteth him in a faire high way, wherein is no turning, either to the right hand or to the left, which he calleth the <hi>Remembrance of God,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Walke with God,</hi> as <hi>Henock</hi> did, &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber wel he that ſhalbe thy Iudge, doth ſee all that thou doſt &amp; heareth thee euery word, &amp; thy thought ſhal keep thee in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way at all times.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Salomon</hi> ſetteth forth the dangers of delay, and draweth them forward as it were with two cordes, that is, ſhort time of their youth, &amp; the infinite infirmities of age, to ſhew how ſoone our youth is gone, which we thinke
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1975:18"/>neuer will haue end. <hi>Salomon</hi> doth not reckon it by yeares, but by dayes. In the dayes of thy youth, ſo the Scripture numbers our life by dayes and houres, and minutes, to teach vs to make carefull vſe of all our time, and euery day thinke vpon our end: yet leaſt they ſhould poſte ouer the remembrance vntill age come, which is the generall day, that all for the moſt part ſet to repent in: therefore after this verſe, <hi>Salomon</hi> bringeth in the old man, deafe, blind, and lame, and ſtammering for the yong man to behold, as if hee ſhould ſay: Looke my ſonne, is this man fit to learne, which cannot heare, nor ſee, nor ſpeake, nor goe? Therefore remember thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the dayes of thy youth, before this doting age come vpon thee: this then is the leuell of your meſſage, to haſten forward them which tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell towards heauen, becauſe there is great ſpace betweene God and vs, and much a doo to aſpire the top of the Mount of Sion, but more a doo to aſpire the top of the mount of heauen.</p>
               <p>This is the preferment of our ſinnes, if they haue beene our companions in youth, in age they will be our counſellers and Maiſters too: therefore the beſt ſeaſon to ſeeke God in, is to ſeeke him early, before the floods of wrath ariſe, and the heape of ſinnes ſtand vp like a rampired wall betweene God and vs. Therefore ſaith our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1975:18"/>Sauiour Chriſt, If you ſeeke the kingdome of God firſt, al other things ſhal be caſt vpon you: he ſaith not ſeeke the world firſt, that heauen ſhall be caſt vppon you, he that doth belieue this would firſt ſeeke heauen: And wee ſay firſt, let mee bury my father, firſt let mee bid my friends farwell, and ſo many things come firſt, ſo long in burying our fathers, ſo long in bidding our friends farwell, that is to ſay, the riches, honors and pleaſures of this world, that there is left no time to ſeeke the kingdome, but <hi>follow mee,</hi> is turned to <hi>follow vs.</hi> Chriſt muſt followe our ſinnes, and come after our pleaſures, or elſe he ſhall not be ſerued at all, therefore I can not ſay to you as Chriſt: ſeeke firſt the kingdome of heauen, for then you ſhould haue ſought it long ago, but now it muſt be ſaid, which the Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>Redeeme the time and at laſt ſeeke the kingdome of heauen,</hi> for it is to bee feared, that as little flyes, when many came together, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued and deſtroyed the Egiptians, ſo ſhorte howers but many in ſinne and ſecuritie will ſteale away our whole life and deceaue our repentance.</p>
               <p>There bee not many <hi>Lots,</hi> but many linger like <hi>Lot,</hi> loth to depart, vntill wee fee the fire come; there bee not many <hi>Simions,</hi> but many as old as <hi>Simion,</hi> which neuer yet imbraced
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1975:19"/>Chriſt in their hearts, they thought to repent before they were ſo old, yet now they dote for age, they are not old enough to repent: Woe to the ſecurity, woe to the ſtubburneſſe, woe to the drowſineſſe of this age.</p>
               <p>Conſider this, yee which might haue knowne a thouſand things more then yee doe, if you had begone when <hi>Salomon</hi> taught you, for God will not alwayes knock at the doore of your hearts. Chriſt will not alwayes clock like a Henne to gather her Chickins, <hi>Iohn</hi> will not alway crye, <hi>Repent, for the day of the Lord is at hand,</hi> but mercy is in the foreward, and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the reereward, yet Wiſdome cryeth in the ſtreetes. Let euery <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſtore vp before the famine come, for hee which promiſeth thee pardon when thou returneſt, doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that to morrow thou ſhalt returne, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is a gift, and a gift muſt bee taken when it is offered, for the time paſt is gone, and thou canſt not call that to repent in, the time to come is vncertaine, and thou canſt not aſſure that to repent in, the preſent time is onely thine, and thou mayeſt repent in that, but a non that will bee gone too.</p>
               <p>Therefore as <hi>Samuel</hi> began to ſerue God in his minority, as <hi>Timothy</hi> read the Scriptures in his child-hood, ſo whether thou bee old or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1975:19"/>yong, thy repentance cannot come too ſoone, becauſe thy ſinne is gone before. And if thou lackeſt a Spurre to make thee runne, ſee how euery day runneth away with thy life, youth commeth vpon child-hood, age commeth vpon youth, death commeth vpon age, with ſuch a ſwift ſaile, that if all our minutes were ſpent in mortifying our ſelues, yet our glaſſe would not bee runne out, before we had purged halfe our corruptions. All theſe examples and ſentences, and prouerbes, &amp; reaſons, do cry with <hi>Salomon, Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it followeth in this ſecond note or part to be obſerued, for the better performance of this our Chriſtian duty, wee muſt yeeld vnto GOD that ſacrifice which hee requireth, and penned by <hi>Salomon</hi> 22.26. vnder the name of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> and directed vnto her ſonnes, for the children of God are called the children of Wiſdome, therefore Wiſdome entreateth her ſonnes, that they would giue her their hearts. This Wiſdome is GOD, wee by adoption are his ſonnes, and our heart is that which Chriſt calleth ſpirit and truth without hypocriſie, <hi>Giue me thy heart</hi> ſaith God: <hi>Dauid</hi> as though hee were at a ſtand and ſorrowed that hee could not doe enough for God, broke forth to himſelfe: <hi>What ſhall I giue vnto the Lord
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1975:20"/>for all that he hath giuen me:</hi> Pſal. 116. the Lord as it were hearing theſe ſighes of his ſeruants, which care and ſtudy what they may doe to pleaſe him, comes in their ſuſpence, and like a friend, which deſireth nothing but good will, anſwers from heauen, <hi>My ſonne giue me thy hart,</hi> vnder which ſute he taxeth them beſides, which are ſuters alwayes to him, and looke ſtill to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue more benefits, and yet neuer caſt in their mindes what they ſhall giue: therefore their tribute is ſet downe by equall meaſure, euery man muſt homage his heart, which is euen the continent of all, and gouernour of mans houſe, which ſits on the bench like a Iudge to giue the charge, and teacheth the toung to ſpeake, the hand to worke, the feete to walke, the eare to attend, the eye to obſerue, the minde to chooſe, the fleſh to obey: This heart we muſt preſent to God, like a burnt ſacrifice, wherein all is offered together. A wiſe toung, a diligent hand, a warie foote, a watchfull eare, a humble minde, an obedient fleſh, put all together and it is but thy heart. <hi>My ſonne,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>giue me thy heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This mite God will haue, for all his benefits, which wee may beſt affoord him, but thy almes to the poore, thy counſell to the ſimple, thine inheritance to thy children, thy trauell in thy vocation, but thy heart vnto God, hee which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1975:20"/>is a ſpirit, requireth the ſpirit, and delighteth to dwell in the hearts of men.</p>
               <p>God here plants himſelfe as in a Caſtle which is alwayes beſieged, with the world, the fleſh, and the Diuell, if thy enimy get a thought, or a word, or a worke, yet hee hath but raiſed the walls, but and if hee take the heart, then the fortreſſe is left, &amp; for that time all our thoughts, words, and workes are in captiuity vnto him.</p>
               <p>Therefore giue God thy heart, that hee may keepe it, not a peece of thy heart, nor a roome in thy heart, but thy whole heart, in the 6. of <hi>Deut.</hi> hee asketh all thy heart, all thy ſoule, all thy ſtrength, there hee requireth all, leaſt wee ſhould keepe a thought behind.</p>
               <p>Yet is thy heart but a vaine heart, a barren heart, a ſinfull heart, vntill thou giue it vnto GOD, and then it is the temple of the Holy Ghoſt, and the Image of God, ſo changed, and formed, and fined, that God calls it a new heart.</p>
               <p>So the heart is all and cheefe in requeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if there bee any goodneſſe, it lieth in the heart, and hee which giueth the heart giueth all, for out of the aboundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh, the eye looketh, the eare liſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the foote walketh to doe good or euill.</p>
               <p>Wee ſee <hi>Dauid</hi> is called a man after Gods owne heart, but becauſe when God ſaid, <hi>Giue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1975:21"/>me thy heart,</hi> his ſpirit anſwered like an Eccho, I giue thee my heart, goe my heart vnto thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, thy bridgroome hath ſent for thee, put on thy wedding garment, for the king himſelfe will marry thee.</p>
               <p>Therefore let al ſuiters haue their anſwers, that the heart is married already, and ſay God hath my heart, and he ſhal haue it, but take heed that thy heart doe not deceiue thee and ſay it is Gods, when it is the worlds, but by this thou ſhalt know whether thou haſt giuen it to God or no, if it bee gone, and ſet forward to God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy members will follow after it, the tongue wil praiſe him, the foote will follow him, the eare will atend him, the eye will watch him, the hand wil ſerue him, nothing wil ſtay after the heart, but euery one goeth like hand-maides af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their miſtris.</p>
               <p>This Chriſt verifyed ſaying, <hi>Make cleane within all &amp; ſhalbe cleane, Saint Paul</hi> teacheth vs to make melody to the Lord in our hearts <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. ſhewing that there is a comfort of al the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, when the heart is in tune, and that it ſounds like a melodie in the eares of GOD, and makes vs reioyce while wee ſerue him, wee haue an enſample hereof in Chriſt which ſaid it was meate and drinke for him to doe his Fathers buſineſſe.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:1975:21"/>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> picketh out the heart for God, ſpeaking as though hee would ſet out the pleaſants and fareſt, and eaſieſt way to ſerue him, without any grudging, or toile or wearineſſe, touch but the firſt linke and all the reſt will follow, ſo ſet the heart a going and it is like the poiſe of a Clocke which turnes all the Wheeles one way, ſuch an oile is vpon the heart which makes all nimble and corant about it, therefore it is almoſt as eaſie to ſpeake wel and doe wel, as it is to thinke wel, if the heart indite a good matter, no maruel then though the tongue bee the penne of a ready writer, but and if the heart bee dull, all is then like a left hand, ſo vnapt and vntoward that it cannot turne it ſelfe to any good.</p>
               <p>The life and conuerſation of a man teſtifieth what is in the heart, and the tongue wil hardly keepe ſecret what is therein.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt verifieth this when hee ſaith, <hi>either make the tree good, and his fruite good, or elſe make the tree euil, and his fruite euill, for the tree is knowne by his fruite,</hi> for a good man out of the good treaſure of the heart bringeth forth good things, and an euill man out of the euill treaſure bringeth forth euill things.</p>
               <p>Therefore the tongue will not praiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the heart doth not loue, the care doth not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1975:22"/>heare, becauſe the heart doth not minde, the hand doth not giue, becauſe the heart doth not pitty, the foot will not goe becauſe the heart doth not ſtirre; ſo that all ſtay vpon the heart, thus to ſhew that hee deſerueth all, euen the Lord our God which bringeth all.</p>
               <p>Againe, God requireth the heart, ſhewing that the things of this world are not worthy of it: no not a thought, for if the heart bee the temple of God, hee which giueth it to any thing elſe, committeth ſacriledge, and breaketh that Commandent, <hi>Giue vnto God, that which is Gods. Math.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Againe, that all ſhould ſo conſent with the heart, that wee ſhould ſpeake, as if our heart did ſpeake; pray as if our heart did pray, heare as if our heart did heare; giue, as if our heart did giue; remit, as if our heart did remit, &amp;c. As the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>Doe all things hartily, Coloſ.</hi> 3.23. Which if wee could doe nothing that wee doe, ſhould any way trouble vs, becauſe nothing is troubleſome, but that which goeth againſt the heart.</p>
               <p>God will not haue vs to ſpeake to him, nor come to him for any thing, vnleſſe wee bring our hearts vnto him, for the tongue without the heart, is a flattering tongue, the eye without the heart, is a wicked eye, the eare without the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1975:22"/>heart, is a vaine eare; the hand without the heart, is a falſe hand, hee which gaue but a mite, and bringeth his heart, bringeth more then he which offereth a Talent.</p>
               <p>God delighteth himſelfe in giuing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee loueth a cheerefull giuer, but hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not giue cheerfully, which giueth not his heart, for hee which giueth God his lippes, inſteed of his heart, teacheth God to giue him ſtones in ſteed of bread, that is a ſhadow of comfort, for comfort it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Of all the ſuters that come vnto vs, it ſeemeth there is none which hath any title to claime the heart, but God, which challengeth it by the name of a Sonne. As if hee ſhould ſay, thou ſhalt giue it to thy Father, which gaue it to thee: art thou my ſonne? my ſonnes giue me their hearts, and by this they know that I am their father, if I dwell in their hearts: for the heart is the temple of God: therefore if thou be his fonne, thou wilt giue him thy heart, becauſe thy Father defireth it, thy Maker deſireth it, thy Redeemer deſireth it, thy Sauiour deſireth it, thy Lord and King, and thy Maiſter deſireth it, which hath giuen his ſonne for a ranſome, his ſpirit for a pledge, his word for a guide, the world for a walke, and reſerueth a kingdome for thine inheritance.</p>
               <p>Now if wee would conſider the right way,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1975:23"/>whereby we may giue our hearts vnto God, the counſell of him whoe ſpeaketh nothing but the very truth, and he himſelfe is the truth that is our Lord and ſauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> which ſaith, <hi>where your treaſure is there will be your hearts alſo,</hi> therefore let our conuerſation be in heauen, and vpon heauenly thinges, that wee may thereby make our traſure there, and ſo wee ſhall haue our heartes there placed, where our enemies cannot take it from vs, thus much for this note as hath beene ſaid, now it followeth in the next.</p>
               <p>Now if wee haue not remembred our Lord and Creator in the daies of our youth, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all haue not giuen our hearts vnto him, whereby we might become religious, and to increaſe in vs renewed hearts and mindes for the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and finding out the right path-way which leadeth vnto eternall happineſſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay if wee haue not prepared our ſelues and done this already, as hath beene declared in this ſecond part, it is then now high time to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to remember God, and to giue our hearts vnto him in age, or elſe to forget him for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, for the gray-head which looketh euery day for his laſt Sabaoth, when hee ſhall reſt in the graue, had neede to pray twice aſmuch,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1975:23"/>heare twice as much, do twice as much to prepare ſacrifice of his body and ſoule ready, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto GOD, becauſe the night is at hand when he cannot pray, nor heare, nor repent any more: It is ſaid, the Diuell is very buſie, becauſe his time is ſhort, but an ould mans is ſhorter, therefore if youth had neede of legges, age had neede of winges, therefore in the next con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence it is further to bee obſerued what further duties wee are to proceede in as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moyſes</hi> in the 90. Pſalme. verſ. 12 ſaith, <hi>teach vs to number our daies that we may apply our hearts vnto wiſdome,</hi> this Pſalme was compiled by <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> as may appeare by the title; At what time the ſpies returned from the land of Canaan, and God for the murmuring of them pronounced that all which were aboue twenty yeares ould ſhould die in the wilderneſſe except <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſua:</hi> that encouraged their bretheren to goe into Canaan.</p>
               <p>Now when <hi>Moyſes</hi> heard the ſentence of death pronounced againſt him-ſelfe and all the Iewes which came out of Egypt, except onely two: That all ſhould die before they came to the land which they ſought for, he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus for himſelfe and the reſt. <hi>Teach vs O LORD to number our daies that wee may
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1975:24"/>giue our hearts vnto wiſdome,</hi> that is, ſeeing wee muſt needs dye, and that our dayes are ſhort, teach vs therefore to thinke vpon death, that wee may dye in thy feare O Lord, and ſo to liue againe for euermore: this ſheweth vs, that the conſideration of our mortality, will make vs apply our hearts to godlineſſe, therefore <hi>Moyſes</hi> thinking of his death, runneth to wiſdome as a remedy againſt death.</p>
               <p>Therefore wee muſt come to ſome Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter, which is like Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt:</hi> what ſhall wee doe, that wee may growe in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as wee grow in yeares? <hi>Teach mee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moyſes</hi>) <hi>to number my dayes, that I may apply my heart to wiſdome;</hi> whereby <hi>Moyſes</hi> telleth vs, that this was one of his helps, which made him profit in the knowledge of God. To remember his daies: as a man which hath a ſet time for his taxe liſtneth to the clock, &amp; counteth his houres.</p>
               <p>So wee haue a ſet time to ſerue God, <hi>worke while it is day, Iohn.</hi> 9.4. ſaith Chriſt: what hee doth meane by <hi>this day,</hi> the Apoſtle ſheweth vs, ſaying: <hi>This is the day of ſaluation,</hi> that is, This life is the day wherein wee ſhould worke our ſaluation: this is a long taxe, therefore wee had need to remember our dayes, and looſe not a minuit, leaſt we be be-nighted before our work be done. As God hath numbered our dayes, ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1975:24"/>we muſt learne to remember our dayes, or elſe it ſeemes we cannot apply our hearts to wiſdom, that is, vnleſſe wee thinke vpon death, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not faſhion our ſelues to a godly life, though we were aſwell inſtructed as <hi>Moyſes</hi> was.</p>
               <p>This we find dayly in our ſelues, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulnes of death, maketh vs to apply our hearts vnto folly, and pleaſure, and all voluptuouſneſſe, that contrary to his aduice, <hi>worke your ſaluation,</hi> we worke our damnation: therefore this is the fruite which commeth to a man, by numbring or remembring his dayes, God teacheth man to apply his heart to wiſdome, and that is his leſſon which he giueth for that purpoſe, <hi>Remember thy dayes,</hi> that is, thinke that wiſdom is a long ſtudy, and that thou haſt but a ſhort time to get it, and this will make thee get ground of vertue.</p>
               <p>Therefore, fiue things are to be noted in theſe words; firſt, that death is the heauen of euery man, whether hee ſit in the throne, or kept in a cottage, at laſt hee muſt knock at deaths doore: The ſecond is; That mans life is decreed, and his bounds appointed, which he cannot paſſe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our dayes are few, as though wee were ſent into this world, but to ſee it. Fourthly, the aptneſſe of man to forget death, rather then any thing elſe. Laſtly, to remember, how ſhort a time wee haue to liue, will make vs to apply
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1975:25"/>our hearts to that which is good. For the firſt poynt is, that as euery man had a day to come into this world, ſo hee ſhall haue a day to goe out of this world, we are not lodged in a Caſtle, but in an Inne, where we are but gueſts, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Peter</hi> calleth vs Pilgrims and ſtrangers, we are not citizens of the Earth, but citizens of Heauen. And therfore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We haue here no abiding citty, but we looke for one to come as</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My Kingdome is not of this world,</hi> ſo we may ſay, my dwelling is not of this world, but the ſoule ſoreth vp-ward whence it came, and the body ſtoopeth downeward whence it came, euery man is but a tennant at will, and there is nothing ſure but death. In Paradice we might liue or die, euery thing and euery day ſuffers ſome eclips and nothing ſtandeth at a ſtay, but our Creator calleth to another, let vs leaue this world, our fathers ſummoned vs, and we ſhall ſummon our children to the graue.</p>
               <p>So in an houre wee are, and are not, wee may well bee called earthen veſſells, for we are ſoone changed, what doe we learne when we thinke of this but that which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, to apply our harts vnto wiſdome? The ſecond note is that the time of man is ſet &amp; his bounds apointed, which he cannot paſſe, to this <hi>Iob</hi> beareth witneſſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Are not his daies determined, thou haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1975:25"/>his bounds which he cannot paſſe.</hi> Againe <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> ſaith, <hi>they could not ſtand, becauſe the day of their deſtruction was come.</hi> As there is a day of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction and a day of death, ſo there is a day of birth, a day of mariage, a day of honour, a day of deliuerance, according to that the determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made, that is GOD hath determined all things. As God appointed a time when his Son ſhould come into the world, and he came at the ſame time, as the Prophets and Euangeliſts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. So he hath appointed a time when all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings ſhall come vnto vs, and they come at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>It may bee ſome will ſay, if any time bee ſet, thus long I ſhall liue and I cannot paſſe, then will I take no Phiſicke, you may aſwell ſay I will take no meate: God hath not ordained the end with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the meanes, but the meanes aſwell as the end.</p>
               <p>If he hath appointed one to die in his youth he hath appointed meanes to ſhorten his life, or if he haue appointed one to liue long, he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed alſo ſome meanes to preſerue him.</p>
               <p>The third note is that our life is but ſhort, the Rauen, the Phenix, the Hart. Lion, and the Elephant fulfill their hundreds, but Man dyeth when he thinketh yet his ſun riſeth before his eyes bee ſatiſfied with ſeeing, or his eare with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1975:26"/>hearing, or his heart with luſting, then death knocks at his dore, and wil not giue him leaue to meditate an excuſe before he come to iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
               <p>This was the Arithmetick of holy men in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, to reckon their dayes, ſo that their time might ſeeme ſhort, to make them apply their hearts vnto wiſdome. As thus, firſt they did deductt the time, which is paſt, for the time which is paſt is nothing, then they did deduct the time to come. The time to come is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, for no man can ſay that he ſhall liue any time: Now when the time paſt and the time to come is ſet aſide, there is then nothing left but the preſent time, and is but a moment which is not ſo much in reſpect of eternity as a little moat to the whole world.</p>
               <p>Thus wee may ſee what an Epitome mans life is come to, <hi>Dauid</hi> numbred his dayes by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, My dayes ſaith he are like a ſpan long, <hi>Iob</hi> ſayth: Man (which is borne of a woman) hath but a ſhort time to liue. Our fathers (marueling to ſee how ſuddenly men are, and are not, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring life to a dreame in the night, to a bubble in the water, to an arrow which neuer reſteth, til his fall. This is our life, for while we enioy it we looſe it as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſayd, that his dayes had bene few, ſo we may ſay that our dayes ſhall be few.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:1975:26"/>
               <p>For as ſome came into the vineyard in the morning, and ſome at noone, and ſome at night for there muſt be ſome goe out of this worldly wilderneſſe in the morning, ſome at noone, and ſome at night, ſome mans life hath nothing but a morning, ſome hath a morning and a night, he which liueth longeſt: liueth al toe day: ſo that a glorious life, may be compared to a glorious day, and a ſorrowfull life to a bloody day, and a long life to a Summers day, and a ſhort life to a Winters day.</p>
               <p>Now why hath God appoynted ſuch a ſhort time to mankind in this world, ſurely leaſt hee ſhould deferre to doe good, as his manner is, for though his life be ſo ſhort, yet he thinketh it to long to repent, for we deferre til that week which we thinke wil be our laſt: Conſider this all which trauell toward heauen, had wee not need to make haſt, which muſt goe ſuch a long iourney, in ſuch a ſhort ſpace, how can he chuſe which remembreth that euery day runneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, with his life.</p>
               <p>The fourth poynt is our aptneſſe to forget death, rather then any thing els, and therefore <hi>Moyſes</hi> prayeth the Lord to teach him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his dayes, as though they were ſtil ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of his mind: For when <hi>Moſes</hi> prayeth the Lord to teach him to remember his dayes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1975:27"/>he ſignifieth that hee very faine would remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, but ſtill his minde did turne from them, and that hee could not thinke vpon them longer then hee thought on the Lord which taught him to remember them.</p>
               <p>Such is the rebelious nature of ours, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remember that which wee ſhould, becauſe we are apt to remember ſo many things which we ſhould forget.</p>
               <p>How often doth the Scripture call death to our remembrance, and yet wee read how many put the day of death from them, and would not remember it. <hi>Salomon</hi> bids vs remember that we ſhall come to iudgement, yea wee ſay in our hearts, there is no death, or at leaſt death will not come before we be old.</p>
               <p>There is a kinde of men which cannot abide to heare of death, they are ſicke with the name of it, the reaſon is, death prophſied no good to the wicked, but euil, for which they cannot abide it, for death commeth to the wicked like a Iai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, which commeth alwaies to haile them to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, therfore their care is not to remember death, that thereby they might apply their hearts vnto wiſdom, and ſo looſe their pleaſures, before their time, for he which doth not purpoſe yet to leaue his ſin would not be troubled with any thought that might make him take his pleaſure fearefully,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1975:27"/>for the deuil doth neuer teach a man to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber his death becauſe he gaineth by the forgetfulnes of death, but the Lord our God which would haue vs to apply our hearts vnto wiſdom, it is he which teacheth vs to remember our daies.</p>
               <p>The laſt point, that to remember how ſhort a time wee haue to liue will make vs apply our hearts to that which is good, two things are to be noted in theſe words, firſt that if we wil find wiſdome we muſt apply our hearts to ſeeke her; the ſecond that remembrance of death makes vs to apply our hearts vnto it: touching the firſt, <hi>Moyſes</hi> found ſome fault with himſelfe, for for al that he heard, and did ſee and obſerued, and was compted wiſe yet he was new to begin to apply his heart to learne wiſdome, ſo vnſaciable and couetous (as I may ſay) are the ſeruants of God, for the more wiſdome, faith and zeale they haue, the more they defer.</p>
               <p>Therefore the way to get wiſdome is to apply our hearts vnto it, for from that day which a man beginnes to apply his heart vnto wiſdome hee learneth more in a month after then hee did in a yeere before, euen as wee may ſee the wicked, becauſe they apply their hearts to wickedneſſe, how faſt they proceed, how eaſily &amp; how quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they become perfect ſwearers, expert drunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerds, cunning deceiuers.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:1975:28"/>
               <p>So if you would apply your harts as throughly to knowledge and goodnes, you might then become like the Apoſtle, which teacheth you, therefore when <hi>Salomon</hi> ſheweth men the way how to come by wiſdome, he ſpeaketh often of the heart: As giue thy heart to wiſdome, Let wiſdome enter into thine heart, get wiſedome, keep wiſdome, embrace wiſdome.</p>
               <p>Thus we haue learned how to apply our harts to knowlede, that it may doe vs good, that we may ſay with the Virgin <hi>Mary, My heart doth magnifie the Lord,</hi> and then the heart will apply it to the eare, and the tongue (as <hi>Chrict</hi> ſaith) out of the aboundance of the heart, the mouth ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>The ſecond note to be obſerued is, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of death maketh vs to apply our hearts to wiſedome: as many benefits come vnto vs by death, ſo many benefits come vnto vs by the remembrance of death. And this is one that maketh a man to apyly his heart vnto wiſdome, for when he conſidereth that he hath but a ſhort time to liue, he is carefull to ſpend it wel, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> of whom it is written, that when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered hee had but a ſhort ſeaſon to liue, hee choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the children of God then to enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:1975:28"/>
               <p>This wiſdome the fathers called the wiſdome of the croſſe, which we call the beſt wiſdome, becauſe it is deareſt bought, it is hard to thinke of a ſhort life, and to thinke euill, or to thinke of a long li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and thinke well.</p>
               <p>Therefore when <hi>Ieremy</hi> had numbred all the calamities and ſinnes of the Iewes at the laſt he imputed all to this, ſhe remembred not her end <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.9. So it may be iudged why natural men care for nothing but their pompe, why great men care for nothing but their honour and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, why couetous worldlings care for nothing but their gaine, why voluptuous Epicures care for nothing but their pleaſures, that it may be ſaid with <hi>Ieremie</hi> they remembred not their endes.</p>
               <p>Seeing then that ſo much fruit groweth of one ſtalke, which is the numbring of our dayes. Let vs therefore conſider what an harueſt we haue loſt, which happily before this day haue neuer prayed with <hi>Moſes</hi> that the Lord would teach vs to remember our dayes, but alſo how many dayes haue we ſpent and yet neuer thought why any dayes were giuen vs.</p>
               <p>It may be that thou haſt but twenty yeares to ſerue God, wilt thou not liue twenty yeares like a Chriſtian, that thou maiſt liue many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares like an Angel? It may bee that thou
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1975:29"/>haſt but tenne yeares to ſerue God, wilt thou not ſerue ten for Heauen, which wouldſt ſerue twenty yeares for a farme?</p>
               <p>If thou be a man, halfe thy time is ſpent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, if thou be an old man, then thou art draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thine Inne, and thy race is but a breath for this cauſe God would not haue men know when they ſhould dye becauſe they ſhould make ready at all times, hauing no more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of one hower then an other.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee that death is the laſt vpon earth and that the time of man is ſet, and that his race is ſhort, and that he thinkes not on it, and that if he did remember it, it would make him apply his mind to good as he doth to euill. And thus I end as I began, the Lord our God teach vs to remember our dayes, that we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our heartes vnto Wiſedome.</p>
               <closer>Amen, Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:1975:29"/>
               <head>The Pilgrims iourney towards Heauen.</head>
               <p>Theſe two parts going before are chapters of preparatiues, wherein euery Chriſtian ought to prepare himſelfe, to become truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, that he may learne to know the way to walke before God: whereby he may attaine to eternall happineſſe, which way is manifeſtly declared vnto vs by the word of God. And for aſmuch as there can be no ſound Deuine or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gramarian, but he muſt firſt come to it by degrees in learning, as appeareth in ſchooles of learning, ſo is it with the Church of God, for our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayth plainely that <hi>None can come vnto him, but he muſt be drawn of the father, Iohn.</hi> 6.44. aleadging the ſcriptures how we are drawne, ſaying: it is written in the prophets: <hi>And they ſhall all be taught of God, euery man therefore that hath heard and learned of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commeth vnto</hi> me. <hi>Iſaie.</hi> 54 13. <hi>Iere:</hi> 31.33.</p>
               <p>Therefore we are to apply our ſelues to thoſe meanes which God hath ordained for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that is the preaching of his word and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations thereof, for the holy Ghoſt is giuen for the working of the ſame in euery Chriſtian; therefore it is written in the Book called <hi>Eccl.</hi> 6 33. ſaying, <hi>My ſon, if thou wilt take heed thou ſhalt be taught, and if thou wilt apply thy mind thou ſhalt bee wiſe, if thou wilt bow downe thine eare
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1975:30"/>thou ſhalt receiue doctrine, and if thou delight in hearing thou ſhalt be wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith: <hi>O giue eare vnto good counſel and be content to be reformed, that thou mayeſt be wiſe in thy latter dayes. Pro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo written in the 22. of the Pro. ſaying: <hi>Bow downe thine earer and heare the wordes of the Wiſe, apply thy mind vnto my doctrine, for it is a pleaſant thing if thou keepe them in thine hart, and order them in thy lippes, that thou maist put thy truſt in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore ſayth the Prophet <hi>Dauid: The mouth of the righteous wil ſpeake of wiſdome, and his tongue wil talk of iudgement, for the law of his God is in his heart, &amp; his lips ſhall not ſlide Pſa.</hi> 37. Therefore ſayth <hi>Salomon: get wiſedome and get vnderstang, forſake her not, and ſhe ſhal preſerue thee, loue her, and ſhe ſhall keepe thee, for the cheefe poynt of Wiſdome, is to poſſeſſe wiſdome and before all thy gooods get vnderſtanding, make much of her, and ſhe wil promote thee, yea if thou embrace her, ſhe ſhal bring thee vnto honor, ſhe ſhall beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thy head with manifold graces and garniſh thee with a Crowne of glory. Pro.</hi> 4.5.6.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer therefore findeth Wiſdome findeth life, and ſhal obtaine fauour of the Lord. Pro.</hi> 8. Now this Wiſdome, is called the wiſdome of the word of God, which proceedeth from God
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1975:30"/>himſelfe, and all to teach vs to walke in holy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and conuerſation, all our dayes, and therein to find ſaluation, and eternall happines. For in matters concerning the trueth of our walking we muſt profes with <hi>Dauid: Thy word is a Lanthorne vnto my feet, and a light vnto my pathes, for whatſoeuer therefore doth not fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the word of God in matters of truth, and ſaluation, maſt euer be ſuſpected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the wiſedome of man when it wandreth without the pales of holy ſcriptures, is meere fooliſhnes, which wil euer be confounded, and brought to nought. 1. Cor. 1.</p>
               <p>Therefore wee muſt attribute nothing vnto na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, when it is not grounded by, ſome conſequent vppon the word of God.</p>
               <p>So that we are there by aught that God hath ordayned the meanes, ſo wee muſt prepare our ſelues to theſe meanes whereby wee are made religious and ſo become capable to receiue thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which come thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:1975:31"/>
               <head>In this third part is the way it ſelfe, which is the principall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow it followeth in this third part, which is the principall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it concerneth the way it ſelfe, which bringeth to eternall happineſſe. And therefore there is none can attaine to finde this way, and walke in it, but the renued, and the regenerate man: For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith plainely, <hi>That the naturall man knoweth not the things of the ſpirit of God, neither can vnderſtand them, becauſe they are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually diſcerned.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle in the 12. to the <hi>Romans; Be yee changed in the renuing of your minds, that yee may prooue what the good will of God is, acceptable and perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> had forbidden the <hi>Romans</hi> to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion themſelues vnto the world, hee ſheweth them another faſhion, which hee calls the renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the minde, this faſhion is called the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment which euery man muſt weare that comes to the banquet of the King: So <hi>Paul</hi> here calleth them to the old faſhion againe, which was vſed in <hi>Adams</hi> time, that is, in the image and faſhion wherein we were created at the firſt.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:1975:31"/>
               <p>Now the reaſon followeth, what benefit the renued minde hath, that is, yee may prooue what the will of God is. As if he ſhould ſay, this is the fruit of your regeneration, when your minds are renued, you ſhall know many things which are hid from you, for you ſhall bee able to iudge doctrins, who preach truth, &amp; who preach error. And you ſhall vnderſtand the will of God, what hee would haue you to do, and what hee would haue you to flie: for this new knowledge wil not abide but in new minds, the mind renued know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, ſo that this ſcripture may be called the path to knowledge, or the way to ſound the minde of God.</p>
               <p>It may be ſaid, why doth nor the word of God teach vs the will of God? yes, but no man doth vnderſtand this word, but he which hath a new minde: for as the Sunne is not diſcerned by any light, but by his own light, ſo no ſpirit can inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the ſcriptures, but by the ſame ſpirit which writ it, which is called the holy ſpirit, becauſe it is holy, &amp; makes vs holy, &amp; is the eſpeciall mean of our regeneration and new birth, whereby we may prooue what the will of God is. It is ſaid in <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.26. <hi>To a man that is good in his ſight, God giueth wiſdom &amp; knowledge:</hi> therfore though you haue ſeene cunning. Lawiers by much reading, &amp; expert Phiſitions by long ſtudy, yet you could
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1975:32"/>neuer ſee a perfect found &amp; iudicial diuine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſſe. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>the knowledge of good things is vnderſtanding. Prou.</hi> 9. So none but they which are holy haue this vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, he which cannot ſay with <hi>Dauid. My heart meditateth a good matter,</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not follow with <hi>Dauid, My tongue is the Pen of a ready writer:</hi> he which bids vs not to caſt Pearles before Swine, doth ſtay his owne hand from caſting knowledge to the vngodly.</p>
               <p>For when wee will learne Diuinity, wee muſt goe aſide from the world, and ſequeſter our ſinnes, and lift vp our minds aboue the earth, or elſe it will not ſtay with vs: There is an Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benger which goeth alway before the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God to prepare the way. And this is loue, the bonde of perfection. <hi>They which haue loue</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iohn) know God.</hi> 1.4 <hi>but they which haue not loue, know not God, though they haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much knowledge beſides:</hi> for hee that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, I haue the ſpirit of Chriſt,</hi> cannot ſay with him, <hi>I haue knowledge.</hi> Holy men were alwayes interpreters of Gods word, becauſe a godly minde, eaſileſt pearceth into Gods meaning, according to that in <hi>Math.</hi> 5.6. <hi>The pure in heart ſhall ſee God.</hi> And that in <hi>Iohn.</hi> 7.17. <hi>If any man will doe Gods will hee ſhall vnderſtand the doctrine, whether it be of God or no.</hi> And in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>They which keepe thy precepts
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1975:32"/>haue a good vnderſtanding.</hi> And that in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. <hi>The ſpirituall man vnderſtandeth all things;</hi> And therefore the feare of the Lord is not onely called the beginning of wiſdome. But in the <hi>Prou.</hi> 2.5. it is taken for Wiſdom it ſelfe. As when Chriſt taught in the Temple, they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, <hi>how knoweth this man the Scriptures?</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>hee neuer learned them.</hi> So it is a wonder, what learning ſome men haue, which haue no learning like <hi>Priſilla</hi> and <hi>Aquilla,</hi> poore Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, which were able to ſchoole <hi>Apollos,</hi> that great Clarke, a man renowned for his learning. What can bee ſaid to this? but as Chriſt ſayd, <hi>Father ſo it pleaſeth thee:</hi> ſo the holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, cannot giue any reaſon, why they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the words of God ſo eaſily, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doe conceiue them ſo hardly, but that Gods brings the meaning ſuddenly into their hearts. As it is ſaid in <hi>Luke.</hi> 24.25. <hi>That Chriſt opened the vnderſtanding, and made them vnderſtand the Scriptures.</hi> So we read in the <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> promiſeth to the righteous; <hi>If yee will turne at my correction, I will powre out my hear vnto you, and make you vnderſtand my words.</hi> There is a kinde of familiarity betweene God and the righteous, that hee makes them of his counſell, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.32. <hi>his ſecrets are with the righteous.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. <hi>His</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:1975:33"/>ſecrets are with the righteous. And <hi>Dauid</hi> in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. his ſecrets are reuealed vnto them that feare the Lord.</p>
               <p>For as the windowes of the temple were large within and narrow without, ſo they which are within the Church haue greater light then they which are without: <hi>For the ſpirituall man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) ſearcheth the deepe things of God, but the naturall man perceiueth not the things of God. Thou haſt reueiled theſe things to babes,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>but thou hast hid them from the wiſe of the world: My ſheepe heare my voyce,</hi> the reaſon of this <hi>Paul</hi> ſetteth downe in a word, ſaying, <hi>The wicked cannot vnderſtand heauenly things, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. Therefore how ſhould hee diſcerne them that hath not the ſpirit: for this cauſe Wiſdome is not ſaid to be iuſtified of any, but of her owne children <hi>Math.</hi> 11.9. Neither doth Chriſt ſay, that any ſheepe heare his voyce, but his owne ſheep, they follow their Shepheatd, they heare his voyce, they vnderſtand his law, they iudge of his iudgments, they haue the meaſure of his word. All is open and plaine, and manifeſt vnto them, they ſearch deeper, and iudge righter, and know ſooneſt. And though they haue no lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet they haue better iudgement then the learned.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:1975:33"/>
               <p>Therefore bee renued that yee may know the good, and perfect, and acceptable will of God, which muſt make vs good and perfect, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable our ſelues: Becauſe we will not renue our minds therefore we are ignorant of ſo many things, which we ſhould know. And vntill wee be willing with diligence to follow the word of God, and to make it a Lanthorne, &amp;c. wee ſhall neuer throughly vnderſtand it. O what a benefit had <hi>Salomon</hi> loſt, if he had loſt his wiſdom which God gaue him? euen as great a benefit doeſt thou looſe, if thou looſe the knowledge of Gods will.</p>
               <p>Wilt thou know what this renuing is? It is the repairing of the Image of God, vntill wee be like <hi>Adam</hi> when hee dwelt in Paradice. As there is a whole old man, ſo there muſt bee a whole new man. The old man muſt change pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties with the new man, that is, wiſdome for wiſdome, loue for loue, feare for feare, his worldly wiſdome, for heauenly wiſdome, his carnall loue for ſpirituall loue, hsi ſeruile feare for Chriſtian feare, his idle thoughts for holy thoughts, his vaine words for wholſome words, his fleſhly workes for ſanctified workes.</p>
               <p>Thus much of our regeneration and new birth, which may bee called the Chriſtian mans
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1975:34"/>practiſe, becauſe it concerneth euery Chriſtian to ſeeke for that foode which belongeth to the renued man, according to the ſaying of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> 1.2.2. <hi>As new borne babes deſire the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Milke of the word, that yee may grow thereby.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The nouriſhment and food for there generate man.</head>
               <p n="9">9. NOw followeth to bee obſerued, for the benefit and duty of the renued man, that hee may proceed and grow on, and dayly increaſe more and more in faith and feare of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, whereby wee receiue all our growth and increaſe in God. And therefore hee hath giuen vs ſpeciall meanes, that is the meditation and liuely preaching of the word of truth. Therefore the Apoſtle by a figuratiue and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed ſpeach, earneſtly preſſeth them to thriſt, and to long for the word of God, euen for the foood of their ſoules: for there are two births mentioned in the Scriptures, the one fleſhly, and naturally by propagation from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> whereby original, and our birth ſinne, as it were a Serpents poyſon paſſeth and tranſfuſeth it ſelfe into vs: the other is heauenly and ſpirituall by renouation from the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> which is
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1975:34"/>Chriſt, whereby grace and holineſſe is deriued and brought vnto vs.</p>
               <p>In this latter and better birth, God is our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to beget vs, the Church his ſpouſe our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to conceiue vs, the ſeed whereby wee are bred and borne againe, is the word of God, the Nurſe to feed and cheriſh vs are the Miniſters of the Goſpell, and the food whereby wee are nouriſhed and held in life, is the Milke of the word.</p>
               <p>Therefore in as much as children, which are new borne, cannot increaſe in growth and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but muſt needs dye and come to diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vnleſſe they bee continually fed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with wholſome food. It behooueth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the faithfull and godly, who are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reuiued in the life of God, as new borne babes, to deſire the ſincere Milke of the word, that they may grow by it. Let vs now therefore come to the perticuler parts, which iſſue and ſpring from the ſeuerall branches of this ſcripture.</p>
               <p>Firſt here is noted a preparation, if wee will be bettered, and increaſe by the word, we muſt be as new borne babes. Secondly, our affection and duty when we are new borne, we muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Thirdly, the matter and obiect of our deſire, is the Milke of the word. Fourthly, the quality
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1975:35"/>of the milke, that muſt be ſincere, laſtly the vſe and end for which we deſire it, that wee may grow thereby.</p>
               <p>Now for the firſt poynt, we muſt be as new borne babes: for Children we know are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally commended for ſimplicity, and harmleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And therefore all thoſe which will profit in the ſchoole of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and receiue light and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, by the preaching and meditation of the word, are heere taught to become as babes, to lay aſide all maliciouſnes, and to bring holy, and ſanctified heartes to the hearing of it. For we are neuer fit to heare and learne of <hi>Chriſt</hi> til we be reformed, and newly renewed and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againe, for the ſecrets of the Lord, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſayth, <hi>is with them that feare him, Pſal.</hi> 25.14 God wil not admit no ſinfull ſoules into his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, for wiſedome wil not reſt in the defiled ſoule, nor in a body that is ſubiect to ſin: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we wil haue the Lord to bleſſe our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and reading we muſt waſh and rence out the dregges of ſinne, that are frozen in vs, that is, wee muſt purge the leuen of maliciouſnes that ſoureth our ſoules, we muſt caſt vp our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe and pride, and our flothfulnes, and for this is the cauſe why there are ſo many ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and <hi>non proficient</hi> hearers of the word
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1975:35"/>becauſe there are ſo many ſinful hearers. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſhut vp this poynt, we muſt be as babes becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> reueileth knowledge and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to none but to babes. And yet we muſt not be babes only, but new borne babes, which haue new ſoules, a new life, new members, new affections imparted vnto them: for we muſt be changed and new faſhioned in euery part. And therefore they which are implanted into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are called new Creatures, becauſe neither the old heart, nor the old man, nor the old eare, nor the old eye, wil ſerue the turne: but all muſt be changed, and new framed againe, for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is borne of the fleſh is fleſh, If we wil haue it ſpirit, that is, fit for Gods worſhip, who is a ſpirit, and wil be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth, we muſt be borne againe of the ſpirit, the ſence heereof made the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> crye out <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in me a cleane heart O God, and renew a right ſpirit in me.</hi> So let vs neuer reſt ſeaſoning our ſoules, til all bee ſanctified, for then we are fit to vnderſtand euery part of Gods will, when wee bee in euery part new borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine</p>
               <p>Wee may ſee the Apoſtle maketh no other accompt of the vnregenerat then of a dead man, and therefore that they muſt be quickned and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1975:36"/>new borne againe, before they can practiſe or performe any vitall action in the life of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> is reſembled to a vine, and wee to the branckes, for that al iuyce and ſap whereby the branches ſpring, and liue, iſſueth &amp; ariſeth from the roote of the vine: So all graces and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that is in vs droppeth and diſtilleth from the riches of the perſon of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſo vntil God bleſſe our hearts they be wicked and fruitleſſe. Therfore as an vncleane fountaine cannot ſend forth ſweet water, nor a bad tree bring forth good fruit, no more can the corrupt and wicked heart of the vnregenerate, bud and bring forth any good and vertuous actions. Thus much of our condition and preparation whereby wee haue learned with how holy, and with how ſanctified affections we ought to repayre the hearing of the word of God.</p>
               <p>Now it followeth our duty and affections when we are new borne, we muſt not be chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in wauering, and inconſtancie, becauſe the Apoſtle ſayth, that <hi>God hath furniſhed his church</hi> with paſtors, and teachers, that we be noe more children wauering, and carried about with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wind of doctrine, nor we muſt not bee chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in vnderſtanding and knowledge, becauſe the ſame Apoſtle ſayth: <hi>Brethren be not children
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1975:36"/>in vnderſtanding &amp; knowledge,</hi> becauſe the ſame Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>Brethreren, bee not children in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, but in maliciouſneſſe be children, but in vnderſtanding be of a ripe age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For when we come to heare the word of God, euery man muſt reach and ſtretch out his heart; to receiue it, for then indeed the word worketh moſt effectually in vs, when our hearts before are kindled and inflamed with deſire of it. So when wee waxe warme in the ſpirit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a deſire and a thirſt of the word, it is an vndoubted token that we are borne againe, and that there is breath and a ſoule in vs, and that wee are not vtterly dead in the life of grace: Therfore we muſt deſire and imbrace the word, becauſe our faith is not able to ſuſtaine and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it ſelfe, vnleſſe it be preſently fed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with the food of life.</p>
               <p>Now we come to the matter and obiect which we muſt deſire, namely, the food and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Chriſt our Lord, which is here called the Milke of the word. By this our Sauiour recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs from all our dainties. <hi>Labour not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>for the meat which periſheth, but for the meat which endureth for euer,</hi> for the word is euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting food, and immortall ſeed, becauſe it makes vs immortall, and to laſt for euer.</p>
               <p>The word of God hath many titles and names
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1975:37"/>giuen for the benefit and nouriſhment of all true Chriſtians: it is called a lanthorne to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs, a medicine to heale vs, a guide to conduct vs, a bit to reſtraine vs, a ſword to defend vs, water to waſh vs, fire to inflame vs, ſault to ſeaſon vs, milke to nouriſh vs, and a key to vnlocke heauen gates vnto vs. It is the word of ſaluation, becauſe it ſaueth euery faithfull ſoule from damnation, it is called the word of life, becauſe it reuiueth the ſpirit, it is called the word of reconciliation, becauſe it is like a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den chaine to linke God and the faithfull toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And in regard hereof it is called a Iewel of ineſtimable price, as if all the treaſures in this world were not ſufficient to buy it. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>it is more to bee eſteemed then gold yea then much fine gold, and it is ſweeter for comfort then hony, and the hony combe. Pſal.</hi> 19. Againe in the 119 Pſal. <hi>O how ſweete are thy words vnto my throate, yea more ſweeter then hony vnto my mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Sallomon</hi> his ſonne ſetteth forth the great benefit and comfort that commeth by the word of God, vnder the title of wiſdom, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed are they that finde wiſdome, and get the vnderſtanding thereof, for the marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe thereof is better then the Marchandiſe of ſiluer, and the gaine thereof is better then gold,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1975:37"/>ſhee is more worth then precious ſtones, yea and all things that thou canſt deſire, are not to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vntò her, in her right hand is long life, and in her left hand riches and honour, her waies are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and all her pathes are peaceable, ſhee is the tree of life, to them that lay hold on her, and bleſſed is hee that entertoyneth her.</hi> Pro. 3.13.14.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſeeing the word is ſo precious, and ſo beneficial vnto euery faithful Chriſtian: let vs moſt earneſtly long and languiſh for the milke therefore: The word is reſembled to milke in three reſpects, firſt, becauſe it is the onely food of the faithful, as milke is the onely proper food for babes: ſecondly, becauſe it is not hard and intricate, but plaine and eaſie to bee conceiued: thirdly, becauſe it is ſweete and comfortable to the ſoule.</p>
               <p>For the firſt our Sauiour Chriſt fendeth vs to ſearch the Scriptures, becauſe by them we haue eternall life. And therefore it is the food whereby our ſoules muſt liue. If wee would duly conſider, that we cannot be nouriſhed vnto eternall life, but by the word of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, wee would rather wiſh our bodies might be without ſoules, then that wee ſhould want knowledge and comfort of the word.</p>
               <p>The ſecond point that the doctrine of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1975:38"/>Goſpel is plaine, when the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>All the words of his mouth are plaine and eaſie to them that will vnderſtand.</hi> Againe, <hi>the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Lord is ſure, and giueth light to the ſimple. If the Goſpell bee hid</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle,) <hi>it is hid vnto them that periſh:</hi> So that if the word of GOD bee a Lanthorne vnto our feete, and a light vnto our pathes: then it is euident that the word hath no darkeneſſe in it.</p>
               <p>The third point that the Goſpell is the onely comfort and conſolation of a faithfull ſoule, the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaith. <hi>Thy words were found by mee, and I did eate them, and thy word was vnto mee reioycing, and the ioy of my heart, thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies haue I taken for an heritage for euer, for they are the ioy of my heart.</hi> In all the ſtory of the <hi>Actes,</hi> wee ſee ioy and comfort to haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the word, ſo all true Pilgrims may haue great matter of ioy and comfort when they heare the word preached, which ſhall carry them to heauen: So that if the wicked did ſeele the calme of conſcience, the ioy of heart, the conſolation of ſpirit, and the exceeding and euerlaſting comfort in God, which the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poſſeſſe and enioy, by hearing and reading the word; they would then more gladly inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure themſelues to heare and read the word
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1975:38"/>with more diligence then they doe.</p>
               <p>Now it is to bee conſidered, the end of our hearing, that is, that wee may grow in grace, and increaſe in the faith of righteouſneſſe: for the faithfull are called the trees of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe they muſt alwayes ſpring: liuing ſtones becauſe they muſt growe in the Lords building, good ſeruants, which muſt trade and traffique the Lords Talents to increaſe, fruitfull branches, which muſt bee purged and pruned by the hand of the heauenly huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman.</p>
               <p>Therefore wee muſt not alwayes bee chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but grow vp and encreaſe, and profit more and more: for wee muſt neuer reſt walking, till wee come to God, if wee haue faith, wee muſt proceed from faith to faith, if we haue loue, we muſt encreaſe and abide in loue, if wee haue zeale, we muſt endeuour to bee conſumed with zeale, if wee bee liberall to the Saints diſtreſſed, wee muſt double our liberalitie, and that with cheerfulneſſe, if wee read the Scriptures, wee muſt goe on, and continue in prayer: ſo wee muſt ſtill increaſe, till wee come to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Let vs bee ledde forward vnto perfection. Hebrew.</hi> 6.1.</p>
               <p>As God hath ordained a heauen for all true Pilgrims, ſo hath hee appointed a way to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1975:39"/>come to it, which way hee that miſſeth, ſhall neuer come to the end of his race, for there bee many wrong wayes, as there is many errors, but there is but one right way, as there is but one truth. <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> is ſaid, not to prepare the wayes of the Lord, but the way, ſhewing that there is but one right way to life. So that the right way to heauen is by the word of God, which came from heauen, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, ſaying; <hi>All Scriptures are giuen by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God, and is profitable to doctrine, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procue, to correction, to inſtruction, which is in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly inſtructed vnto all good workes</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. And againe, it is ſaid, <hi>The Scriptures came not by man, neither by the will of man but holy men of God ſpake as they were mooued by the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore this word of truth muſt alwaies goe before vs, like the fierie pillar, to ſhew vs, when wee are in the way, and when wee are not, or elſe the broad way would ſeeme the beſt way. Therefore all they which care not for the word, goe like blind men to hell for heauen: for the Papiſt deuiſeth many wayes to come to heauen, not beeing grounded vpon the word of God, therefore they are blind leaders of the blind.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Apoſtle doth warne vs to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1975:39"/>our ſelues whether wee bee in the faith, that is, in the true faith: therefore it is not enough to beleeue, but wee muſt care how to beleeue. It is not enough to pray, but wee muſt care how wee pray. It is not enough to heare, but wee muſt care how wee heare. It is not enough to worke, but wee muſt care how wee worke, for wee cannot doe good, vnleſſe wee doe it well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now wee come to the knowledge of the perfect truth, which leadeth all true Chriſtians vnto eternall happineſſe.</head>
               <p>THerefore GOD hath prepared the right way, wherein euery true Chriſtian may learne to trauell towards Heauen, and to walke truly, and euermore to know the true way from the falſe, and is manifeſtly and truly declared by the word of God. And therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath layd downe the true foundation of this way, which is Ieſus Chriſt alone, and as hee himſelfe teſtifeth, ſaying; <hi>I am the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y the truth, and the life, that is, the true way to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. Iohn.</hi> 14.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:1975:40"/>
               <p>Therfore learne <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and learne the true and petfect way to heauen, for to learne <hi>Chriſt truly</hi> is as much as is needfull to be learned in all the whole ſcriptures, for all the ſcriptures runne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is vnto the faithfull al in al for our ſaluation, and that <hi>no man</hi> (ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>can lay any other foundation that can ſtand,</hi> he exhorteth therefore to take heed how hee buildeth, for the iudgement of the ſcriptures ſhall trye euery mans worke, that is euery mans preaching, euery mans fayth, euery mans life: And if any man build vppon this foundation, layd by <hi>Paul.</hi> I meane <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> buildeth ſurely to ſtand faſt for euer, becauſe he is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning and the end of our ſaluation: therefore he is figured in the law, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told in the Prophets, and fulfilled in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſome places poynt to his diulnity, ſome to his humanity, ſome to his kingdome, ſome to his prieſthood, ſome to his propheſie, ſoem to his conception, ſome to his birth, ſome to his life, ſome to his miracles, ſome to his paſſion, ſome to his reſurrection, ſome to his aſcention, ſome to his glorification.</p>
               <p>All poynt to our Sauiour, therefore learne <hi>Chriſt</hi> and learne all that wee may the better learne, we muſt be taught how we ſhould heare; how we ſhould pray, how we ſhould loue, how
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1975:40"/>we ſhould beleeue, and how we ſhould follow <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that we may know when we haue learned him: therefore the Apoſtle in the 13. to the Rom. ſayth, <hi>put ye on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as though this word did containe al our duties vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to put him on which ſeemes to be the leuel of this phraſe, if you mark how it commeth in, for before S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>Caſt away the works of darkneſſe, and put on the armour of light,</hi> then he nameth the workes which he ſhould put off, that is, Gluttony, Drunkenneſſe, Strife, Enuy, Chambering, wantonneſſe: After he nameth the armour of light, which hee ſhould put on, and calleth it by the name of the giuer, the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he doth not apply vertue againſt vice as one would thinke when he had ſayd caſt off Gluttony, he ſhould haue ſayd, put on ſobriety. Alſo when he ſaid caſt off wantonnes, he ſhould haue ſayd put on continency, when he ſayd, caſt off enuie, he ſhould haue ſayd, put on loue, but in ſtead of al vertues he commendeth the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for euery vertue, and oppoſeth it againſt euery vice: for his enſample wil teach him what he ſhould doe, and what he ſhould fly better then all the precepts in the world: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtuddy what this meaneth. To put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> this phraſe is read in none but S. <hi>Paul</hi> which
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1975:41"/>hath written moſt of iuſtification by Chriſt, and therefore hee vſeth all fitte phraſes, to expreſſe how wee ſhould apply Chriſt vnto vs. And in no termes hee hath ſhewed it more liuely then in this phraſe, for it ſignifyeth that Chriſt doth couer vs like a Garment, and defend vs ſafely like an armour, hee hideth our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe with his righteouſneſſe, hee couereth our diſobedience with his obedience, hee ſhadoweth our death with his death, that the wrath of God cannot finde vs, iudgement cannot ſpye vs, the curſe cannot ſee vs, but Chriſt is not our head and ſaue-gard, vnleſſe wee bee his members. Chriſt is not our Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnleſſe wee put him on: As Chriſt did put on our Garment, when hee clothed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with our fleſh, and tooke our infirmities, and bare our curſe. So wee muſt put on his Garment, that is, his righteouſneſſe, his merits, and his death, which is as ſtrange a veſture to vs, as our fleſh was to him: And much a doe wee haue to put it on, and when it is on, there is great cunning to weare it, cleanly and comely, from foyling and renting it, leaſt ſuch a precious Garment bee not taken from vs againe.</p>
               <p>Therefore many ſeeme to weare this Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1975:41"/>which ſhould bee thruſt from the banket, becauſe they weare it not as thoſe which will ſay, when the Lord ſhall come to Iudgement; Wee haue ſeene thee in our ſtreetes, wee haue heard thee in our Synagogues, and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied in thy name, wee haue caſt out Diuils in thy name: Then CHRIST will ſay vnto them, <hi>I know yee not,</hi> there is their reward, you weare not my liuery, you beare not my cognizance, for all your ſhewes, therefore depart from mee, ſo hee put them off, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had not put him on, for they had no faith to apply his merits, his mercies, his death and his righteouſneſſe vnto themſelues, without which no man can put on CHRIST, nor weare him, for faith is the hand which putteth him on, ſaith firſt taketh his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and couereth her vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then ſhee taketh his obedience, and couereth her diſobedience; then ſhee taketh his patience and couereth her impatience, and ſo taketh one vertue after another, and tricketh her ſelfe vntill ſhe haue put on IESVS CHRIST, that is, vntill ſhee appeare in the ſight of Almighty GOD like IESVS CHRIST, cloathed with his merites and graces, that GOD hath no power
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1975:42"/>to be angry with her becauſe ſhee commeth ſo like his ſonne.</p>
               <p>This is to put on <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and this is the wedding Garment, without the which no man can feaſt with the Lord, this garment is called an armour becauſe it defendeth vs from all the aſſaults of the deuill, the fleſh, and the world: this garment is called a light, becauſe it is the beauty and glory of them which weare it, this garment is called a kingdome, becauſe none but Kings do weare it, that is they which are inthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the kingdome of <hi>Christ</hi> and made kinges ouer the world, the fleſh, and the diuill.</p>
               <p>This Garment Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſent vnto vs, to goe before the king of Heauen and earth: A holy garment, a royall garment, an immaculate Garment, an euerlaſting Garment, whereof euery hemme is peace of conſcience, euery pleat is ioy in the holy Ghoſt, euery ſtitch is the remedy of ſome ſinne, and ſaueth them which weare it.</p>
               <p>Thus if wee put on <hi>Christ,</hi> wee are clothed with his obedience, whereby our wickedneſſe is couered, wee are clothed with his merites, whereby our ſinnes are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, wee are clothed with his holy ſpirit
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1975:42"/>whereby our heartes are mollified, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and renewed, til we reſemble <hi>Christ</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>This is the Apoſtles meaning to put on <hi>CHRIST,</hi> ſo that to put on <hi>CHRIST</hi> is to put on the new man with all his vertues vntill we bee renewed to the Image of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> which is like a new man amongſt men, they which labour to be righteous, and yet beleeue that <hi>CHRISTS</hi> righteouſneſſe ſhall ſaue them, and haue put on <hi>CHRIST</hi> truely, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would haue them, and then wee ſhall heare the voyce: Thy ſinnes are forgiuen, and then wee ſhall haue that bleſſing thy ſinnes are coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>Hee doth not put on <hi>CHRIST</hi> but put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth off <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and putteth on Beliall, which faſhioneth himſelfe to God and to the world; for as <hi>Chriſts</hi> coate was without ſeame, ſoe, they muſt bee without ſtayne that weare it, therefore when we haue put on this gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we muſt waſh our ſelues, and pick our wayes, and chuſe our worke, that is we muſt not thinke as we did, nor ſpeake as wee did, but remember that we haue changed our mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and to ſerue him with whom wee are bound.</p>
               <p>Now to learne further how wee may apply
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1975:43"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> vnto vs, the text wil catechiſe it in three names, that is, <hi>Lord, Ieſus, Chriſt,</hi> the Apoſtle ſeemeth to ſpell out the way vnto vs how we ſhould weare this garment.</p>
               <p>Firſt we muſt put him on as Lord, then wee muſt put him on as <hi>Ieſus;</hi> laſtly we muſt put him on as <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Firſt as <hi>Lord,</hi> that is our ruler to command vs, our tutor to gouerne vs, and our Maiſter to direct vs, we muſt be no mans ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant but his, we muſt alſo put him on as <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that is our Sauiour in whom we truſt, our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector on whom we depend, our redeemer on whom we beleeue, we muſt not looke for our ſaluation from Angells, nor Saintes, nor any thing beſides him, for the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Sauiour, and is giuen to none but to him, for he is the only Sauiour; therefore when hee is called our ſaluation, it implyeth that there is no ſauiour beſides him. Alſo wee muſt put him on as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is a king to rule, a Prophet to teach, a prieſt to pray and ſacrifice and to pacifie the wrath of God for vs.</p>
               <p>For the name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth ſignifie that he was anointed a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet for man. A King to rule him, a Prieſt to ſacrifice for him, a Prophet to teach him; So then wee put on Chriſt as Lord, which worſhippeth none but
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1975:43"/>him, we put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>Ieſus</hi> which beleeueth in none but him, we put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> which heareth none but him, beleeueth in none but him, furthermore when wee put <hi>Chriſt</hi> firſt on, is when we are baptiſed, then we are ſealed and conſecrated to his ſeruice. For ſo ſoone as we came into the world we vowed to renounce the world, the fleſh, and the Deuill, and to ſerue God, we haue put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> againe, when we are called and ſanctified, that is, when wee caſt off the old man, which is corrupt with the luſts of the fleſh, and the pride of this life, with the cares of this world, and put on the new man which is regenerate, in righteouſnes and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the Image of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> againe when wee receiue his holy ſacrament, and are partakers of his body and blood, that is, the merites of his obedience and paſſion by fayth, then <hi>Chriſt</hi> is become ours and dwelleth in vs, and feedeth vs with his grace to eternall life.</p>
               <p>Now when wee haue put on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in theſe three ſortes, which is our garment for this world, after we ſhal put on <hi>Chriſt</hi> in heauen, and bee clothed with his glory, and that ſhall bee our laſt veſture, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer weare out. Thus hath it beene ſet downe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1975:44"/>what is meant by putting on Chriſt, to clothe our ſelues with his righteouſneſſe and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that is, to beleeue that his righteouſneſſe ſhall ſupply our vnrighteouſneſſe, and his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, ſhall ſtand for our ſufferings, becauſe hee came to fulfill the law, and beare the croſſe, and ſatisfie his Father for vs, that all which beleeue in him, might not dye, but haue life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>And that wee may the better, and with more ſtrength, bee able to walke in this our right path and way towards heauen, wee muſt pray vnto our mercifull God, and with all our diligence ſeeke vnto the meanes for the obtayning the Iewell of our ſaluation, that is, a liuely iuſtifying faith, according to the faith of Gods elect, which faith is not mans opinion and conceit, as when they heare the ſtory of the Goſpell, and withall there followeth no good workes, nor amendment of life, though they heare, yea and ſpeake many things of faith, but a right faith is the gift of God, as the Apoſtle ſaith, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from him, and wrought by the holy Ghoſt in vs, and changeth vs, turneth vs into a new nature, and begetteth vs a new in God, as we may read in the firſt of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and killeth the old man, and maketh vs altogether new in heart, minde, and will, and in all our affections and powers of the ſoule, and bringeth the Holy
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1975:44"/>Ghoſt with her: this faith is a liuely thing, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in working, valiant and ſtrong, euer dooing, euer fruitfull, ſo that it is vnpoſſble that hee which is endued therewith, ſhould not liue a godly and an holy life, and alwayes bring forth fruites of good workes.</p>
               <p>Such is his nature, for quick faith in the heart, and liuely moouing of the ſpirit driueth him, and ſtirreth him therevnto. Faith then is a liuely and a ſtedfaſt truſt in the fauour of God, wherewith we commit our ſelues altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and that truſt is ſurely grounded in our hearts, by the word of God, that it cannot bee remooued with any tribulation. And ſuch truſt wrought by the holy Ghoſt, through faith, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man, glad, luſtie, cheerefull, and true-harted vnto God, and vnto all creatures, ſo that it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to ſeperate good life and good workes from this faith, euen as it is impoſſible to ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate heate and burning from the fire: Therefore take heed to thy ſelfe and beware of thine owne fantaſies, and imagination, which to iudge of, faith and good workes, that thou wilt ſeeme wiſe, when in deed thou art ſtarke blind: Pray vnto GOD therefore, that hee will in mercy vouchſafe to worke this true faith in thine heart, or elſe ſhalt thou remaine euermore faithleſſe.</p>
               <p>Now it is for euery true Chriſtian to know
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1975:45"/>and vnderſtand that they are accepted, iuſtified, and at peace with God, only through fayth in <hi>Chriſt</hi> our ſauiour, and that workes are to be ſet apart, in the only poynt, to bee any cauſe of our iuſtification with fay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet hope and charity follow the ſame ſaith, by which we are iuſtified, in the regenerate that are the Children of God, yet wee are not iuſtified by them, no nor by fayth as of it owne vertue, otherviſe then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally, as apprehending the righteouſnes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is without vs, and is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ours then by imputation: for as a good tree hath good fruites neceſſarily, ſo hath a right fayth good life and good workes, but then good workes though they bee not ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from fayth, yet they are ſeperated from being any cauſe of iuſtification with fayth; As the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> maketh diuers and ſundry arguments for the proofe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>As in the 3. to the <hi>Rom:</hi> 20.21.22. &amp;c. where he teſtifieth that by the workes of the law no fleſh could be iuſtified in the ſight of God, for by the law commeth the knowledge of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But now</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>is the righteouſneſſe of God made manifeſt without the law, hauing witnes of the Law and the prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:1975:45"/>
               <p>To wit, the righteouſneſſe of God, by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, vnto all, and vpon all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
               <p>For there is no difference, for al haue ſinned, and are depriued of the glory of God.</p>
               <p>But are iuſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Whom God hath ſet forth to be a reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through faith in his bloud, to declare his righteouſneſſe, by the forgiueneſſe of the ſinnes that are paſt.</p>
               <p>To ſhew at this time his righteouſneſſe, that he might be iuſt, and the iuſtifier of him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth of Ieſus Chriſt. Now the Apoſtle when he had teſtified, that wee are iuſtified by grace through faith, and not by workes concludeth by poſing a queſtion and giuing anſwer thereunto, ſaying, <hi>where then is thy reioycing? it is excluded, by what law? of workes, nay but by the law of faith,</hi> affirming with a concluſion, wee hold that a man is iuſtified by ſaith without the works of the law.</p>
               <p>Againe know this that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the law, but by the faith of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and we haue beleeued in Ieſus Chriſt, that we might be iuſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the workes of the law, becauſe that by the workes of the law no fleſh ſhalbe iſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:1975:46"/>
               <p>For if there had been a law giuen which could haue giuen life, ſurely then righteouſneſſe ſhould haue beene by the law, but the Scripture hath concluded all vnder ſinne, that the promiſe by the faith of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſhould bee giuen vnto them that beleeue. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21.22.</p>
               <p>Yee are aboliſhed from Chriſt ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, whoſoeuer are iuſtified by the law, yee are fallen from grace, for wee through the ſpirit waite for the hope of righteouſneſſe through faith. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.4.5.</p>
               <p>Againe, by grace wee are faued through faith, and that not of our ſelues, it is the gift of God, not of workes, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for wee are his workemanſhip created in Chriſt Ieſus, vnto good workes, which GOD hath ordeyned, that wee ſhould walke in them. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8.9.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſaith, that the promiſe that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſhould bee heire of the world, was not to <hi>Abraham,</hi> or to his ſeed through the law, but through the righteouſneſſe of faith, for if they which are of the law bee heires, then is faith but vaine, and the promiſe made of none effect. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13.14.</p>
               <p>For if righteouſneſſe come of the law, then is Chriſt dead in vaine. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.21.</p>
               <p>Beſides many other places in the Scriptures,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1975:46"/>which tend to the ſame purpoſe, as to the <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.9, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.6, <hi>Titus.</hi> 3.5, 2. Tim. 1.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4.</p>
               <p>Now it followeth, to bring ſome arguments and reaſons, to prooue, that man is iuſtified by faith onely, and not by workes.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that whereby man ſhall liue, for euer, by that alſo hee ſhall be iuſtified.</p>
               <p>By faith in Chriſt Ieſus, man ſhall liue, for euer, <hi>ergo,</hi> by faith alſo man ſhall be iuſtified. For, as wee attaine to eternall life for Chriſt his ſake, beeing apprehended by faith: So, for his ſake wee are pronounced for iuſt, and abſolued from the guilt and puniſhment of eternall death, therefore theſe two propoſitions are conuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. A man iuſtified ſhall liue for euer, and a man liuing for euer is iuſtified, theſe effects of iuſtification is in the holy Scriptures attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto this onely cauſe Faith, for what is more knowne then that ſaying; <hi>So GOD lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the world, that hee hath giuen his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſayd by the Prophet <hi>Abacuck.</hi> 2.4. <hi>The iust man ſhall liue by his faith,</hi> and what is more manifeſt then that, beeing iuſtified by faith, wee are at peace with GOD. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:1975:47"/>
               <p>So then, if man bee iuſtified by his faith, that is by the righteouſneſſe of another, to wit, Chriſt apprehended by faith, then is hee not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by his owne righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>For man is ſaued either by his owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, or by the righteouſneſſe of another.</p>
               <p>But man is ſaued by the righteouſneſſe of another, namely by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, as is declared by <hi>Abacuk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> man is not ſaued by his own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherefore if man ſhould bee iuſtifyed by his workes, then ſhould hee alſo liue by his workes.</p>
               <p>But by the teſtimony of <hi>Baruk,</hi> man ſhall not liue by his workes, but by faith onely.</p>
               <p>For workes that are wicked, and doe nothing elſe but prouoke Gods wrath, deſerue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or recompence, much leſſe doe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue righteouſneſſe and eternall life.</p>
               <p>But the workes of all men are wicked, and doe nothing elſe but prouoke GODS wrath, <hi>ergo,</hi> the workes of no man but CHRIST onely deſerue any reward or recompence, much leſſe doe they deſerue righteouſneſſe and eternall life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:1975:47"/>
               <head>How Faith doth iustifie, and how workes.</head>
               <p>GOD doth commend vnto all the world, the adioyning of outward workes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward faith. Conſonant vnto which is <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, when hee requireth a faith that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by loue, and telleth vs, that aſwell with the mouth wee confeſſe vnto righteouſneſſe, as with the heart beleeue vnto ſaluation. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. Alſo our Sauiour him-ſelfe, who requireth to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acknowledging of him in the heart, the outward profeſſion of him before men. <hi>Math.</hi> 10 This is that which <hi>S. Iames</hi> meaneth, where hee ſaith <hi>Abraham</hi> our father was iuſtified by works, when hee offered <hi>Iſaack</hi> vpon the Aultar, <hi>ſeest thou not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that the faith wrought with his workes, and through the workes, was the faith made perfect, &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>Abraham</hi> by this meanes was knowne and declared to be iuſtified, and his faith beeing effectuall and fruitfull by workes, was thereby knowne to bee a true faith, and not a ded faith, for <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſpeaketh not of the cauſes of iuſtification, but by what effects we may know that a man is iuſtified, true is the diſtinction therefore euen of Schoolemen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Chriſt doth iuſtifie a man effectiue,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1975:48"/>effectiuely by working his iuſtification, faith doth iuſtifie a man apprehenſiue by apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, becauſe it taketh hold of Chriſt, who is our iuſtifier. And workes doe iuſtifie alſo, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue, declaringly, becauſe they ſhew that a man is iuſtified, as hath beene ſaid: ſo Chriſt, faith, and workes doe all iuſtifie, but diuerſly. Alſo it is that <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith, workes are <hi>via regni,</hi> but not <hi>cauſa regnandi,</hi> that is the way to the kingdome, but not the cauſe of the raigning there.</p>
               <p>And now wee ſee and vnderſtand that faith being the onely ſpeciall meane for euery true Chriſtian to attaine vnto ſaluation, and Chriſt Ieſus the ſpeciall cauſe thereof: therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth euery child of God to imbrace the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Goſpel, ſeeing God doth ſo mighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe the preaching of the ſame to beget faith, &amp; to confirm the ſame in the hearts of the elect, &amp; ſo to bring them to ſaluation: We ſhold great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therfore eſteem of the preaching of the word, and haue it in great price, as in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.21.24. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.25.</p>
               <p>The grace of God and ſaluation is giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them onely that haue faith and beleeue in Chriſt, for they onely are iuſtified: <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16.</p>
               <p>Therefore neither doth ſaluation nor the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1975:48"/>doctrine therefore belong at all vnto infidels or vnbeleeuers. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.18.</p>
               <p>As vnto the beleeuers the Goſpel is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God vnto ſaluation: ſo vnto the vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers it is the ſauor of death vnto death, becauſe they either condemn or corrupt it. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15.16</p>
               <p>The promiſe of ſaluation belongeth not onely vnto certaine men, as Prophets, Apoſtles, but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally vnto all beleeuers. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no man ought to diſpaire or to thinke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, but repent &amp; beleeue only. Lu. 8.50</p>
               <p>The Maieſty and excellency of the goſpell muſt needs be great, ſeeing in times paſt it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by the Prophets as a ſingular and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble guift: &amp; being thus promiſed was commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in wryting for the perpetuall nouriſhing of the hope of the faithfull.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel or Euangel by the very ſound and ſignification of the word, is diſcerned from the law, the goſpell to ſpeake properly, is not a doctrine teaching precepts or perfecter Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels then the law of God, but a doctrine bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from heauen moſt ioyfull newes, touching the ſauiour, and grace of God in Chriſt, towards all ſuch as by faith lay hold on the Mediator.</p>
               <p>Hereupon Chriſt ſaid that the eies and eares of his diſciples were happie, when they had heard the preaching of the Goſpell, and ſeene the ſame
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1975:49"/>confirmed with miracles, for that they ſaw and heard thoſe things which many Kings and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets deſired to ſee &amp; heare, and yet could not: But wee at this day are no leſſe happy then the Diſciples, yea we are much more happy now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were then, for albeit they ſaw Chriſt in the fleſh, and heard him teach, yea at that time, they had not heard that hee died for vs, and that our ſins being altogether waſhed away by his death, &amp; that he had riſen againe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, &amp; aſcended into heauen, and ſat at the right hand of God the father, all which are in the goſpel declared to vs.</p>
               <p>By the bookes of the new Teſtament we bee taught alſo, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> afore promiſed, which is God aboue all things, moſt bleſſed for euer, euen he which was ſhadowed in the bookes of the old Teſtament, and in ſacrifices figured, that he was ſent at the laſt from the father, the ſelf ſame time which the father did conſtitute within himſelf, at that time when all wickedneſſe abounded in the world, &amp; then he was ſent, &amp; this Ieſus our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, being borne in the fleſh, ſuffered death, and roſe again from the dead, which acts of his, were not done by him in reſpect of the good works of any man (for we are all ſinners) but that this God our father ſhould appeare true in exhibiting the abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t riches of his grace which he promiſed, and that through his mercy he might bring vs to ſaluation.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:1975:49"/>
               <p>Wherevpon it is euidently ſhewed in the new Teſtament, that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> being the Lambe, the true ſacrifice of the world, putting away the ſins of men, came into this world to purchaſe grace and peace for vs with the father, waſhing vs from our ſinnes in his blood, &amp; ſhould deliuer vs from the bondage of the Diuill, whom by ſinne wee did ſerue, and ſo we ſhould bee adopted by him to be the ſonnes of God, and heires with him of that moſt excellent and euerlaſting kingdome.</p>
               <p>Now that we ſhould acknowledge this ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and excellent benefit of God towards vs, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God giueth vs his holy ſpirit, the fruit, &amp; effect of which is faith in God, &amp; in his Chriſt, for without the holy Ghoſt, by which we are inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted &amp; ſealed, neither can we beleeue that God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father ſent <hi>Meſſias,</hi> nor yet that <hi>Ieſus</hi> is <hi>Chriſt:</hi> So <hi>no man,</hi> ſaith, <hi>S. Paul, can ſay that Ieſus is the Lord, but by the holy Ghoſt the ſame ſpirit witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to our ſpirits, that we are the children of God, and powreth into our bowels, that charity which S. Paul deſcribeth to the Corinthians.</hi> Furthermore, that holy ſpirit doth giue vs hope, which is a ſure looking for eternall life, whereof hee himſelfe is the certaine token and pledge.</p>
               <p>Alſo hee giueth vs ſpirituall gifts, of which <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> therefore the benefit of faith is not to be deſpiſed, or ſo little
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1975:50"/>to be ſet by, for by the meanes of this truſt and fayth in <hi>Chriſt</hi> which worketh by charity, and ſheweth it ſelfe forth by the works of harit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y moouing men therevnto, we are iuſtified and ſanctified, that is to ſay, God the father of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> which is made our father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by him being our brother, doth accompt vs to be iuſt and holy through his grace, &amp; through the merit of his ſonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> not imputing our ſinnes to vs ſo farre forth, that wee ſhould ſuffer the paines of hell for them.</p>
               <p>Finally <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe came into the world to the intent that we through him being ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and clenſed from our ſinnes, following his will in good workes, ſhould deny the things pertaining to the fleſh, and freely ſerue him in righteouſnes and holines all the dayes of our liues: And that by good works which God hath prepared for vs to walke in, we ſhould ſhew our ſelues to be called to his grace and gift of faith, which good workes and life who ſo hath not doth ſhew himſelfe not to haue ſuch a faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as is required in vs.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt we come, and follow him with acheerefull mind, that he may teach vs, for he is our maiſter lowly and humble of heart, he is to vs an example wherby we muſt learn the rule to liue well.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:1975:50"/>
               <p>Moreouer he is our Biſhop and our high prieſt, which did himſelfe offer vp for vs his owne blood, being the only mediator, betweene God and men, who now ſitteth at the right hand of God the father, being made our aduocate, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king interceſſion for vs, who doubtles ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for vs whatſoeuer we ſhal deſire either of him or elſe of his father in his name if ſo be that we thus deſiring ſhal beleeue, that he wil ſo do: for thus hath he promiſed, therefore let vs not doubt, if we ſinne at any time, to come with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and with ſure truſt to the throane of his grace, with this beleefe, that wee ſhal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mercy, for therefore came hee into the world, that hee might ſaue ſinners by his grace.</p>
               <p>This is verily <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> which ſhall come at a certaine time appoynted by his father, and ſhal ſit in great maieſty to iudge all men, and to render to euery man the workes of his body, according to that he hath done whether it bee good or euill, And he ſhall ſay to them which ſhall be on the right ſide, which in this world did looke for the good things to come, that is to ſay life euerlaſting. <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enioy the kingdome that hath beeene prepared for you from the beginning of the world,</hi> but to them which ſhall be on the left hand, he ſhal ſay
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1975:51"/>
                  <hi>Depart from me yee curſed into euerlaſting fire pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared for the Deuill and his Angells,</hi> and then ſhal the end be, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> hauing vanquiſhed all manner of enemies, ſhall deliuer vp the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to God the father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A breefe Deſcription of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHriſt</hi> is deſcribed firſt by his perſon, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly by his office. In his perſon wee are to note firſt, that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is true God, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he is true man, thirdly, that the perſon of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is but one, in which there is, to wit, the deuine and the humane natures.</p>
               <p>He is prooued to be God, becauſe hee is the ſonne of God and becauſe his deuine maieſty is declared by vndoubted teſtimonies, firſt, by his might and power in working miracles, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by his eſſentiall ſanctity, and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his reſurrection from the dead, becauſe hee quickned and gaue life vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The office of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is heere breefely touched,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1975:51"/>firſt, becauſe hee is <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that is the ſauiour of his people. <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.21. ſecondly becauſe he is, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is anoynted with the fulneſſe of the ſpirit aboue meaſure, <hi>Eſay</hi> 61.1. Pſal. 45.7. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.34. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.38. to be a Prophet a Prieſt and a King. and ſo our Lord, not only by reaſon of our creation, but eſpecially becauſe he bought vs with his blood, and purchaſed vs for peculiar people and Church for himſelfe.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt to the <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 30. ſaith, that <hi>Christ</hi> is made of God the father righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vnto vs; and that is to be conſidered, in two poyntes firſt is in diſcharging vs of our ſinnes, and the puniſhments due for the ſame, the ſecond is in preſenting ve blameleſſe before his heauenly father in ſuch perfect obedience as the law cannot reprooue, or iuſtly charge with any want of obedience, according as the Apoſtle ſayth, that <hi>Christ</hi> is the end, of the law, for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to all that beleeue.</p>
               <p>That is, <hi>Christ</hi> hath fulfilled the whole law, and therefore as many as haue true fayth in him are compted righteous before God as if they had fulfilled the law themſelues.</p>
               <p>And alſo diſcharged the puniſhments which were due for our ſinnes, and ſo thereby wee are receiued vnto grace, and accepted before
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1975:52"/>God as righteous in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Prophet declareth plainely of Chriſts obedience, ſaying; <hi>Hee hath onely taken on him our infirmities, and borne our paines, and was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for our offences, and ſmitten for our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for the paine of our puniſhments was layde vpon him, and with his ſtripes are wee healed.</hi> Eſa. 53.2.3.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe Saint <hi>Peter</hi> affirming, that Chriſt his owne ſelfe bare our ſinnes in his body, on the tree, that wee beeing deliuered from ſinne, ſhould liue vnto righteouſneſſe, by whoſe ſtripes wee are healed. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24.</p>
               <p>All this is performed in Chriſt for vs, who hath ſatisfied in his ſufferings for our ſinnes, and wrought our full diſcharge, in that hee perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept the whole law, and euery commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, in the behalfe of vs that bee his, for hee beeing God and aboue the law, as Lord and giuer thereof, needed not to haue bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſubiect therevnto for himſelfe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it appeareth plainly, that hee went vnder that obedience in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> names, and for vs, and that the ſame obedience of his is auaileable for vs that bee his, as it is written, that as by one man his diſobedience, many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one, (which is Chriſt) ſhall many alſo be made righteous.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:1975:52"/>
               <p>The tree muſt bee good before the fruite bee good, and therefore wee our ſelues muſt bee made righteous before any good fruits of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe proceed by faith, as righteous in Chriſt, whoe is made of God the Father our righteouſneſſe, before the Lord will take in good part any thing that ſhall proceede from vs.</p>
               <p>For the Apoſtle prooueth plainely, that our good workes, and holyneſſe of life, going before, doe not iuſtifie vs, or make vs righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
               <p>For it is written, that God which is rich in mercy, for his great loue wherewith hee loued vs, euen when wee were dead in ſinnes, hath quickened vs, together with Chriſt, by whoſe grace we are ſaued. <hi>Epheſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore no workes then thoſe went before to quicken vs, ſeeing it is ſayd, that when wee were dead in ſinnes, not onely ſinnes, but dead in ſinne. God hath quickened vs: This prooueth plainly, that our good workes and holyneſſe of life did not procure righteouſneſſe to bee in vs, when the matter is cleare that wee are dead in ſinnes, when he in mercy quickned vs.</p>
               <p>So that wee ate not to looke for any righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to bee in vs, but onely in and by Chriſt, whoe is made of GOD the Father
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1975:53"/>righteouſnes vnto vs, according as the Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith to the Cor. that <hi>Chriſt is made ſinne for vs which knew no ſinne, that we might be made the righteouſnes of God in him,</hi> it is not that Chriſt did ſinne, for in him was no ſinne at all.</p>
               <p>But by way of imputation, that is, our ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imputed vnto him and he take them vppon him, whereby his righteouſnes was imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that we might be made &amp; accepted righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before God in him.</p>
               <p>We muſt therefore bee grafted into Chriſt and then draw power from him to bring forth fruit that ſhall be pleaſing vnto him, and acceptable in his fight, according as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſayth, <hi>As the branch cannot beare fruit of it ſelfe, except it abide in the Vine, noe more can yee, except yee abide in Me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus is Chriſt made our Redeemer, Deliuerer, Reconciler, Mediator, Interceſſor, Aduocate, Hope, Comfort, Protector, Defendor, Strength, Health, Satiſfaction, and Saluation, his blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhedding, his death, and all that euer he did is ours, and doth euery true faithfull Chriſtian as good ſeruice, as though they had done it themſelues, ſo that Chriſt hath left nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>done
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1975:53"/>that might pertaine to our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Thus haue wee found the hidden treaſure which hee that findeth it truely, will ſell all that euer he hath, or euer he would looſe it, as <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaith in the 16. to the Rom. 25. verſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:1975:54"/>
               <head>The Path of a Chriſtian to walke in.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW it followeth in this fourth part, to learne and know how all true Chriſtians ſhould walke in the truth of this way, for as Chriſt is the onely way it ſelfe, ſo is hee alſo the truth, whereby wee muſt walke, for all the wayes of God are truth and mercy both, for who ſo doth feare the Lord, him will hee teach, and direct ſuch with his ſpirit to follow the right way. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.12.</p>
               <p>Wherefore receaue the truth, loue the truth, and beleeue the truth, otherwayes if thou refuſe the bread of life, and digge vnto thy ſelfe a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne that will hold no water: then ſhalt thou lead thy dayes in wilfulneſſe, and dye in ſinne, thy bloud ſhall bee vpon thine owne head, and thou ſhalt not ſee the glory of God, death and damnation ſhall bee thy portion, becauſe thou hadſt pleaſure in wickedneſſe, and didſt not giue thy heart to receiue, loue, and beleeue the truth. To this end the Apoſtle exhorteth the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uians,</hi> ſaying. <hi>Wee beſeech you bretheren, &amp; exhort you in the Lord Ieſus, that yee increaſe more and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1975:54"/>more, as yee haue receiued of vs, how yee ought to walke and to pleaſe God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is, as the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you not, nor vſe any force, but intreat you with all patience and meekneſſe, that you will haue a regard, and loue your owne ſoules, and thinke and doe thoſe things which may pleaſe God: you are they to whom the promiſe was made, God hath called you out of darkneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his maruelous light, hee hath not dealt ſo with euery nation, neither haue they knowne his iudgments. <hi>Wee come not to you in our owne name,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We haue charge to preach the Goſpell to all nations, therefore wee ſpeake vnto you in the name of our Lord Ieſus Christ, wee ſhew you the way that you may walke in it, wee declare vnto you the will of God, that you may be ſaued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee haue opened vnto you the whole treaſure of Gods mercy, wee haue led you to the throane of grace, and made you ſee the Lambe of God, that taketh away the ſinnes of the world, wee haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto you the remiſſion and forgiueneſſe of your ſinnes through his name, if you beleeue you ſhall bee ſaued, if any man preach vnto you other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you haue receaued let him bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is not enough that yee beleeue, yee muſt alſo walke and liue accordingly to knowledge, this is the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1975:55"/>will of God, for wee are his workemanſhip created in Chriſt Ieſus to good workes, which God hath ordained that wee ſhould walke in them</hi> Ephe. 2. <hi>For the grace of God hath appeared that bringeth ſaluation vnto all men, and teacheth vs that wee ſhould liue ſoberly, and righteouſly, and godly, in this life, looking for the bleſſed hope and appearing of the glory of the mighty God, and of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> Titus 2.</p>
               <p>In this ſort, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>hath our teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been among you, that you might ſhew forth your faith by your workes, for it auaileth you nothing to ſay you haue faith if you haue no workes, becauſe the faith that hath no workes is dead: thus wee are taught by the workes of our Lord Ieſus,</hi> hee ſaith not euery one that ſaith, <hi>vnto me Lord, Lord, ſhal enter into the kingdome of heauen, but he that doth my Fathers wil that is in heauen. Againe euery tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewen downe and caſt into the fire.</hi> Thus hath our Lord God commanded vs to be like our Father which is in heauen, to let our light ſo ſhine before men that they may ſee our good works, thus the Apoſtle taught, thus the Church of God this day teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, it requireth faith as the inſtrument and meanes to apply the merits and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt for our ſaluation, and good workes, as fruites, and witneſſes of our faith. Whoſoeuer
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1975:55"/>learneth aright and beleeueth the Goſpel as he ought, groweth, and goeth forward from vertue to vertue, if he were ignorant before, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thereby to knowledge, if he were weake, he groweth in ſtrength, if hee were wicked, hee turneth vnto godlineſſe. For as we haue beene taught that wee are ſaued by faith in Chriſt, without the works of the law, which doctrine, though it be moſt true, &amp; moſt ſoundly proued and flatly concluded <hi>Ro.</hi> 3.16. yet being vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood a miſſe as <hi>Pauls</hi> writings ſometimes are 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.28. it hath beene the decay of all good deeds and brought in Epicuriſme, &amp; al vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: it is true in deed, that eternal life is the gift of God through Ieſus Chriſt <hi>Ro</hi> 6.23. yet this gift is beſtowed only vpon thoſe for whom it is prepared <hi>Math:</hi> 20.23. &amp; which haue exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed themſelues in the workes of mercy. <hi>Math:</hi> 25.35. for in reſpect of God our election ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſure, &amp; certaine from al eternity, for it hath his ſeale, <hi>The Lord knoweth them are his.</hi> 2. Tim: 2.19. <hi>and I know whom I haue choſen.</hi> Ioh. 13.18. but in reſpect of our ſelues it is vncertaine, and therfore we muſt ſtriue to make our calling &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure by good works, albeit it is ſure in it ſelf, for aſmuch as God cannot change, yet wee muſt confirme it in our ſelues by the fruits of the ſpirit knowing that the purpoſe of God, electeth
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1975:56"/>leth, ſanctifieth, and iuſtifieth vs, theſe are the wayes to come to heauen, though they bee not the cauſe for <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the only cauſe, therefore we muſt keepe the way if euer wee meane to come to heauen.</p>
               <p>For as we are ordained to the end, ſo are we ordained to the meanes which bring vs to the end: If God hath predeſtinated any to eternall life he hath alſo predeſtinated them to the means whereby they muſt attaine eternall life, that is faith and a good conſeience.</p>
               <p>For the end of Gods law is loue, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without a good conſcience, neither a good conſcience without faith, nor fayth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou the word of God: therefore it is certaine that whoſoeuer is to be ſaued ſhal at one time or other, before they depart out of this life bee called truely to beleeue, and ſhal endeauour by all meanes as <hi>Paul</hi> did to keepe a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God and man Acts 24.16.</p>
               <p>For that which is ſpoken of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in ſpecial in 40. <hi>Pſal. thou haſt loed righteouſnes and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iniquity,</hi> muſt be verrified, and in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure accompliſhed in al the members of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they muſt loue righteouſnes and hate iniquity, &amp; this is the difference that the Apoſtle putteth betweene the children of God &amp; the children of the Deuil, that the children of God both loue &amp;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1975:56"/>do righteouſneſſe, and the children of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill loue ſinne, and doe it 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.6.7. Let no man therefore thinke that he is predeſtinated to ſaluation, vnleſſe he feele, and find in himſelfe the effects, and fruits of predeſtination, for thoſe whom God hath predeſtinated, them alſo in his good time he calleth. <hi>Ro:</hi> 8.29.30. not vnto vncleanneſſe, but vnto holineſſe. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.7. and whom he hath called, them alſo hee iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and indueth, with the grace of ſanctification <hi>Ro.</hi> 6. and whom he iuſtifieth, them alſo he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth, <hi>Ro.</hi> 8 if any be ingrafted into <hi>Chriſt</hi> by a liuely fayth, hee cannot but bring forth the fruit of god life. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. And whoſoeuer doth not bring forth ſuch fruit, it is a certaine note that he is not yet grafted into <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>None can ſay that they are grafted in <hi>Chriſt</hi> and ſhall be ſaued by him, but only thoſe in whom the new worke of regeneration is wrought, and doe by the inward work of the ſpirit feele <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be theirs, for it is the ſanctifiing ſpirit that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth feeling in this point. For as the Vine branch cannot liue and bring forth fruit, except it abide in the Vine, no more can we except we abide in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and be truely grafted in him by a liuely fayth, none can haue any benefit by him, but they only which dwell in him, none can liue by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but they which are changed into
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:1975:57"/>Chriſt, none are partakers of his body, but they only which are in his body, none can be ſaued by Chriſt crucified, but they which are crucified with Chriſt, noue can liue with him being dead but thoſe which die with him being aliue. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs roote downward in mortification, that we may ſhoote vpward in ſanctification. Let vs dye to ſinne, that we may liue to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. Let vs dye while we are aliue that wee may liue when we are dead.</p>
               <p>Let vs not therefore flatter nor deceiue our ſelues, as though we had true fayth, when wee haue not the true fruites of fayth: for as the ſun cannot be without light, nor the fire without heat, no more can a ſauing faith bee without good workes, which are the fruites and effects thereof. The penitent theef had but a ſhort time of repentance: yet in that ſhort time, he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no good works to declare his fayth by <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.40.41. for no ſooner was it giuen him to beleeue in Chriſt but that preſently he maketh anſwer on the behalfe of Chriſt, and cleareth him of all amiſſe, herebuketh his fellow for his incredulity, he confeſſeth the greatneſſe of their ſinne, and their iuſt puniſhment for the ſame, he acknowledgeth Chriſt to be the Lord, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vppon him.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is not enough for vs to ſay we
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1975:57"/>haue faith, the diuills haue a kinde of faith, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.19. nor it is not enough for vs to come to the Church onely, and to call vpon the Lord: for to ſay Lord, Lord, wil not ſerue thy turne: <hi>Math.</hi> 7.21. nor it is not enough for the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to preach vnto vs, for vnto ſome that haue preached in the name of Chriſt, it ſhal be ſaide at the laſt day, <hi>Depart I know you not,</hi> it is not enough for vs to be onely hearers of the word, for then we deceiue our ſelues <hi>Ia.</hi> 1.22. but you that ſay you haue faith muſt ſhew it by your deedes. <hi>Ia.</hi> 2.17. And you that come to call vppon the Lord muſt depart from iniquity, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 19. And they that preach vnto vs muſt practiſe that themſelues which they preach, and be an example of holy life for vs to follow. 1. <hi>Pet</hi> 5.3. and we that are hearers of the word, muſt be doers of the ſame: and then we ſhall be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p>There are 10. ſpecial notes to be required of al thoſe that ſhal be able to walke in this holy &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly way, which leadeth to eternal ſaluation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is he muſt be a new creature 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly he muſt haue fayth according to Gods elect, &amp; therby we are at peace with God.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly he muſt not liue after the luſt of men but after the will of God. 1, <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.2.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:1975:58"/>4. Fourthly hee muſt walke as Chriſt hath walked <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.6.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly he muſt not walke after the fleſh but after the ſpirit. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sixthly he muſt be zealous of good works. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Seuenthly hee muſt die to ſinne, and liue to righteouſneſſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Eightly hee muſt bee holy and vnblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Ninthly hee muſt crutifie the fleſh with effects and luſts. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Tenthly and laſt hee muſt ſerue God in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe all the daies of his life. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.75.</p>
               <p>God requireth true and vnfained holineſſe, <hi>waſh you</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.16. <hi>Make you cleane, take away the euill of your workes from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine eyes, ceaſe to doe euill,</hi> this is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, that ſo wee ſhould bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his heauenly nature, <hi>As he which hath called you is holy, ſo bee yee holy in all manner of conuerſation</hi> ſaith <hi>Saint Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our bodies are the temples of the holy Ghoſt</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle to the <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. and therefore glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God in your bodies, and in your ſpirits, for they are Gods, in theſe bodies, we ſhall riſe out of our graues and appeare before the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1975:58"/>ſeate of God, in theſe bodies we ſhall ſit vpon the twelue tribes, God ſhall crowne them with glory and honour, keepe theſe veſſels cleane, theſe are precious, keepe them in honor, keepe them in holineſſe, make not the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt the members of the deuil, ſhame not your bodies ſhame not your ſelues.</p>
               <p>The Scripture teacheth vs manifeſtly that none ſhall become pertakers of the glorious ryſing againe, wherein conſiſteth the full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our felicity, but thoſe which haue ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured here to die vnto ſinne, and to liue againe in newneſſe of life, which is called the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, euen by the ſpirit of Chriſt, whom all true Chriſtians haue clothed themſelues with all, and which haue mortified the deeds of the fleſh which haue put off the old man with his workes, and put on the new man according to the Image of him that created vs, and which haue clenſed themſelues heere from all vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe both of body and ſoule, and that is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why <hi>Saint Paule</hi> hauing ſaid that when Chriſt appeareth we alſo ſhall appeare with him in glory, doth forewarne vs to mortifie our members that are vpon earth, whereby hee doth vs well to vnderſtand that this mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt goe before in vs here, if we purpoſe to attaine to glory.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:1975:59"/>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Paul</hi> telleth vs that <hi>our bodies ſhall be quickned by reaſon of Chriſts ſpirit which ſhall haue dwelling in vs heere, and whereby wee ſhall haue repreſſed all our former affections.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> proteſteth that <hi>whoſoeuer putteth his truſt in Chriſt doth purge himſelfe after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To bee ſhort there are infinite places touching this poynt in the holy Scriptures, and though there were no more but this one that is vttered ſo often, namely: That the vnrighteous ſhal not inherit the kingdome of God, it might bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to content vs withall, and to put vs in feare, and make vs to come to the true and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repentance.</p>
               <p>It is comfortably ſayd: God hath commanded vs to beleeue in his ſonne, and for beleeuing in him, he promiſeth vs euerlaſting life, ſo that all they which beleeue in Chriſt, taking him for their Sauiour, and applying to themſelues al the benifits, which he hath purchaſed for vs by his death are in the right way.</p>
               <p>But who bee theſe beleeuers? <hi>euen they</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>which walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit, they which take paynes to frame them-ſelues to the will Chriſt into whoſe body they are grafted and vnto whom they bee knit together as his liuely members,</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:1975:59"/>they which endeuour to loue God, and to giue ouer the loue of themſelues, and of the world, they which haue their whole conuerſation in heauen, they which loath their former life, and for feare of falling there-into againe doe the more watch, and looke the wariler to their thoughts, deuices, words and deeds, they which feeling their owne weakeneſſe and infirmities, make inceſſant praier to God for the ſpirit of ſtrength and ſteadfaſtneſſe, and they which feele their coldneſſe &amp; vnluſtineſſe, doe craue the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of feruentneſſe &amp; earneſtneſſe, they which do in the time of aduerſity keepe themſelues from murmuring, &amp; endeuor to be patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they which be thinke themſelues of Gods benefits &amp; yeeld him thankes for them: they which ſtriue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſuccor the poore &amp; needy both in body &amp; ſoule, and at a word, they which crucifie the fleſh with the affections and luſts thereof.</p>
               <p>For in ſo much that they in whom theſe fruits are not found, wee make the talent of faith to preuaile in ſuch manner as hath beene ſaid, cannot be ſaid to bee in the number of true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eeuers and faithfull ones: notwithſtanding though they pretend ſome countenance of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and therefore much-leſſe can thoſe bee ſaid to bee of that number in whom the workes of the fleſh are aparant.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:1975:60"/>
               <p>But ſome fleſhly Chriſtian will ſay ſtill that as for him he is clothed with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and that the perfect obedience which Chriſt hath yeelded to God his Father in ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the law, is imputed vnto him, as if he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had yeelded it. And to bee ſhort that he is reckoned for righteous by his faith, ſo as none of all his imperfections are to bee made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of.</p>
               <p>If thou liſt to beguile thy ſelfe, thou maiſt, but it wilbe to thy harme and confuſion, indeed Chriſt laieth not our ſinnes to our charge, if wee beleeue a right in him, neither ſhall all our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections hinder the vertue and efficacie of his death: But to beare thy ſelfe in hand, that Chriſt holdeth thee for righteous, when thou giueſt thy ſelfe to vnrighteouſneſſe, and haſt no other care but to follow thine owne inordinate luſtes, it is not only a doing great diſhonour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him but alſo a ſcorning of him for his redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of thee.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> ſaith manifeſtly, <hi>that as Chriſt is righteous, ſo hee that worketh righteouſneſſe is righteous, and that hee which ſinneth is of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill:</hi> yea and he ſaith moreouer, <hi>that the thing wherein the children of God doe ſhew themſelues to differ from the children of the deuill, is that the one ſort worke righteouſneſſe, and the other ſort
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:1975:60"/>worke ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of a truth I cannot tell how Gods true Children, who are al true Criſtians, could other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be better marked out then by their aplying of themſelues night and day to doe what-ſoeuer is pleaſant and acceptable to their heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whome becauſe they know to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they alſo doe wholy endeuor themſelues to doe righteous thinges, wherein they ſhew themſelues to be borne of God, as Sainr <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth further: <hi>If you know that God is righteous, know ye alſo that whoſoeuer worketh righteouſnes is borne of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer how can it come to paſſe that the true Chriſtians ſhould not giue themſelues to righteouſneſſe, ſeeing they haue <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſpirit to guid them, for <hi>he that hath not Chriſts ſpirit</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>is noe Chriſtian, which beeing holy of himſelfe, cannot but driue foreward the party to all holines, whom he poſſeſſeth.</hi> And it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but that he muſt needes bring forth his fruites, which are louingneſſe, goodneſſe, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, mercifulneſſe, meekeneſſe, faithfulneſſe, mildneſſe, and ſtayedneſſe: to be ſhort, it cannot be but that hee muſt needes alter the whole man both within and without, to make a new creature of him.</p>
               <p>For ſith that <hi>CHRISTS</hi> life was not ſet
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1975:61"/>forth vnto vs all onely to make aledgement of it, or to make a wondring at it in wordes, but to be followed by vs: it is the marke wherevnto wee muſt bend, in drawing to perfection, as neere as is poſſible, and as much as our frailty can afford. And otherwiſe ſeeing we be towled therevnto by <hi>Ieſus</hi> Chriſt himſelfe, not only in wordes, but alſo in examples, which are as liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly portratures of the life which wee ought to lead heere in wayting for his glory and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous comming againe, wee cannot exempt our ſelues from it without preiudice of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no nor yet without be wraying that we haue no luſt to it, for were we rightly deſirous to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come happy, and to attaine to the endleſſe life, which is promiſed vs in CHRIST, wee could not ſhew it better in taking the way thereto, whereby wee may, and muſt attayne vnto it.</p>
               <p>And that way is none other then to beleeue in Chriſt, and to walke as he walked, and that is Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> meaning where he ſayth, that <hi>hee which ſayth he dwelleth in Chriſt ought to walke as he walked, that is he ought to endeauour to liue as be liued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And certes it is not poſſible that they which are vnited and knit vnto Chriſt, as his members ſhould not be touched with deſire to reſemble
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1975:61"/>him and to follow his ſteppes, for the very thing, wherein the vnion and coniunction is ſhewed, is that the members doe ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be of the ſame that the heade is, and where that is not done, it is an euident proofe that the member is rotten, ſenceles, and voyd of life which is in the head.</p>
               <p>Not without cauſe therefore doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, that <hi>we must be of the ſame mind which Ieſus Chriſt was of,</hi> for thereby his meaning is, to giue vs to vnderſtand that we which are members of Chriſt, muſt be anſwerable to him in vnion of affection, and will, which thing he teacheth yet more plainely in another place, where he ſayth that <hi>we be grafted into Chriſt after the likenes of his death and reſurrection,</hi> meaning thereby that we which are ioyned vnto Chriſt as an impe is to the ſtock of a tree, ought ſo to liue of his life as there may not appeare any deformity in vs, but that as he hath dyed, ſo wee muſt dye alſo and as hee is riſen againe, ſo wee muſt riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine likewiſe, wee muſt dye vnto ſinne and riſe againe vnto newnes of life, for that is the death and the life which hee ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of.</p>
               <p>How ſhall wee know that wee bee in him and are made partakers of his graces
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:1975:62"/>but by our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndeauoring of our ſelues to keepe his commandements, and ſoothly the only mean to know and to be aſſured in our ſelues that we dwell in Chriſt, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in vs, is our keeping of his commandements as <hi>Iohn</hi> teacheth adding further that our knowing that he dwelleth in vs is by the ſpirit which he hath giuen vs, becauſe that by that ſpirit wee endeauour to follow him, and to frame our ſelues to his will, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we yeeld proof of the vnion that is between him and vs, for euen as the children of the world witneſſe themſelues to be alone with the world by following their worldly luſts, ambition, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and pleaſures, which may be likewiſe ſayd alſo of the members of Sathan. So in like caſe, the Chriſtians ſhew themſelues to be made one with <hi>Chriſt</hi> by his holy ſpirit, when they follow <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſteppes, and make his life to ſerue them, as a moſt perfect rule to lead their liues by.</p>
               <p>What remaineth then to be done in this caſe? ſoothly that we on our parts doe enforce our ſelues by eſchewing all flothfullneſſe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurtfull, and noyſome in this behalfe, for as much as it is of ſuch importance, that we cannot neglect it without wilfull diſappoynting our ſelues of our ſaluation and ſoueraigne felicity.</p>
               <p>This way is narrow and rough, I confeſſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1975:62"/>it is ſo, as all Chriſtians doe, and ſo doth Chriſt himſelfe ſay it alſo, for in as much as thereby we muſt forſake our ſelues to follow Chriſt, which is very painfull and hard to the fleſh, which deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nothing but her owne pleaſures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, no doubt but wee feele it, to bee ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bitter, and burthenſome, but what for that, yet muſt we take that way without ſtepping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide one way or other, for that is the only way which after many labours and hard pinches, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the end vnto life. As for the other way, it is very broad, faire, and accompanied with great pleaſures but the end thereof ſaith our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, leadeth vnto death.</p>
               <p>Now to conſider that it is much better to go by labour to reſt, by tribulation to ioy, by death to life, then contrariwiſe to go by reſt to labour, by ioy to tribulation, and by life to death, and looke what eſtate commeth laſt ſhall bee euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
               <p>What thing then ſhould hold vs back or hinder vs in the race.' if it bee the world, with all the goodnes, honours, and pleaſures thereof, let vs vnderſtand that all thoſe things paſſe away like an arrow which is ſhot at a white or marke, the trace whereof is not perceiued any more, by the roughnes and vneaſines of the way. Let vs conſider how there is nothing ſoe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1975:63"/>vneaſie nor rough which becometh not eaſie and ſmooth by continuall vſe.</p>
               <p>If it bee the infirmity and weakeneſſe of our nature, let vs thinke vpon him which hath promiſed to ſtand by vs to helpe vs, and to ſtrengthen vs, who being good will helpe vs, &amp; being almighty wil alſo ſtrengthen vs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally that we pray to him continually. <hi>Aske</hi> ſaith hee <hi>and it ſhalbe giuen vnto you ſeeke and you ſhall finde knocke and it ſhalbe opened vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prouided alwaies that wee on our ſide doe ſtriue our ſelues, for he helpeth not them that are idle and doe nothing, hee giueth his ſpirit, but it to ſuch as feeling their owne feebleneſſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpleaſed there-with, doe earneſtly deſire and craue his ſpirit for helpe, to ſuch as nothing asketh, nothing hee giueth, it is euen hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that worketh in vs, both the will and deede, how-be-it not ſo long as wee our ſelues ſleepe, not ſo long as wee fould our armes a croſſe, and much leſſe ſo long as wee reſiſt him.</p>
               <p>The Kingdome of GOD ſaith <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> ſuffereth violence, and the violent pluckt it to them, and who bee thoſe violent? they which beeing inflamed with great deſire
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:1975:63"/>and zeale, to faſhion them-ſelues like to their head, and doe violence and force to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the intent that their nature and fleſh being reſtrained and brideled, may not caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impediment in the way of Gods ſpirit, which worketh in them: thoſe which feele them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues cold and laſie whether it bee in praying to God, or in giuing him thankes for all thinges, thoſe that doe quicken and ſtirre vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues without ſuffering them-ſelues to goe on and to be ouer-come of their fleſh: Thoſe which take paines to marke all their owne thoughts and affections and to reſtraine them from paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their bounds, and from rouing a ſtray, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſure watch vpon their mindes and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the counſell of the wiſe: Becauſe that from the mind commeth the welſpring of al euil, and finally they which by CHRISTS ſpirit doe inceſſantly crucifie the fleſh with the luſts thereof.</p>
               <p>And of a truth wee bee of our owne nature ſo contrary to GOD, and ſo bent to the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our ſelues and our affections are ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and vehement, and we be haled vnto euill with ſo great force of our fleſh that we muſt not thinke that GOD can haue his dominion in vs, vnleſſe wee vſe great force to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1975:64"/>and ſubdue our ſelues vnto him.</p>
               <p>To conclude, that they onely true marke of all Chriſtians, and right beleeuers, is loue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which a man may well talke of Chriſt, and of the Goſpell, and may well haue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and all the godly ceremonies that can be deuiſed, and yet all ſhalbe nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Conſtancy in going forward vnto the end of our race.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fift part in this happy iorney is Conſtancy &amp; perſeuerance to the end, for if thou begin by time &amp; find the way, and go a right, and continue not vnto the end, thy reward is with them of whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>their end is worſe then their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is nothing in our life which ſuffereth ſo many changes, as our deuotion, hot and cold, in and out, of and on, not in one mood ſo long as the Sparrow ſits vpon the ground. Thus man is roulled vpon a wheele, that neuer ſtandeth ſtill, he is vpon the ſide of a hill, where it is eaſie to ſlide, and hard to get vp the fleſh: therefore the Apoſtle mooued with pitty, ſeeing man ſtand vpon ſuch a ſlippery ground, as it were in a ſhip
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:1975:64"/>ready to ſinke, he crieth to them that ſtand ſureſt <hi>take heed leaſt yee fall,</hi> that is, when thou haſt put on the armor of light, and art in the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al field, to fight the Lords battaile againſt the world, the fleſh, and the deuill, turne not backe like <hi>Demas,</hi> but remember the comfort of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha,</hi> that there bee more with thee, then againſt thee, and that the tempter can ouer-come nonê but them which yeeld. Take example of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> beeing called by Chriſt, immediatly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke the world, and embraſed the Goſpel: for all that ſerue God, are like the ſeruant which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a print in his eare after the maner of the Iewes, in token that he would ſerue his Maſter for euer.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle doth not teach vs theſe phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to doubt of our ſaluation, or of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God but of our Conſtancy in his ſeruice; nor leaſt we fall from our election, but leaſt wee fal from our righteouſneſſe, this is a godly feare; <hi>and bleſſed is he</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon not he which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in feare of Gods mercy, but hee which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in feare of his owne frailty.</hi> Pro. 28.14. As <hi>Iob</hi> which feared all his workes <hi>Iob</hi> 9 28. Wee muſt haue confidence towards God, but diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence towards our ſelues, for God wilbe true to vs, if wee bee true to him: This feare is not contrary to faith, but cannot be without it, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:1975:65"/>take heed leaſt yee fal, is, take heed leaſt yee ſinne.</p>
               <p>Therefore the holy ghoſt crieth ſo often, be faithfull euen vnto the death, be not weary of well doing: take heed leaſt yee fall, for when thou art weary of thy goodneſſe, God doth not compt thee good, but weary of thy goodneſſe and when thou declines from righteouſneſſe, God doth not compt thee righteous, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoulted from righteouſnes: according to the ſaying of the Prophet, <hi>If the righteous turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his righteouſneſſe, and commit iniquity, and doe according to all the abominations that the wicked man doth, ſhal he liue? All his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that he hath done ſhall not bee mentioned, but in his tranſgreſsion that hee committed, and in his ſins, that he hath ſinned, in them he ſhall die.</hi> Ezek. 18.14. As Gods mercy endureth for euer, ſo our righteouſnes ſhould endure for euer: euery thought, word and deed of a faithfull man is a ſtep towards heauen, in euery place he meeteth Chriſt, euery good thing putteth him in minde of God, hee ſeeketh to finde him, and when hee hath found him, he ſeeketh him ſtill, hee is not ſatisfied, becauſe at euery touch there commeth ſome vertue from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> ſerued ſeuen yeeres for <hi>Rachaell,</hi> and after them ſeuen yeeres more, and when hee
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:1975:65"/>had ſerued ſo many yeeres, they ſeemed vnto him as nothing becauſe he loued her: he which ſerued ſo long for <hi>Rachael,</hi> ſerued all his life for heauen, and if he had liued vntill this day, hee would haue ſerued God ſtill, and thought it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing becauſe he loued him.</p>
               <p>To haue the Arke but a while, doth more hurt to the Philiſtians, then benefit them: ſo to ſerue God but a while doth more damage vs, then helpe vs, for happier is the child that which neuer began, then <hi>Iudas</hi> whoſe end was worſe then his beginning.</p>
               <p>Wiſdome is angry with him which leaueth his righteouſnes to become worſe, the vine would not forſake her grapes, the Oliue would not forſake her fatneſſe, the fig-tree would not leaue his ſweetneſſe, but the bramble did, he is not the vine, nor the Oliue, nor the fig-tree, but he was a bramble, made for the fire, which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the ioyes.</p>
               <p>Let the dogge turne to the vomet, and the ſwine to the walow, but thou, like <hi>Abraham,</hi> hold on thy ſacrifice vnto the euening, euen the euening of thy life, and then a full meaſure ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be meaſured vnto thee.</p>
               <p>The way to heauen, if men would bend themſelues as much to doe good, as they beate their braines to doe euill, they might
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:1975:66"/>goe to heauen with leſſe trouble then they goe to hell: our idle houres are enough to get wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and knowledge, and faith, til wee were like Saints among men.</p>
               <p>But if thou looke only to thy ſteppes, and tel the rubbes which lye in the way, thou ſhalt goe fearefully and vnwillingly, euery thing ſhall turne thee aſide, and euery Shale ſhal ſtep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and take thy Crowne from thee.</p>
               <p>But then lift vp thine eyes from the earth, and looke to <hi>Chriſt</hi> calling, the ſpirit aſſiſting, the father bleſſing, the Angells comforting, the word directing, the Crowne inuiting, and then the fetters ſhal fal from thee, and thou ſhalt riſe like the ſonne and maruel how the thing could ſeeme ſo hard, and be ſo eaſie, when you doe well, remember that ye change not for worſe, and doing ſo, you ſhall continue vnto the end, and receiue the bleſſing of eternall happineſſe, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth, <hi>he that continueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end ſhall be bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we may the better hold on, &amp; be conſtant, in going foreward vnto the end, it is good to make ſpeed, and for this cauſe the Apoſtle ſayth <hi>So runne that ye may obtaine.</hi> 1. Cor. 9.24. which is the ſwifteſt pace of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though he ſhould goe faſter to heauen then to any place els in the world, his meaning is this, that as a man doth
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1975:66"/>watch and runne, and labour to be rich quickly ſo he ſhould heare, and pray, and ſtudy, and vſe all means to be wiſe quickly.</p>
               <p>Thus the Apoſtle vnderſtandeth when he bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs adde, as if he ſhould ſay; when thou art in the way to continue, and knoweſt good from euill, euery day kill ſome vice, and euery weeke ſow ſome vertue, and make thy two talents fiue talents, and thy fiue talents tenne talents, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be doing good, and at laſt it ſhall be opened; becauſe thou haſt knocked, Chriſt ſayth, the kingdome of heauen is gotten by violence; therefore a man muſt be earneſt, and zealous in religion, for zeale is the loue of God, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>be ſwift to heare,</hi> we muſt be ſwift to pray, ſwift to obey, ſwift to doe good, for he is not curſed only, which doth not onely the Lords buſines, but he which doth it negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, <hi>Iere.</hi> 48.10. that is hee which doth any thing before it, like him that would bidde his freinds firſt farewell, and follow Chriſt after.</p>
               <p>The Hound, which runneth for the hare, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth as faſt as poſſibly he can, and ſhall hee that runneth for heauen creepe more ſtowly then the Diall? our Sauiour ſaith not that his father is glorified that we bring forth frute, but that we bring forth much ftuite, for is it not better
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1975:67"/>to bee veſſels of gold, then veſſels of braſſe.</p>
               <p>God hath placed vs here in a race to runne, we muſt therefore ſo runne that we may attaine the priſe, wee are grafts of the Lords planting, we muſt grow to the height and breadth of a tree and bring forth fruit, we are Pilgrims and ſtrangers, and paſſe by the wilderneſſe of this world, into our heauenly reſting place: wee may not ſtay by the way, but muſt remooue our Tents, and continually march on forward vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that day come when we ſhall enter into the land of promiſe.</p>
               <p>Now, that we may the better &amp; with ſtrength walke conſtantly, by continuall increaſe in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in this our holy iourney towards heauen: let vs therfore embrace theſe comfortable duties of a true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> the firſt &amp; the 5.16.17.18. ſaying, <hi>Reioyce euermore, pray continually, In all things, giue thankes:</hi> from theſe are to bee gathered many profitable inſtructions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the firſt to reioyce euermore.</head>
               <p>It is not an indifferent thing to reioyce, and not to reioyce, but we are commanded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, to ſhew that wee breake a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if we reioyce not: but here God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to reioyce, as though ſome men did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:1975:67"/>enough: therefore you muſt vnderſtand to whom he ſpeaketh thus in the Pſal. 149.5. <hi>It is ſaid let the Saints bee ioyfull with glory, not let the wicked reioyce:</hi> and in <hi>Eſay</hi> the 40.1. <hi>Comfort my people, not comfort my enemies,</hi> ſhewing to whom this Commandement of <hi>Paul</hi> is ſent. <hi>Reioyce euermore,</hi> it is not in this as Chriſt ſaith: <hi>That which I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto all, but that which I ſay vnto you</hi> I <hi>ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all. Salomon</hi> ſaith fiue times that this is the portion of man vnder the ſunne, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue in the gifts of GOD with thankfulneſſe and to reioyce in them, <hi>Hee which would haue vs holy as Hee is holy, would haue vs ioyfull as Hee is ioyfull, Hee which would haue vs doe his will vpon earth, as the Angels doe in heauen, would haue vs reioyce vpon earth, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels reioyce in heauen, Hee which hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs the Kingdome of Saints would haue vs reioyce that wee haue ſuch a Kingdome to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore he ſaith to his diſciples, <hi>reioyce that your names are written in the booke of life,</hi> the ſpirit of God is called the comforter, becauſe wee ſhould haue ioy in it. I <hi>will ſend you the Comforter</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>to shew that they which haue the ſpirit haue comfort too, and they which reſiſt comfort reſiſt the ſpirit:</hi> therefore
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:1975:68"/>the ſonne of God is called the conſolation of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and that ioy is where Chriſt is, as the light is where the ſunne is, therefore the chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ioy is called the ioy of the holy ghoſt, to ſhew that they haue the chiefeſt ioy that haue the holy ghoſt, and the greateſt peace is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the peace of a good conſcience, to ſhew that they haue the greateſt peace which haue a good conſcience: <hi>therefore the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are to bee annointed with the oile of ioy,</hi> Eſay 61.3. As though ioy were their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, therefore they are ſaid to be clothed with the garment of gladneſſe, as though gladneſſe did compaſſe them like a garment.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in all his Epiſtles doth ioyne grace and peace together, to ſhew that the peace of God doth follow them which haue the grace of God: It is ſaid in <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.9. That God reioyceth to doe vs good, and in the 28. <hi>Deut. the Iewes are reprooued, becauſe they reioyced not in the ſeruice of God.</hi> As the Lord loueth a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full giuer, ſo he loueth a cheerefull ſeruer, and a cheerefull preacher, and a cheerefull hearer, and a cheerefull worſhipper: as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let vs ſing heartily vnto the Lord,</hi> ſhewing, as it were, a tune which delighteth Gods eares, that is, you muſt giue heartily, you muſt loue heartily, you muſt obey heartily, and when you doe all theſe
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:1975:68"/>things heartily, then you ſhall doe all things cheerefuly.</p>
               <p>Therefore now I may ſay vnto thoſe which reſiſt comfort, and nouriſh griefe, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, <hi>who hath required theſe things of you:</hi> God doth require no ſorow, but the ſorow for ſinne, no feare but the feare to ſinne, no care, but the care to pleaſe God, nay he hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den all care elſe, and therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Caſt your care vpon him,</hi> although God did not alow vs to care, he ſent his Apoſtles with this charge, to caſt their care vpon him, as we doe caſt our ſinnes vpon Chriſt: for God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to labour, and not to care, but care hindreth our labours.</p>
               <p>As we are taught to diſcerne of ſpirits and doctrines, ſo we muſt diſcerne of care and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, when we ſorrow for any thing but ſin, our ſorrow is murmuring, <hi>for the ſorrow of the heart,</hi> ſaith Salomon, <hi>is the conſuming of the bones,</hi> that is it will pull downe the ſtrongeſt man that is, therefore let no man drinke of ſorrow before hee taſt it, for the charge is not to get thy lyuing with care of the minde, but with the ſweat of thy browes: Now as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>Reſiſt the diuell, and he will flie from you,</hi> ſo reſiſt ſorrow, and it will flie from you.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:1975:69"/>
               <p>This is all the care, and all the feare, and all the repentance which euer could be found in the Scriptures: therefore let vs pray to God euery day, to turne all our ioy into the ioy of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and al our peace into the peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and all our ſorrow into the ſorrow for ſinne, and all our feare into the feare to ſinne, and ſo wee may reioyce and ſorrow together, feare and hope together, that is haue one eye to the law to keep vs from preſumption, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other eye to the Goſpell to keepe vs from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire and then this comfort is ſent to vs: Reioyce euermore or elſe wee haue nothing to doe with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>It followeth the next du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>to pray continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter reioyce continually, hee biddeth vs pray continually ſhewing that it muſt be ſuch reioycing continually, that we may pray continually too, or elſe he doth not alow vs to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:1975:69"/>reioyce, how can theſe two ioyne together, pray and reioyce? ſome if they ſhould pray cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for their hearts, nay their heartes are ſick, vntill their prayer be done, this is the difference betweene the reioycing of the wicked and the godly.</p>
               <p>The comfort of the wicked is like a compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded medicine made of many mixtures, for there muſt be piping and dancing, and piping &amp; feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and dallying at the game, or elſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be merry, but the comfort of the godly is like a light in the ayre which ſhineth, when no matter is ſeene, ſo the godly reioyce when no cauſe is ſeene, if they doe but thinke vpon God, they reioyce ſtraight-way, if there be but a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and a thankfulneſſe and a meditation, theſe are inſtruments enough for them, and they can be as merry as Birds in May, the reaſon of it is this, As Chriſt ſayd I haue another meat, which you know not of, ſo the godly haue another ioy which the world knoweth not of, of this ioy a man may reioyce continually. And therefore <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſayth: <hi>a good conſcience is a continuall feaſt Pro.</hi> 15.15. that is a continuallioy.</p>
               <p>Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ioyneth reioyce, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, with prayer continually, as if he ſhould ſay, by this you ſhal know whether you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce well if you can pray to, that is if
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:1975:70"/>thy reioycing mooue thee to pray, as the ioy of the Angels maketh them praiſe God and ſing, holy, holy, holy, alwaies vnto him. All this doth conclude, that as we ſhould doe Gods will on earth as it it is done in heauen, ſo wee ſhould reioyce in earth as they reioyce in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and then this ioy is a ſigne of another ioye.</p>
               <p>Now we are to conſider more perticularly, the benefit of praier: of all our duties this is the onelie dutie vnto GOD, which is giuen to none but God, according to that, <hi>Him onely ſhalt thou ſerue,</hi> ſuch an excellent thing is praier that is offered to none but him, which <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth excellent.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, it is ſuch a pleaſant thing that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> enioyneth to pray continually, with reioyce continually, to ſhew that no man hath ſuch ioy as hee which is often talking with GOD by praier, as if hee ſhould ſay, if thou haue skill to pray continuallie, it will make thee reioyce continually, for in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of God is nothing but ioy and gladneſſe of heart.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is ſuch a neceſſary thing that Chriſt calleth his temple the houſe of praier, to ſhew that we ſhould pray in the Temple, which is ſo neceſſary that GOD built a houſe for it,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:1975:70"/>and called it the houſe of prayer, as though prayer brought God and vs to dwell continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in one houſe togither.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, if wee endeuour our ſelues to liue vprightly and in the feare of God, according to the preciſe rule of his Commandements, we ſhall finde ſuch a heauenly life that it will make vs like the Angels which are in heauen: for when wee reade GOD ſpeaketh vnto vs, becauſe wee read his word, but when wee pray wee ſpeake to God, becauſe wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence our ſuites to him, and ſo praier maketh vs like the Angels which are alwaies ſinging to God.</p>
               <p>The fifth, it is ſuch a ſweet thing aboue all other things that wee doe for God, that in the <hi>Reuelations</hi> 7. the praiers of the Saints are called incenſe, becauſe when they aſcend to heauen God ſeemes to ſmell a ſweet fauour like incenſe.</p>
               <p>Sixthly it is ſuch a profitable thing that it doth more good then almes, for with almes I helpe but a few, but with my praier I may helpe thouſands, praier is the rich mans almes aſwell as the poore mans, for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for praier, aſwell as <hi>Lazarus</hi> begged for crummes.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is ſo victorious and powerfull that it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:1975:71"/>ouercommeth God himſelfe, which ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all things, for if wee will ouercome our Lord as <hi>Iacob</hi> did, we muſt ouercome him by praier, this God ſheweth when hee ſaid to <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, pray not for his people,</hi> ſhewing that the praier of the righteous is of ſuch force &amp; power that he forbiddeth them to pray when he would not grant, leaſt hee ſhould bee ouercome, this Chriſt ſheweth againe when hee reſembleth his Father to the deafe Iudge, &amp; the ſuppliant to the importunat woman, which cried vpon him, and made him harken to her, as if ſhe had compelled him. We read that the Iewes did preuaile more by praier, then they could by fight, therefore one ſaith, <hi>hee that can pray can doe all things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee can ouercome God, ouercome the diuell, which hindreth all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath ſuch a hand in all things that it is like the ſanctifier of euery thing, it bleſſeth our thoughts, it bleſſeth our ſpeeches; &amp; bleſſeth our actions, for whatſoeuer thou doeſt, before thou haſt bleſſed it with praier, thou haſt no promiſe that it ſhall proſper or doe good, therefore wee ſhould not preſume to vſe any of Gods gifts, or any of Gods graces without praier, leaſt that which is good, doe not good, but hurt vnto vs.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth vs to pray before we eate. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.6. for this cauſe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:1975:71"/>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> praied before hee ioyrned. Acts 20.36. For this cauſe the Iſraelits praied before they fought, for this cauſe the Preacher prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before hee preach. It is a good thing to preach, and yet we ſee they doe not pray mee to preach before they pray, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> planteth, <hi>Apollo</hi> watereth, but God giueth encreaſe.</p>
               <p>Euen ſo wee ſhould not preſume to exerciſe our faith, nor our repentance, nor our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence without praier, becauſe there is no faith ſo perfect but it had need of praier to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it, there is no loue ſo perfect, but it had need of praier to confirme it, there is no repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſo perfect but it had need of praier to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it, there is no obedience ſo perfect, but it had need of praier to direct it, therefore he doth ſinne which doth preſume to doe any good worke without praier, becauſe he ſeemes to doe it, by his owne power, for that he craueth not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from God, which giueth power to faith to bring forth works, as well as he doth to trees to bring forth fruits. Therefore no vertue hath don ſo much as praier hath done, for all vertues haue had their power from praier: aman cannot pray heartily, when wrath, malice, or luſt, or ſuch like cary his minde away, this <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth againe when hee ſaith, <hi>how ſhall they call vpon him, in whom they haue not beleeued,</hi> ſhewing
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:1975:72"/>that none can pray, but they which haue fayth, and that is a ſigne the ſpirit is within, if wee can pray: thetfore as long as God doth not take away thy praying, he hath not taken away his mercy.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his 12. to the <hi>Ro.</hi> teacheth vs a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſeruice to God, But here he ſeems to ioyn an vnreaſonable ſeruice of God: for who did euer pray continually, or if we ſhould pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, when ſhould wee heare, or preach, or when ſhould wee ſtuddy, or when ſhould wee worke, ſo one ſeruice ſeemeth to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all other ſeruice: but indeed it doth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all other ſeruices, and therefore wee are commanded to pray continually, becauſe we can doe nothing without prayer: but if you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that this commandement is broken, if your lippes be not alwayes going, then you are out of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> mind, for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did not pray continually with his lippes, and therefore he doth not meane a lipp-prayer onely, neither did <hi>Paul</hi> frequent the Temple day and night, and therfore he doth not meane a Church-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er only. And further it ſeemes that the Iewes were not appoynted to pray at all times, for they had ſet times of prayer, and therefore wee read how <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> went vp into the Temple at the time of prayer.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:1975:72"/>
               <p>Therefore to pray continually is to lift vp our hearts continually vnto God, and pray in our thoughts as <hi>Moyſes</hi> did, though he opened not his lippes, and ſo we may pray continually. As when a good man is to anſwer before the perſecutor, a thought prayeth in his heart, that he may anſwer wiſely, when he is to giue almes a thought prayeth in his heart, that he may doe good, when he is to heare a Sermon, a thought Prayeth in his heart that he may be edified and ſanctified by it.</p>
               <p>Thus may we pray, and heare, pray and ſpeake pray and eat, pray and ſtuddy, pray and work together, therefore prayer ſeemeth a harder thing then it is for if it had beene irkſome for any to pray Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would not haue ioyned prayer, and reioycing together, it is not hard when a man doth it and reioyceth.</p>
               <p>Now if you will know what prayer is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table with God? <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth <hi>the prayer of the iuſt auayleth much if it be feruent, Ia.</hi> 5.16, not that the prayer of the wicked auaileth any thing for <hi>Sal mon</hi> ſayth their prayer is abominable therefore it is ſinne, if it be neuer ſo feruent, but the perſon muſt be iuſt, that is, he muſt be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by a true and a liuely fayth in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord. By this thou mayeſt know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy prayer be acceptable with God or noe.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:1975:73"/>
               <p>Thus much for the benefit and neceſſity of praier. Now for the manner of praier, there might be as much ſaid, but for tediouſneſſe I will ſay no more but the parts thereof, and ſo end for this duty.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The firſt is to whom we ſhould pray</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſecond is the cauſe why we ſhould pray.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The third for the things for which wee ſhould pray.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The fourth the Mediator which we ſhould pray by.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The fifth and laſt the affection which we ſhould bring to pray.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Now wee are to ſpeake of the third dutie which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth admoniſh vs of ſaying, <hi>In all things giue thankes.</hi> 1. Theſſ. 5.18.</p>
               <p>Theſe three duties are badges or Cognizan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Chriſtian ſouldier, that is, to reioyce in the mercy of God, to be feruent in praier, and to giue thankes to God in all things: The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens which haue no part in the Kingdome of Chriſt, are thankfull for their life, liberty, wealth, and glory, and worldly proſperity, but Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought to be thankefull euen in perſecution, in thraldome, in aduerſity, in ſhame, in miſery and in death it ſelfe.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:1975:73"/>
               <p>Who hath not heard of the patience of <hi>Iob,</hi> his heards of cattle were driuen away: his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes conſumed with fire, his children ſlaine, his body ſtricken with ſcurffe and mangineſſe, his wife loathed him, and his friends forſooke him: what did <hi>Iob</hi> in all theſe miſeries, what thought he, or what ſpake he? his patience in ſuffering, and his words of thankeſgiuing doe teach vs how to beare aduerſity, <hi>the Lord,</hi> ſaith Iob, <hi>hath giuen, and the Lord hath taken it, bleſſed bee the name of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are we then that are neither thankfull for riches, nor for health, nor for our pleaſures in the aboundance of all things: who hath giuen them vnto vs, the earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the world and all that dwell therein, he openeth his hand and filleth all things lyuing with his good bleſſings.</p>
               <p>Let vs looke vp into the heauens, there is God the Father of lights, there is our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ieſus Chriſt, in whom are hid all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wiſdome and knowledge: when wee turne in our beads, when wee ſee our fare and furniture on our tables, when wee ſee our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and children about vs, when wee ſee our money and houſes, and lands, let vs thinke with our ſelues how many good men and faithfull ſeruants of God lack the ſame, &amp; haue
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:1975:74"/>not receiued theſe bleſſings in the ſame meaſure as wee haue done, in all theſe things God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to vs, and ſaith, <hi>I haue giuen them thee, thou haſt them at thy hands, vſe them well, and be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man ſhould declare what cauſes wee haue to giue thankes vnto God for all his benefits and bleſſings, noe man could make an end, their is noe beaſt in the ground, nor fiſh in the Sea, nor bird in the ayre, nor ſtar in the heauens, noe leaſe on the tree, no corne in the field, no ſand in the ſhore, no drop of water, no ſparke of fire, but God hath giuen them all for the ſonnes of men: ſo much are wee bound alwaies to giue thankes to God, and to ſay with the Prophet, <hi>O Lord our God, how excellent is thy name in all the world: Let vs confeſſe before the Lord his louing kindneſſe in his wonderfull workes before the ſonnes of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But who is able to render thankes ſufficient to God for that hee giueth vs the knowledge of his Goſpel, &amp; maketh vs know the ſecrets of his will: This is a great bleſſing, and farre aboue all the other comforts of this life, they that haue not this are in darkeneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death: wee haue to praiſe God, wee muſt ſay, I thank thee O God for thou haſt deliuered me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this body of death, thou haſt tranſlated mee vnto thy ſelfe, that ſo I may remaine with thee
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:1975:74"/>in glory, thus whether ſo euer yee turne, what ſtate or part of life, or death ſo euer yee conſider, whether yee be in trouble or peace, things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or things to come, heauen or earth, life or death, you ſhall alwaies finde cauſes to bee thankefull.</p>
               <p>What haue you that haue not receiued, ſaith the Apoſtle, therefore to teach man to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his maker, hee was not made in Paradice, the place of ioy and happineſſe, but hee being made out of Paradice, was brought into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, to ſhew how al his ioy and happineſſe came from God, and not from nature, that hee might know where to beſtow his thankefulneſſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dauid,</hi> to perſwade all men to thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſaith, It is a good and pleaſant thing to be thankefull if wee loue goodneſſe and pleaſure, we are bound to be thankefull.</p>
               <p>All things which wee receiue in this life are giuen vs, leaſt wee ſhould want meanes to ſerue God, then becauſe the Apoſtle requireth for all things as it hath beene ſhewed, to be thankefull to God, he is not thankefull before God, which thankes him onely for his benefits: but hee is thankefull indeed which thanketh him for his chaſticements: it may be while the Lord giueth, many will ſay, bleſſed bee the name of the Lord, but when the Lord taketh, who will ſay
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:1975:75"/>bleſſed be the name of the Lord, when the Lord did take, <hi>Iob</hi> ſayd, <hi>bleſſed bee the name of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that it hath bene ſpoken of theſe three principall duties of a Chriſtian, the Apoſtle for the conſirmation, and ſtrengthening thereof like a father which is come to the end of his life, who becauſe he hath but a while to ſpeake, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vp his leſſons together, which he would haue his ſonnes to remember when hee is gone, ſetting downe in foure next verſes following, theſe foure admonitions, two negatiue, and two affirmatiue, the firſt two negatiue, are, <hi>Quench not the ſpirit,</hi> 2. <hi>deſpiſe not propheſying,</hi> the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue are, <hi>Trye all thinges, and keeepe that which is good,</hi> 2. <hi>Abstaine from all appearance of euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His firſt aduice is, <hi>Quench not the ſpirit,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19.20.21.22. that is when a good motion commeth, welcome it like a friend, and croſſe it not with thy luſts, the ſecond admonition tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth how the firſt ſhould be kept, that is, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not propheſying,</hi> and the ſpirit wil not quench becauſe propheſying doth kindle it: the third ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition teacheth how to make fruit of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, that is, trye the doctrines of them which propheſie, and thou ſhalt not beleeue error for truth, but hold the beſt: the fourth admonition
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:1975:75"/>is the ſumme of all, and commeth laſt, becauſe it is longeſt in learning, that is, <hi>to abstaine from all appearance of euill,</hi> for he which can abſtaine not only from euill, but from the appearance of euill, that man is ſo perfect, as can be in this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full life, put all theſe together, and it is as if S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſay, Quench not the ſpirit by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſing of propheſying, neither diſpiſe propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing becauſe all do not preach alike, but rather when you heare ſome preach one way, and ſome another way, doe you trye their doctrines by the Scriptures, as the men of Berea did, and then chuſe that which is beſt, and ſoundeſt, and trueſt, hauing alwayes ſuch an eye to the truth, that thou abſtaine from all appearance of error, ſo zealous the holy Ghoſt would haue vs of our fayth, that wee ſet no atticle vppon our religion, but that which is an vndoubted truth.</p>
               <p>The ſpirit is quenched as our zeale, our faith and our loue are quenched with ſinne; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery vaine thought, euery vaine word, and euery wicked deed is like ſo many droppes to quench the ſpirit of God, ſome quench it with the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this world, ſome quench it with the luſts of the fleſh, ſome quench it with the cares of the mind, ſome quench it with long delayes: that is, not applying the motion
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:1975:76"/>when it commeth, but croſſing the good thoughts with bad thoughts, and doing a thing when the ſpirit ſaith <hi>doe it not,</hi> ſome-time a man ſhall feele himſelfe ſtirred to a good worke, as though hee were led to it by the hand, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he ſhalbe frighted from ſome euill thing, as though he were reprooued in his eare: then if he reſiſt, he ſhall ſtreight ſeele the ſpirit going out of him, and heare as it were, a voice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing him guilty, and ſhall hardly recouer his peace againe, therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>grieue not the ſpirit,</hi> ſhewing that the ſpirit is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten grieued, before it bee quenched, and that when a man begins to grieue and checke, and perſecute it, that is vntill hee ſeeme to haue no ſpirit at all, but walketh like a temple of fleſh.</p>
               <p>It is ment by the ſpirit the gifts and graces of the ſpirit, the ſpirit of God is the ſpirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the ſpirit of truth, <hi>No man,</hi> ſaith Paul, <hi>can ſay that Ieſus is the Lord, but by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt.</hi> Againe, the ſpirit helpeth our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the ſame ſpirit beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit, that wee are the children of God, it is hee that leadeth vs into all truth, and openeth our hearts to vnderſtand, and guideth our feete into the way of peace, O diſpiſe not the wiſdome of the ſpirit, refuſe not his helpe, but ſeeke it, that you may be ſtrengthned: Comfort your ſelues
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:1975:76"/>in his teſtimony of your adoption, quench not the light he hath kindled in your hearts, diſdaine not his leading, abuſe not his mercy. Abuſe not the time of your viſitation, let not ſo great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God beſtowed on you be in vaine, fulfill not your owne wils, Abſtaine from fleſhly iuſts: walke in the ſpirit, defire the beſt gifts, and let euery man as hee hath receiued the gift, ſo mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſame to another, as good diſpoſers of the manifold graces of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diſpiſe not prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</head>
               <p>THis admonition is as it were the keeper of the former, for by prophecying the ſpirit is kindled, and without prophecying the ſpirit is quenched, and therefore after, <hi>Quench not the ſpirit</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> ſhewing that as our ſinne doth quench the ſpirit, ſo prophecying doth kindle it, this you may ſee in the diſciples that went to <hi>Emaus,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, when Chriſt preached vnto them out of the law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the ſpirit was ſo kindled with his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their hearts waxed hot within them.</p>
               <p>This is no maruell, that the ſpirit of man ſhould be ſo kindled and reuiued, and refreſhed
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:1975:77"/>with the word of God, for the word is called the food of the ſoule, take away the word from the ſoule, and it hath no food to eate, as if you ſhould take food from the body, the body would pine, therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>without preaching the people periſh,</hi> therefore hee which loueth his ſoule, had no need to diſpiſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying, for then hee famiſheth his owne ſoule, and is guilty of her death.</p>
               <p>Prophecying is the preaching, and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word of God, and hee is called a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and doth prophecy, that openeth vnto vs the will of God, diſpiſe not therefore to heare the word of God preached, turne not away thine eare from vnderſtanding. God giues power to his word, that it may worke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his good pleaſure, it will let thee ſee the weakneſſe of thine error, and ſettle thee in the way wherein thou ſhouldeſt walke: if it had beene dangerous for thee to heare the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying of the Goſpel, he would not haue ſent his diſciples into the world to preach it, if <hi>Lidia</hi> ſhould not haue liked to heare <hi>Paul</hi> preach, how might ſhe haue known God, if thoſe great numbers, which heard <hi>Peter</hi> and were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted had diſpiſed prophecying, and would not haue heard him declare the grace of the goſpell vnto them, they had neuer conſidered the great
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:1975:77"/>mercy of God, nor ſought to bee inſtructed in their ſaluation, <hi>faith commeth by hearing</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. This hath beene the meanes by which Chriſt hath giuen knowledge to Kings and Princes, and all nations, <hi>it hath pleaſed God</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, by fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue them that beleeue.</hi> 1 Cor. 1. diſpiſe not then to come to the Church of God, to pray with the congregation of the faithful, to heare the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God read, and expounded, it is the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, offered vnto thee, he that diſpiſeth it ſhalbe diſpiſed of the Lord, and he ſhalbe left in darkeneſſe, thus much for the negatiue parts which we muſt not doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>It followeth to try all things and keepe that which is good.</head>
               <p>AFter diſpiſe not prophecying it followeth trie all things, as if hee ſhould ſay, but for all that trie prophecying leaſt thou beleeue errour for truth, for as amongſt Rulers, there bee bad Rulers, ſo among Preachers there bee falſe Preachers, this made Chriſt warne his diſciples to bee ware of the leauen of the Phariſies, that is, of their falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, this made <hi>Iohn</hi> ſay, <hi>trie the Spirits,</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:1975:78"/>therefore, wee reade in the Acts 17.11. How the men of <hi>Berea</hi> would not receiue <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine before they had tried it, and how did they trie it? <hi>It is</hi> ſaid <hi>they ſearched the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> this is the way which <hi>Paul</hi> would teach you to trie other, whereby he was tried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, thereby you may ſee that if you vſe to read the Scriptures, you ſhalbe able to trie all doctrines, for the word of God is the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of euery doubt, like the light which God made to behold all his creatures, ſo is the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to decide all queſtions, euery doubt muſt come to the word, and all controuerſies muſt be ended at this tribunall, the Scripture muſt ſpeak which is right, and which is wrong, which is truth, and which is error, and all tongues muſt keepe ſilence to heare it.</p>
               <p>A man trieth his friend before he truſt him, and ſhall not wee trie our faith which muſt ſaue vs, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. <hi>Let euery man be able to giue a reaſon of his faith,</hi> is this a reaſon of our faith to ſay, <hi>I beleeue ſo, becauſe Rome beleeueth ſo,</hi> or not rather becauſe the word of God doth teach me ſo, it will not anſwere for them that die in hereſie to ſay the Papiſts taught vs ſo: for God ſaith, <hi>bee not deeeiued neither by Serpent, nor by Prophet, nor by Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God doth giue vnto his children the ſpirit of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:1975:78"/>diſcretion and of iudgment, to be wiſe and know what is that good and acceptable will of God, be not therfore deceiued with words of mens wiſdome, let not the baſeneſſe or ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of any cauſe you reſuſe the meſſage which he brings, and carry not your ſelues to liking of al that what ſo euer ſhalbe told you of ſuch as beare a great ſhew and countenance, this was it that deceiued the people of God, they gaue eare to falſe teachers which led them to worſhip the workes of their owne hands.</p>
               <p>The Scribes and Phariſes ſeemed ſo graue and wiſe, that the people thought nothing good but what they allowed, they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together aplyable to beleeue, to doe, to ſpeake, and to thinke whatſoeuer the Phariſes willed them.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſaith <hi>bewane of falſe Prophets which come to you in ſheepes clothing, but inwardly they are rauening wolues.</hi> Mathew 7. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> therefore ſaith, <hi>Deerely beloued, beleeue not euery ſpirit, but trie the ſpirits whether they are of God, for many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> Iohn 11.4. and further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth vnto vs how wee ſhould trie them, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhall yee know the ſpirit of God, euery ſpirit that confeſſeth that Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh is of GOD. Againe heereby you
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:1975:79"/>may trie them, whoſoeuer tranſgreſſeth and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt hath not God, hee that continueth in the doctrine of Chriſt, he hath both the father and the ſonne, if there come any vnto you bringing not this doctrine receiue him not into your houſes, neither bid him God ſpeed, hereby Saint <hi>Paul</hi> requireth the <hi>Galathians</hi> to trie betweene him and their falſe Apoſtles, if any man, ſaith hee, preach vnto you otherwiſe then that you haue receiued let him be accurſed <hi>Gala.</hi> 1. <hi>Paul</hi> putteth <hi>Tymothie</hi> in minde, wherefore he left him at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that is to command ſome that they teach no other doctrine, and to warne both the teachers, and the hearers that they giue no heed to fables and genealogies which are endleſſe, which breed queſtions rather then godly edifying, which is by faith.</p>
               <p>Thus are the people of God called to trie the truth, to iudge betweene light and darkeneſſe, God hath made them the promiſe of the ſpirit, and hath left vnto them his word, they of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea</hi> when they heard the preaching of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſearched the Scriptures daily whether thoſe things were ſo as hee taught them, and many of them beloeued, ſo doe you: giue heed to inſtructions, and yet receiue not all things without proofe and triall, that they bee
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:1975:79"/>not contrary to the wholſome doctrine of the word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Keepe that which is good.</head>
               <p>VVHen you haue tried and found the truth, be conſtant and ſetled in it. A wauering minded-man is vnſtable in all his waies, follow the truth, and bee not carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with euery wind of doctrine: The diuell will come in the name of God, and change him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into an Angel of light, let him not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the loue of the truth from you: let him not remoue you from faith, &amp; a good conſcience. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne not like Swine vnto your mire: God hath purged your hearts, and made them cleane, and except they be preſerued, and kept occupied, the vncleane ſpirit will returne, and enter in, and dwell in you: ſo the laſt eſtate of you ſhalbe worſe then the firſt.</p>
               <p>Wee haue great cauſe to hearken diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the Apoſtle to keepe that is good, for wee ſee dailie great confuſion in all places, Sathan would faine intangle vs againe with the error of the wicked, and ſeeketh to draw vs from our ſtead-faſtneſſe: Now is the time wherein God maketh ſome trial of his ſeruants;
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:1975:80"/>now iniquity ſeekes to haue the vpper hand, they ſeduce people and ſay heere is Chriſt, there is Chriſt, heere is the Church, there is the Church, GOD giue vs his holy ſpirit, to guide vs in iudgement, that wee may diſcerne the truth from falſhood, and know the bleſſed and gracious will of GOD, that wee may walke in his waies, and ſerue him in reuerence and feare al the daies of our liues, for as their are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeeke Chriſt with an vnfained heart, ſo their are many that ſeeke Antichriſt, and as their bee many true profeſſors of the truth of God, ſo are their many diſpiſers of the ſame, this may wee ſee heere at home within this Realme, wee may ſee it, and mourne for it in our hearts.</p>
               <p>Their practiſes are opened, they haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out into open rebellion, to the breach of the peace both of God and man, they ſay with their lippes <hi>GOD ſaue King</hi> IAMES, yet they hold vp their ſwords againſt him, alas! what hath hee deſerued at their hands? hath hee not dealt mercifully, without crueltie, without ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bloud? GOD preſerue him that hee may long reigne ouer vs, and bring all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to confuſion: What pretence make they for this their doing, that heereby they ſeeke to haue religion reformed, thankes bee
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:1975:80"/>to God religion is reformed far better then euer our fathers knew of theſe many hundred yeeres, for if thoſe that liued before vs might haue ſeene and heard, as wee ſee and heare, they would haue reioyced and thought themſelues happy.</p>
               <p>But they would haue the Maſſe, what finde they or ſee they in it wherefore they ſhould ſo deſire it? <hi>Trie all things</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore examine and trie the Maſſe what wee doe learne by it, what doctrine, what godlineſſe in life, what comfort of ſaluation, it is dumbe and deadly ſeruice, it is the very key of their religion: the people are bound to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at it, yet they neither receiue any thing nor eate, nor heare, nor vnderſtand any thing, you are wiſe, you haue reaſon, you are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, be you Iudges herein, and iudge vprightly, for it is Gods cauſe: wil they call this the Lords ſupper? Is this the Sacrament of our redemption, is this that which <hi>Paul</hi> receiued of the Lord, and deliuered vnto the Church? is this the ſhewing forth of the Lords death till hee come?</p>
               <p>They paint their banner with the Croſſe and fiue wounds, why bring they theſe Armes againſt vs? Doe not wee beleeue the Croſſe
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:1975:81"/>of Chriſt, doe not we reioyce and comfort our heartes, by the remembrance of his woundes? do not we read, and ſhew forth to the people the ſtory of the paſſion? God knoweth it, and the world can witneſſe it, and they themſelues cannot denye it, but that we make this worke of our redemption, wrought, by the paſſion of our ſauiour Chriſt, the cheefe and principall rock and foundation of our faith: therefore ſay we with the Apoſtle, <hi>God forbid that we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in any thing, but in the croſſe of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi> nay rather they are become our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies becauſe we beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt crucified becauſe we ſay as Gods word teacheth, that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is the only aduocate to the father for our ſinnes, and that he hath with one ſuffering conſecrated for euer them that are ſanctified, and that the blood of Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, clenſeth vs from all ſinne, for this cauſe are they become our enemies.</p>
               <p>Let vs nothing feare their trecheries and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts: let vs keepe that is good, and hould it faſt vntill death: now that we haue taſted of the good word of God, and haue receiued the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of the Goſpell: Let vs not deſpiſe it, nor be weary of it, let vs pray to God that he wil eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the loue of his truth in vs, and that he wil
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:1975:81"/>open the eyes of their harts, &amp; bring them to be partakers of thoſe mercies which yet through ignorance they haue deſpiſed.</p>
               <p>Now when we haue tryed by the word which is truth, and which is error, what ſhall we them doe? keep that which is beſt, that is to ſay, as the truth, we muſt keepe and hold the truth, that is defend it with thy tongue, maintaine it with thy purſe, further it with thy labour: in danger and trouble, loſſe and diſpleaſure, come life, come death, thinke to doe as Chriſt did, ſeale the truth with his blood, ſo thou muſt ſeale it with thy blood, or elſe thou doſt not keepe it, but let it goe. Well did <hi>Paul</hi> put <hi>trie</hi> before <hi>chuſe,</hi> for he which tryeth may chuſe the beſt, but hee which chuſeth before he trye, taketh oft the worſt before the beſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now it followeth in this laſt <hi>admonition Abſtaine from all appearance of euill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter trye all things and keepe the beſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth abſtaine from all appearance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, as if he ſhould ſay, that is like to bee beſt which is ſo far from euill that it hath not the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of euil, &amp; that is like to be truth, which
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:1975:82"/>is farre from error, that it hath not the ſhew of error, whereby ſheweth that nothing ſhould be brought into the Church, or added to our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but that which is vndoubted truth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuſpition of error, it is not enough to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of our faith, but we muſt be aſſured of it, for religion is not built vppon doubts, but vpon knowledge.</p>
               <p>Heere we may maruell why <hi>Paul</hi> biddeth vs <hi>abſtaine from all appearance of euil:</hi> becauſe ſin and hereſie and ſuperſtition are hippocriſie, that ſinne hath the appearance of vertue, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie hath the appearance of truth, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath the appearance of religion: but this the Apoſtle doth note, that there is no ſinne, nor hereſie, nor ſuperſtition, but if the Viſor be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from it, it will appeare to be ſinne, and hereſie, and ſuperſtition, though at the firſt ſight, the Viſor doe make it ſeeme none, becauſe it couereth the euill, like a painted ſepulcher vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon wormes and rotten bones.</p>
               <p>Therefore keep your ſelues not only from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things which are euill, but alſo from all appearance of euill: offend not the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thy brother, that he may haue no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to thinke euil of thee: commit not adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and withdraw thy ſelfe from the company of ſuch vnthrifty, light, and ſuſpected perſons, be
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:1975:82"/>not like to them that are ſuch, lay not out thy money to vſury, nor doe any thing whereby o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may thinke euill of thee, beware of vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable conueyance of thy money, be no Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and leaue of to do any thing that may bring you into ſuſpition of Idolatry, giue not thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour unto any creature, which is proper vnto God, haue no fellowſhip with their workes, beare no ſhew, no appearance of liking their euill, goe not as they goe, liue not as they liue.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reprooueth the Galathians, ſaying yee obſerue dayes, and monethes and times, and yeares, I am in feare of you leaſt I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on you labour in vaine, Gal. 4. ſo doth he the Colloſſians 2. If ye bee dead with Chriſt from the ordinance of the world, why as though yee liue in the world are yee burthened with traditions, as touch not, taſt not, handle not: ſo doe the Idolaters, you ſhould not be like vnto them, they are the children of darkneſſe, you are the children of light, they will not be like you, and forſake their falſe Gods, why ſhould you then become like vnto them, &amp; forſake the God that made the heauens &amp; the earth? you cannot make them aſhamed of their errors, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the truth, why then ſhould you betray the truth, and be partakers with them in error?</p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:1975:83"/>
               <p>The King <hi>Antiochus</hi> ſent to Ieruſalem and to the Citties of Iuda, that they ſhould follow the ſtrange lawes of the country, many of them choſe rather to die, then to be defiled with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane things, and ſo to breake the holy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which God gaue them. <hi>Machab.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Therefore, abſtaine from all appearance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, be not like the wicked of this world, you are the ſalt of the earth, you ſhould not bee partners of their corruptions but powder and ſeaſon them: You are the light of the world, you may not be partakers of their darkneſſe, but lighten and guide them, deſſemble not, but ſerue God in the ſimplicity of your hearts, and in the ſight of the world, let it bee written in your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, what you thinke in your harts, why ſhould any man be aſhamed of Gods truth.</p>
               <p>Thus wee haue heard the care of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in teaching the Theſſolonians three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall duties of a Chriſtian, that is to reioyce, to pray, and to giue thankes, as hath beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared more at large, and withall for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereof in the verſes following foure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, which are as fortreſſes to hould vp thoſe duties that is, 1. quench not the ſpirit. 2. diſpiſe not prophecying. 3. trie and examine all things, and ſo hold faſt that which is good, the laſt is, abſtaine from all appearance of euill, which
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:1975:83"/>hath alſo beene declared: Now when the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had taught them theſe leſſons, and ſet them forward in the race of true Godlineſſe, like a good Paſtor which hath care ouer his flocke, he doth not thus leaue them, but withall giues them a friendly farwell in the next verſe ſaying, <hi>Now the very God of peace ſanctifie you throughout, and I pray God that your whole ſpirit and ſoule and body may bee kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>That is as if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, our God is the God of peace, hee giueth peace, and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe to his Church, he doth muſſell the Lion, maze the Tyrant, make blunt the Sword, and quench the Fire prepared againſt his ſeruants, hee giueth his Sonnes peace and quietneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them-ſelues, hee abhorreth diſcord and malice betweene bretheren: God is loue ſaith <hi>Iohn,</hi> and hee that dwelleth in loue, dwelleth in God, and God in him, hee that loueth not his brother, abideth in death, God hath made vs all members of one body, there is noe reſpect of perſons with him, noe difference of learned and vnlearned, wiſe or fooliſh, rich, or poore, his will is, that wee all ſhould be as one, of one mind, and that wee ſhould all thinke one thing, and ſpeake one thing, and that wee ſhould bee one
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:1975:84"/>fould vnder one ſhepheard, and with one mouth glorifie the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>For this peace Chriſt praied for, ſaying, <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie them through thy truth, bleſſe them, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all bitterneſſe, and ſwelling from among them, make them Citizens of thy heauenly Ieruſalem, that they may liue in peace, and loue one another, that they may bee one, as thou O Father art one in me, and I in thee.</hi> This peace we had need of, the peace of conſcience within our ſelues: of peace from the rage and fury of the world, and of peace of thoſe that are of Gods houſhold. Let vs ſeeke peace at the hand of God, and hee will ſtabliſh vs in the peace of the Goſpell, and ſo giue vs reſt and peace of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>Now that wee haue heard ſome profitable meanes declared, to keepe vs conſtant from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolting and turning backe, but to perſeuer ſtill foreward in our race: it is therefore needfull to conſider how eaſily man may bee deceiued, that ſo the better we may know the corruptions and weakeneſſe of our nature: and therefore what cauſe wee haue euer to walke warily, to take heed to ourſelues, and to pray vnto God, that he will incline our hearts vnto his teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: when I ſay man may be deceiued, I meane not children, or babes, or the ſimpler ſort of men onely, but the learned, the wiſe, the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:1975:84"/>the, Kings and princes of the world, the teachers and rulers of the people, as appeareth by diuers examples,</p>
               <p>To begin with <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt man, when hee was in Paradice, and made ruler ouer all beaſts of the field, and was full of graces and bleſſings of God, he ſoone departed from the counſell of God, and gaue eare to the Serpent, ſo eaſily was he deceued. Iſrael was as the apple of the Lords eye, a people whom the Lord loued, and to whom be gaue their hearts deſire, he deliuered them from <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and with an out-ſtretched arme led them through the red Sea: who would haue thought ſo great mercies would euer haue beene forgotten, or ſuch a people ſo well taught in the knowledge of God, and ſo often put in mind of their duties, ſhould either moſt part, or all of them turne from God? <hi>Moſes</hi> was but abſent a while, he went aſide to receiue the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the couenant, in the meane time they made vnto themſelues a molten Calfe, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped it, they offered vnto it and ſaid theſe be the Gods of Iſraell that haue brought thee out of the land of Egipt, ſo eaſily were the wiſeſt of them, and <hi>Aaron</hi> and the whole multitude de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
               <p>The Children after them forſooke the Lord and ſerued <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>Aſtroth,</hi> Iudg. 2. <hi>they haue
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:1975:85"/>turned their backs to me, and not their faces ſayth God by his prophet Ieremie</hi> 2. And was this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of ſome ſmall number? were they but few or of the baſer and ſimpler ſort? no they depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from God in great multitudes, with ful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and they warranted their doings by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and by the cuſtome of their fathers before them.</p>
               <p>The Prophet ſayth according to the number of thy Citties were thy Gods O Iudah, and to the number of thy ſtreetes O Ieruſalem, haue ye ſet vp altars of confuſion, euen Altars to burne Incenſe vnto Baal, <hi>Iere.</hi> 11.13, Againe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he ſayth, <hi>a great multitude euen all the people that dwelt in the land of Egipt in Phathros anſwered Ieremie ſaying, the word that thou hast ſpoken vnto vs in the name of the Lord wee wil not heare it of thee, but wee wil doe whatſoeuer thing goeth out of our mouth, as to burne incenſe to the Queene of heauen, and to poure out drinke offrings vnto her, as wee haue done, wee and our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, our Kinges and our Princes &amp;c. Iere.</hi> 44.16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus euen among that nation which God hath choſen vnto himſelfe the Apoſtacie was ſo great the departure from true holineſſe was ſo vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall that not only euery Citty, but euery ſtreet was defiled with their Idolatry, and beſides the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:1975:85"/>women with burnt-incenſe vnto other Gods. A great multitude yea all the people with one conſent cryed out againſt their prophets and preachers, refuſing to heare the word of God, but maintained their ſuperſtitions.</p>
               <p>The like may be ſayd of the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, they were wiſe men, they were learned and carried a great ſhew of holineſſe, yet they loued darkneſſe better then light, they were blind leaders of the blind, they diſpiſed the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandements of God, for their owne tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and not only they but <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate</hi> with the Gentiles, and people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell gathered themſelues together againſt the Lord and againſt his Chriſt.</p>
               <p>What ſhall I ſpeake of thoſe churches which the Apoſtles of Chriſt planted and watered, and confirmed in the truth, At Corinth <hi>Paul</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the goſpell, they reioyced at it gladly, hee thanked God on their behalfe that in all things they were made ritch in him, in all kind of ſpeaches, and in all knowledge.</p>
               <p>Yet ſoone after they abuſed the holy miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, they denied the reſurrection of the dead, they became carnall, and had enuying, and ſtrife &amp; contention among themſelues: The Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans alſo reioyced ſo much in him, that hee wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus of them, I beate you record that if it
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:1975:86"/>had beene poſſible you would haue plucked out your owne eyes, and to haue giuen them to me, yet they did not abide in the truth, but gaue eare to falſe Apoſtles, and ſo were decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <p>Therefore he reprooueth them ſaying, <hi>O yee fooliſh Galathians, who hath bewitched you that yee ſhould not obey the truth? Are yee ſo fooliſh that after yee haue begunne in the ſpirit yee would now be made perfect in the fleſh, yee did runne well, who did let you that you did not obey the truth, I am in feare of you leaſt.</hi> I <hi>haue beſtowed labour in vaine. Gal.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>This frailety and weakenes of our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſhewed it ſelfe forth, and hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all ages, we and our fathers haue gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, and haue followed after lyes, the Lord hath looked downe from heauen vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men to ſee if there were any that would vnderſtand and ſeeke God, but all are gone out of the way, they are all corrupt, there is none that doth good, no not one, ſayth the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> therefore the Apoſtle beſeecheth the Church of Theſſalonica that they ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vppon a ſure foundation, and that they be not remooued from the truth: he putteth them in mind what they haue heard, and of whom they haue heard it, and exhorteth them to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:1975:86"/>ſtedfaſt therein.</p>
               <p>Seeke therefore the kingdome of God, and the glory thereof, and ſeeke not your ſelues, weigh truth and falſehod in an indifferent bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, ſoe ſhall the heauier weight of the one, bewray the lightnes of the other, what thing in the world is ſoe maſſie, and ſoe weightie as the truth?</p>
               <p>Therefore as the prophet ſaith, <hi>If ye will heare the voyce of God, harden not your hearts,</hi> as they did in the prouocation, and as in the day of temptation in the wildernes: it is noe ſinne to yeilde vnto God, it is noe ſhame to lay apart all affections, and to change our mindes to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of all vngodlynes and imbracinge of true holineſſe.</p>
               <p>It is the part of a good Chriſtian and a wiſe man to know himſelfe, and to know the nature of his fleſh, which hee beareth about him, which fighteth alwayes ſo mightily againſt the ſpirit, and to know the waywardneſſe, and crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his heart, and the weakneſſe and vanity of his mind.</p>
               <p>Many are ſo farre from this, they thinke all their ability is of themſelues, I haue, ſaith one, iudgement, I haue the light of reaſon, I haue ſence, I haue vnderſtanding, and Counſell, and the ordering of mine owne way, thus ſay they
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:1975:87"/>that neither know God nor themſelues.</p>
               <p>The will and power to doe well is of God, and not of our ſelues, therefore we muſt humble our ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God, and acknowledge that we are nothing, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with S. <hi>Paul</hi> I <hi>know that in me,</hi> that is in my fleſh, <hi>dwelleth no good.</hi> Ro. 7. Againe it is not in him that willeth, not in him that run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but in God that ſheweth mercy. Ro. 9. Our Sauiour Chriſt ſayth, <hi>that which is borne of the fleſh is fleſh and that is borne of the ſpirit is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Iohn</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And God ſayth the immagination of man heart is euill from his youth <hi>Gene,</hi> 8. this is his ſaying and his iudgement of vs: this we find true, for our will is froward, and our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding blind: therefore ſayth the Prophet, <hi>O Lord I know that the way of man is not in himſelfe neither is it in man to walke and direct his ſteppes Iere</hi> 12. Againe the ſteppes of man are ruled by the Lord. How can a man then vnderſtand his owne way? <hi>Behold as the clay is in the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hand, ſo are you in my hand. O Iſraell,</hi> I <hi>mould you and frame you to my glory ſayth the Lord. Iere.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>When the Apoſtle putteth the Corinthians in mind of that good ſucceſſe, which God gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his miniſters, among them, hee ſayth, <hi>ſuch truſt haue we through Chriſt to God, not that wee
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:1975:87"/>are ſufficient of our ſelues, but our ſufficiency is of God. Cor.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſheweth this to his diſciples ſaying' <hi>I am the Vine, you are the branches, he that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in mee, and I in him bringeth forth much fruit for without mee yee can do nothing, Iohn</hi> 15. To the Colloſſians <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: <hi>It is God that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in you both the will and the deed euen of his good pleaſure. Colloſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>It is God that diſpoſeth our goings, and turneth our hearts as ſeemeth him best, hee is able to make of the ſtones in the Streetes children vnto Abraham, hee is able to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our ſtony heartes, and giue vs heartes of fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Conſideration heereof leadeth vs to ſeeke help and comfort by prayer at the hand of God, and becauſe wee ſtand in need of continuall help either to giue vs ſomthing that is good, or to deliuer vs from that is euill, the Apoſtle biddeth vs pray continually, for the eares of the Lord are open to the righteous, therfore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>aſke and it ſhall be giuen you, ſeeke and yee ſhall find, knoek and it ſhalbe opened vnto you Math.</hi> 7. Let vs therefore go boldly to the throne of grace that we may receiue mercy and find grace to help in time of need.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man according to Gods own heart prayed diuerſly, Open thou mine eyes, lighten
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:1975:88"/>my darkeneſſe, direct my feete into the way of peace: incline my heart O Lord, vnto thy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, eſtabliſh O God that which thou haſt wrought in vs, take not thy holy ſpirit from vs, bee thou our helper in trouble. O for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake vs not veterly! <hi>Dauid</hi> beeing a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of GOD found no way to attaine vnto knowledge of the will of God, vnleſſe God would open his vnderſtanding, and endue him with his ſpirit: faith is the gift of GOD, or elſe was the Apoſtles praier in vaine: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without the grace and mercy of GOD, wee can doe nothing to the ſetting forth of his glory, and to the attayning vnto our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſaith vnto the faithfull, <hi>Let your conuerſation bee in heauen, from whence you looke for the Sauiour, euen the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Yee were once darkeneſſe, but now yee are light in the LORD, walke as children of the light, approouing that which is pleaſing to the Lord.</hi> The great day of the Lord ſhalbe dreadful and come ſodainely vpon the wicked, but to you it ſhall not ſeeme ſodaine, which feare the LORD and put your truſt in him, and take all care to bee in readineſſe againſt his comming. Arme your ſelues therefore ſtrongly, the enemy is the diuell with all his force, your ſtrength ſtandeth not in your owne
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:1975:88"/>proweſſe or man-hood, but in the mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, put on therefore the breſt-plate of faith, and loue, hee that beleeueth ſhalbe ſaued, hee that abideth in loue, abideth in God, and whoſoeuer putteth his truſt in him ſhall neuer be confounded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the grace of God that bringeth ſaluation vnto all men hath appeared,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>and teacheth vs to deny vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and that wee ſhould liue ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world, looking for the bleſſed hope, and appearing of the glory of the great God, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, which gaue himſelfe for vs, that hee might redeeme vs from all vnrighteouſneſſe, and purge vs a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto himſelfe, zealous giuen to good workes.</hi> Titus 2.11.12.</p>
               <p>Therefore wee muſt not alwaies be children, but grow vp and increaſe, and profit more and more, for wee muſt neuer reſt walking till wee come to God, if we haue faith, wee muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from faith to faith, if wee haue loue, wee muſt abide and increaſe in loue, if wee haue zeale, wee muſt endeauour to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with zeale, if wee bee liberall to the Saints diſtreſſed, wee muſt double our libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallity, and that with cheerefulneſſe: if wee read the Scriptures, wee muſt goe on, and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:1975:89"/>continue in praier, ſo wee muſt ſtill increaſe till wee come to perfection, <hi>Let vs bee led for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>vnto perfection.</hi> Hebr. 6.1.</p>
               <p>As God hath ordained a heauen for all true faithful Pilgrims, ſo hath he appointed a way to come to it, which way hee that trauaileth not ſhall neuer come to the end of his race, for there be many wrong waies, as there are many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but there is but one right way, as there is but one truth.</p>
               <p>To knit vp this part with that warning and exhortation of the Apoſtle ſaying, <hi>Let vs drawe neere with a true heart in aſſurance of faith, ſprinckled in our hearts from an euill conſcience, and washed in bodie with pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, let vs hold the poſſeſſion of the hope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wauering,</hi> for hee is faithfull that promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for if wee ſinne willingly after that wee haue receiued the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſinnes, but a fearefull looking for iudgement and violent fire, which ſhall deuoure the aduerſaries. Hebr. 10.22.23.26.</p>
               <p>So it cannot be that they which were lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and haue taſted of the heauenly gift and were become pertakers of the holy ghoſt, and haue taſted of the good word of God, and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:1975:89"/>the powers of the world to come, and they fall away, ſhould be renued againe into repentance crucifying to themſelues the ſonne of God a freſh. <hi>Heb</hi> 6.4.5.6.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle therfore admoniſheth the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to haue diſcretion in their walking, ſaying, <hi>Take heed that y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e walke circumſpectly, not as vnwiſe, but as wiſe, redeeming the time becauſe the daies are euill,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore bee yee not vnwiſe, but vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what the will of the Lord is.</p>
               <p>Speaking vnto your ſelues in pſalmes and hyms, and ſpirituall ſongs, ſinging and making melody to the Lord in your hearts.</p>
               <p>Giuing thankes alwaies for all things vnto God the Father, in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now as al theſe parts of Scriptures going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this Booke are needfull &amp; ſpecial means to teach all true Chriſtians to walke the right way towards heauen, whereby we may bee able not only to walke aright, but alſo to make a right and ſound reaſon of our religion agreeable to the word of God, a ſound reaſon of our faith, and a ſound reaſon of our ſaluation agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſame word of truth, and ſo to continue to the end of our race, then ſhall
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:1975:90"/>wee bee made happy for euermore, and be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured happy in the great day of our Lord, by our Lord: and, <hi>you bleſſed of my Father inherite the Kingdome of heauen which is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you from the beginning,</hi> which kingdom grant vs Lord for Chriſt Ieſus ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1975:90"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
